<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[strugee.net blog - 'development' category]]></title><description><![CDATA[strugee.net blog - 'development' category]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/category/development</link><generator>stratic-indexes-to-rss</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2017 19:04:56 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://strugee.net/blog/category/development/index.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><copyright><![CDATA[© Copyright 2012-2017 Alex Jordan. Available under the GNU Affero GPL.]]></copyright><webMaster><![CDATA[Alex Jordan <alex@strugee.net>]]></webMaster><item><title><![CDATA[How I accidentally started maintaining a social network with thousands of users]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>As some of my readers (particularly Recursers) know, a couple of weeks ago I became an Invited Expert at the <a href="https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg">Social Working Group</a> at the <a href="https://www.w3.org/">W3C</a> (World Wide Web Consortium). The W3C is a standards body. That means it's responsible for defining things like how things work on the web, such as how web pages are styled using CSS and how web developers can protect their apps from security vulnerabilities using <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/CSP3/">Content Security Policy</a>.</p>
<p>My first thought when I got the email that my application had been accepted was, "<em><strong>WHOOOOOOOOO!</strong></em>" It was probably one of the most thrilling moments of my whole life. My second thought was, "how in the <em>world</em> did I get here!?" The truth is, it was almost an accident.</p>
<p>It started when I got involved in the <a href="http://pump.io">pump.io</a> project. pump.io, for those who haven't heard me talk about this endlessly (e.g. at RC), is a decentralized social network. That means that there can be multiple servers run by different people that are part of the social network, but the users on those servers can interact with each other in just the same way they could if it was just one big centralized server[1]. I first got involved in the pump.io project in August 2015. I was experimenting with different social networking software and decided to <a href="https://pump.strugee.net/">deploy</a> pump.io on my server. When I did I realized that pump... well, it didn't work very well. The web UI was kinda basic[2], everything was pretty buggy, and there were a lot of problems with the overall user experience. In fact, I know the exact day I set up pump.io (August 12th) because all throughout the experience <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/issues/1093">I</a> <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/issues/1094">was</a> <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/issues/1095">filing</a> <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/issues/1096">bugs</a> on things needing improvement. It was a shame, I thought, because this software seemed really neat. I thought it had a lot of potential.</p>
<p>After about two weeks it became clear that there was no activity in the upstream pump.io project. So after some deliberation, I ended up forking it (briefly). You can watch <a href="https://media.libreplanet.org/u/libreplanet/m/pump-io-the-federated-extensible-social-network/">this talk</a> around 16:00 to hear me talk about this a bit, though to be honest it's kind of just a footnote in the project's history. In the end Evan Prodromou, pump.io's author, ended up handing off some commit rights to community members.</p>
<p>Well, I thought, that was the end of that. Everything's smooth sailing from here on out! There were some big problems, though: the people who now had commit rights all were involved in other things and, more importantly, none of them knew JavaScript or Node.js! This makes me chuckle to this day, honestly.</p>
<p>So I started triaging issues. When people sent Pull Requests, I'd review them since it seemed like no one else was going to do it. <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/pull/1114">#1114</a> was, as far as I can tell (or remember), the very first of these "unofficial" PR reviews. I kept going; I even reviewed Menno Vossen's <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/pull/1136">epic PR which fixed all the tests</a> (fixing the tests being a feat which, having tried to start that work myself, I am to this day in awe of and <em>incredibly</em> thankful for). For that last one in particular, you'll note that <em>I</em> merged it, not Chris Webber. At some point in January(?), he asked me in <code>#pump.io</code> on IRC if I'd like write access to the repository, to which I said (paraphrased) "heck yes!" So he made it happen.</p>
<p>I never really intended for that to happen. However, I <em>was</em> the one doing almost all of the work. After a while it just made sense. This is what, among other things, I find so incredible about freedom-respecting software: you can just <em>do</em> things. I didn't ask anyone for permission to do those reviews. I just saw the need for a reviewer, and decided I'd help out.</p>
<p>Fast-forward to today, and I'm now an owner of the pump.io organization on GitHub. I make technical decisions about what to prioritize and what should go into pump.io core. I do a lot of the day-to-day work running the project, too, and setting up technical and policy infrastructure (with a lot of help from the community, of course, plus input from Evan). That, too, just made sense, as did my becoming an Invited Expert - I was pretty deeply engaged with the SocialWG's <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/">ActivityPub</a> specification already since it's based on the pump.io protocol, and I was really excited about said protocol being standardized. So I was participating pretty heavily and I think it just made sense to people in the Working Group for me to join. In fact, that also kinda happened by accident. I couldn't get edit access to the W3C wiki so we were speculating in <code>#social</code> on the W3C IRC server that it might be because I wasn't a "W3C member" or something. So some people at W3C were pinging the sysops team, etc., trying to mark me as a "trusted" user when someone - <a href="https://www.w3.org/People/Sandro/">Sandro Hawke</a>, I believe - said, "the other option is for you to just join the Working Group." To which I said, "well, but I'd have to join as an Invited Expert, and I don't think I qualify as an expert." Chris Webber's response? "You're just as much of an expert as me when I joined!"</p>
<p>tl;dr how in the world did I get here? I tried some software and got annoyed at it, so I just kind of <em>"did some stuff"</em> that led to me doing code reviews. That led to me getting involved in the decentralized social web which led to me <em>"doing some more stuff"</em> that got me involved in standards. Then because of that, I tried to edit a wiki and ended up being invited to apply as a W3C Invited Expert.</p>
<p>I mean, what the hell? Honestly. I can't emphasize enough that I didn't plan ANY of this. It just sort of... happened. And that, I think, is what's so cool about the free software community. It isn't about who you are, where you come from, or what your goals are. It's only about, do you show up? Do you show up and do awesome stuff?</p>
<p>I showed up, kind of by accident, and I now run a decentralized social network with thousands of users called pump.io.</p>
<p>What will happen if <em>you</em> show up?</p>
<p><em>Thanks so much to <a href="https://github.com/anjakefala">Anja</a> and <a href="http://jvns.ca/">Julia</a> for providing feedback on a draft version of this post.</em></p>
<p>[1]: I really hope this explanation makes sense and if it doesn't, I apologize - I use diagrams to explain this in real life.</p>
<p> [2]: Still is, but that should improve now that the technical debt work I've been focusing on for the past year is now <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/express-4.x-in-pump.io-core">basically done</a>!</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/05/pump.io-accident</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/05/pump.io-accident</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[pump.io]]></category><pubDate>Sat, 13 May 2017 03:51:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[pump.io 4.0 in beta]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>pump.io 4.0.0 is officially in beta! Whooo!</p>
<h1>Highlights</h1>
<p>This is a positively <em>huge</em> release, and I'm so excited to share it with the community. Some highlights:</p>
<ul>
<li>Express 4.x - I wrote about the significance of this change <a href="http://pump.io/blog/2017/03/express-4.x-in-pump.io-core">here</a>, but suffice to say that this significantly improves security, performance, and future maintainability</li>
<li>Performance and correctness improvements to the web UI's JavaScript</li>
<li>Better administrative experience, including the ability to specify configuration via environment variables</li>
<li>Better interoperability with the <a href="https://indieweb.org">IndieWeb</a></li>
</ul>
<h1>Upgrading</h1>
<p>The upgrade to Express 4.x and the improvements to configuration loading have the potential to break <em>some</em> existing pump.io installations, although 95% of installs should be completely unaffected. If you want to help test this beta, please set aside extra time as necessary to perform this upgrade - full documentation can be found on <a href="https://pumpio.readthedocs.io/en/latest/upgrades/3.x-to-4.x.html">ReadTheDocs</a>.</p>
<p>As always, this release will follow our normal <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/wiki/Release-cycle">release cycle</a>, which means that the stable 4.0.0 release will go out in about a month.</p>
<h1>Test days</h1>
<p>Due to the complexity of this upgrade, we've decided to have some test days during the beta where we upgrade prominent nodes for a day, then downgrade them again. This will help expose problems earlier and make the upgrade smoother for everyone. So far Jason Self, who runs <a href="https://datamost.com/">Datamost</a>, has volunteered for this - if you're interested in joining him, please <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/wiki/Community">get in touch</a>!</p>
<p>Happy hacking!</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/04/pump.io-4.0-in-beta</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/04/pump.io-4.0-in-beta</guid><category><![CDATA[pump.io]]></category><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2017 21:03:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Getting on board with configuration management]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>For a long while I've really disliked configuration management. This mostly stemmed from my experience <a href="https://github.com/strugee/steevie/blob/3069f53ee82c6b1709f22285b71ccdc0e5e0bced/apache-config/apache-config.pp">managing Apache via Puppet</a>, which I found indirect and unnecessary - the only reason I did this was basically to get version control. In fact, I even started a project called <a href="https://github.com/strugee/bindslash">bindslash</a> which I literally described as "not configuration management".</p>
<p>However, last Thursday, steevie (my primary server) crashed <em>again</em>. So I went into a fallback DigitalOcean VM I'd set up the last time this had happened and updated stuff. I presented my <a href="https://strugee.net/presentation-pumpio/libreplanet/">LibrePlanet slides</a> from that. And eventually I bit the bullet and set up a secondary email server which, to my great surprise, has not received a flood of spam yet (though I'm sure it will at some point).</p>
<p>The whole ordeal really made me understand the benefit of configuration management. I would've spent less time and been less stressed if I could just plug in a config management system to get a useful failover system. So as of today, I'm on board with configuration management, and bindslash is dead.</p>
<p>I still kinda hate Puppet, so I think I'll try out Ansible and <em>maybe</em> Chef. Ansible's agentless model in particular probably makes a lot of sense for my needs. It also makes me sad to kill bindslash, since I still think it would be a useful project and there's definitely a place for it in the world. But I no longer have any reason to work on it, so I'm just going to stop pretending I'll ever finish it. If anyone is interested in that approach, talk to me and I'll happily give you the name, the repo, my thoughts on its design, etc.</p>
<p>Anyway. Now to set up outbound mail on the failover VM.</p>
<p>*big sigh*</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/getting-on-board-with-configuration-management</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/getting-on-board-with-configuration-management</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[sysadmin]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2017 20:59:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Express 4.x in pump.io core]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>So I thought I'd take a moment to announce that the upgrade from Express 2.x to Express 4.x is <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/pull/1208">finally complete</a>! I fixed up the last couple test failures last Wednesday, and the branch got merged on Thursday.</p>
<h1>A long time coming</h1>
<p>Believe it or not, the work to do this upgrade started almost an entire <em>year</em> ago. Express 2.x has been outdated and unmaintained for a long time now, so upgrading has been a high priority. However, it wasn't as simple as adjusting a version number - there were a staggering number of changes that needed to be made due to Express deprecating, removing, and changing things around. One of the most significant problems was the fact that the old template system that we used, utml, was not compatible with Express 3.x and above. That meant that we had to rewrite every single template into a modern language - an effort that resulted in <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/pull/1170">over a thousand lines changed</a>!</p>
<p>However, the time for Express 4.x has finally arrived. With that and some other trivial version bumps, I'm proud to announce that pump.io is fully up-to-date in terms of dependencies with only three, non-critical exceptions. Whooooo!</p>
<h1>Immediate benefits</h1>
<p>There are a lot of reasons this is immediately awesome:</p>
<ol>
<li>Express 4.x fixes significant performance problems that existed in Express 3.x</li>
<li>Relatedly, Express 4.x fixes some security problems present in 3.x</li>
<li>The fact that our dependencies are <em>finally</em> up-to-date means that we can (and do!) now make use of <a href="https://greenkeeper.io/">Greenkeeper</a> and the <a href="https://nodesecurity.io/orgs/pumpio/projects/32213bb8-f9a6-4dd0-8fc6-5caa8ea5f8fc">Node Security Platform</a> to automatically track dependencies to make sure they're up-to-date and not introducing security vulnerabilities</li>
</ol>
<p>That last one is particularly significant. Greenkeeper and NSP will continuously monitor the project's dependencies and automate away a lot of the pain that's associated with keeping pump.io up-to-date. Everyone will get a more secure and stable codebase because of this setup.</p>
<h1>Looking forward</h1>
<p>The Express 4.x upgrade is a big change, and it's definitely possible that stuff has broken. We want to make sure that breakage doesn't make it into production. This change went into pump.io 4.0, which will go through our normal <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/wiki/Release-cycle">release cycle</a>. That means it'll be in beta for a month before being released. As a part of that, <a href="https://jxself.org/">Jason Self</a> - who's kind enough to administer <a href="https://datamost.com/">Datamost</a> - has agreed to have a test day where Datamost upgrades to the beta for a day, then downgrade it again. This test day will give us much wider exposure than we would've gotten otherwise, which will be incredibly valuable feedback in the effort to identify and fix regressions. We haven't set a date yet, but if you'd like to join Jason in helping us find bugs, please get in touch with <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/wiki/Community">the community</a>. We'd love your help.</p>
<p>Beyond the immediate release, though, there's still things to look forward to. Express 4.x gives us a better way to structure routing code, and a refactor to use this structure <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/issues/1232">is planned</a>. There's a lot of room for improvement. But really, the most important benefit is this: technical debt is a far less pressing issue than before. That means that we can shift focus and spend more time fixing user-facing bugs, adding useful features, and generally improving the experience for our users. I couldn't be more excited.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/express-4.x-in-pump.io-core</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/express-4.x-in-pump.io-core</guid><category><![CDATA[pump.io]]></category><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2017 20:22:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Default-secure systems]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>So recently I presented on <a href="https://strugee.net/presentation-operational-security/">operational security</a> and then started in on the nightmare that is <a href="https://strugee.net/presentation-https-deployment/">HTTPS deployment</a>. And like I did with <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/01/new-programming-language-part-i-handlers">language-level security</a> (I <em>still</em> need to write part 2 of that post), I thought to myself, this is so difficult. Why isn't there something that will do this for me? That's what my latest project is.</p>
<p>Here's the tl;dr:</p>
<pre><code>type(app)
=&gt; Django/Express.js/etc. app
secure_system(app)
=&gt; Docker image
</code></pre>
<p>Or in other words, you'll be able to take an existing web app that you've written, run it through this system, and it will spit out a complete, reasonably-secure system image.</p>
<p>Let's step back.</p>
<h1>The status quo</h1>
<p>Currently, when a developer wants to run a web app, they can either use something like Heroku, which is fully manged, or a VM from DigitalOcean or Amazon EC2 or something. There are a variety of reasons you might not want to use Heroku, but the only other option is a VM - and with a VM, you get a bare system where you have to set up everything from scratch. Lots of developers just don't have the operational experience to do this properly or securely, but it's not like they can go and get an operations team to do it for them. So they end up with systems that may have active security problems as well as little to no defense-in-depth mitigations for when security inevitably fails. Security is just another operational concern the developer has no time and no expertise to deal with, so it just doesn't happen. The developer spins up a VM, gets it to where it "works" and then moves on. <strong>This is not good enough.</strong></p>
<p>I don't want to create a false dichotomy, though: this is not the developer's fault. Everyone has conflicting priorities and it's unreasonable to expect the developer to spend lots of time learning to administrate systems so that they can then spend even more time, you know, administering systems. The problem is that there just isn't enough options available - we have to provide something better.</p>
<h1>A middle ground</h1>
<p>This is what my project is about: creating a middle ground between fully-managed deployment platforms and barebones, setup-from-scratch VMs.</p>
<p>This project rests on the idea that operational security (at least, in a single-server, single-admin context) flows from consistency, least privilege, and proactive, defense-in-depth security measures. Here are a couple core design goals:</p>
<ol>
<li>Meet developers where they are. Configuration management like Puppet is a great way to enforce consistency, but it adds a level of indirection and is just another thing that people running hobbyist projects don't have time to learn.</li>
<li>Tight integration with apps - this excludes more obscure types of web applications, but gives us a better footing to set up a solid deployment environment. It also may let us integrate more tightly with things like Content Security Policy in the future.</li>
<li>Support virtual hosting. The ability to run multiple apps while paying for a single VM is a compelling reason people go with VMs over e.g. Heroku - we won't be helping anyone if we leave this out.</li>
<li>Upgrades are optional. Any system image created by this project will present a system that is organized and can be maintained and modified by hand without breaking everything.</li>
<li>Upgrades are possible. Tight app framework integration will aid with putting data into well-known places that can be backed up and migrated to a new image generated by a newer version of this system.</li>
<li>Not designed for "real" production environments. Any project that has a dedicated operations person should not be using this; they should be rolling their own custom environments with something like Puppet. Accordingly, there won't be compromises in security in favor of flexibility - it's designed to cover 75% of cases "pretty well", which is still better than the status quo for smaller projects (almost 100% of cases don't have any security at all).</li>
</ol>
<p>I'd also like to highlight one really important decision: the output is complete system images. Probably at first this will mean Docker containers but this could easily be turned into VM images. This is a critical part of the design because it allows us to make broad, sweeping changes - for example, preferring system components written in memory-safe languages, replacing OpenSSL with LibreSSL, or creating systemd unit files that lock down service runtime environments to reduce the impact of a compromise. These improvements aren't possible unless we control the whole system. And because upgrades are optional but possible, the developer can get security improvements by "just" upgrading a component that they use, in the same way that they'd upgrade a library or something, as opposed to security being a continuous process they have to worry about. Again, obviously not perfect - but much better than the status quo.</p>
<p>I hope to have a MVP out Real Soon Now™. But in the meantime, if you have thoughts, feel free to reach out.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/default-secure-systems</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/default-secure-systems</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 20:59:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[How I passed 2k GitHub contributions]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>So the other day I logged into GitHub and saw something crazy:</p>
<p><img src="/images/github-2k-contributions.jpg" alt="Screenshot of my GitHub contribution graph showing 2,054 contributions over the past year"></p>
<p>How in the hell did I end up with that many contributions? Well, I think I know why - it happened because of a couple related, small habits I have. I thought I'd share them with everyone else as a sort of trivia - maybe you can adopt these habits too! (Although hopefully because you think they're good ideas, not because you just want to make yourself look cool on GitHub.)</p>
<h2>Fix typos</h2>
<p>If projects are freedom-respecting, that means that anyone is welcome to contribute if they're able to offer something valuable. How many times have you seen a typo in some docs? GitHub makes it super, super easy to fix these (just click the pencil icon in the upper-right of GitHub file views), and they're a fantastic way to contribute a little back to projects. Even if you aren't reading docs on GitHub, it often doesn't take that much time to find where they're hosted (which is frequently GitHub anyway). Really good docs will even have a link to their source right on the generated page.</p>
<p>So whenever I see a typo, I send a Pull Request. It's become an automatic response to seeing something that needs fixing, and is pretty routine for me nowadays.</p>
<p>Oftentimes there are changes that aren't as easy as a typo, but are still super easy to fix. Take <a href="https://github.com/Homebrew/brew/pull/1634">this Homebrew PR</a> - I authored it on a tablet and it took me under 3 minutes to make the suggested change[1]. That's not a lot of effort, and it'll help lots of people looking for the Homebrew change log. The next time you find yourself thinking "it kinda sucks that..." ask yourself - can I fix this myself? And if you can, go for it! Even if you screw up, I promise most projects will want to help you out instead of making fun of you[2] - as someone who runs several freedom-respecting projects, I know that getting new contributors is very, very valuable and because of that I'll do a lot to make contributing a good experience. I would encourage everyone to, as Mike McQuaid puts it in that Homebrew PR, "be the change you want to see in the world."</p>
<p> [1]: of course, that's partly because I'm pretty good at git and grok things like <code>rebase -i</code>. But even if that's not you and it would take you longer, it sounds like a great opportunity to improve your git skills to me!</p>
<p> [2]: I feel obligated to point out that not every project is like this - there are some projects that have a terrible culture (*coughcough*Linuxkernel*cough*). Screw them. They're not that common in my experience and it's their loss, anyway. Don't let them deter you from trying to improve things outside of their bubble of suck.</p>
<h2>File issues</h2>
<p>I just talked about making small changes whenever you see something you can improve with a couple minutes' time. But what if you're in a hurry, or it would take longer?</p>
<p>Filing issues is a super easy way to solve this. Get into the habit of filing issues for everything that irks you[3] - you're not allowed to say "such-and-such a project sucks because it's buggy!" when you haven't told the developers about the bug you're experiencing!</p>
<p>Filing issues also takes very little time and is super helpful to the developer. Probably a lot of the people who read this blog are software developers, so I'm betting you can understand how great it is to receive an issue that gives you lots of details that you can then use to fix a bug or a design problem. So why not give the gift of issues? Just make sure to search for duplicates! (This accounts for a significant amount of those 2,000 contributions on my GitHub profile. Over the course of my time on GitHub, I've filed 619 issues, 438 of which were on other people's projects. Of course, that's just on GitHub - I also do this frequently <em>outside</em> of GitHub.)</p>
<p>Again, every time you find yourself saying, "why doesn't it..." or "I wish it..." or "it's so annoying when...", let the developer know! You'll help them make their project better.</p>
<p>  [3]: this is not to suggest that you file ridiculous issues that don't really say anything or just complain. But a focused bug report describing something concrete that's problematic is awesome.</p>
<h2>Publish by default</h2>
<p>This is the last and biggest habit I have that I think led to those 2k contributions: I publish everything by default, no matter what. It doesn't matter how bad or hacky or ugly I think a software project is, I just publish it. Because honestly, why not?</p>
<p>Keeping projects public doesn't get in anyone's way. It's not like someone will look at your GitHub and be <em>annoyed</em> that you give so much software to the world. And there's even a chance that your hacky script may actually be <em>useful</em> to someone. Even if I think a project is "bad" I'll still publish it because the reality is that no one is going to go around GitHub specifically trying to find people to make fun of.</p>
<p>Publishing projects also gives me incentive to clean them up - write a README, write tests, and keep a change log (if relevant). My standards are higher because I know all my work is all in the open - not because I'm afraid of other people telling me I'm doing it wrong, but because I want to create high quality code that has a better chance of being useful to the wider community.</p>
<h2>In summary</h2>
<p>All of these habits are related. The tl;dr is this: engage by default. Get used to being involved instead of shrugging off a problem and moving on. Put your work out there for other people to see. The open source/freedom-respcting software community belongs to everyone - and that means we can all contribute to improving it. We just have to start.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/how-i-passed-2k-github-contributions</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/how-i-passed-2k-github-contributions</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 17:46:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[From static to Stratic - part 1]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>So a couple days ago I published <code>generator-stratic@1.0.0-beta.1</code> to npm. Since Stratic is now officially in beta, I thought I'd write up a guide to converting a regular, static site to a Stratic-powered blog.</p>
<p>Each step in this blog post (part 1 of 2[?]) will take you closer to having a fully-functional blog, but because of Stratic's decoupled design, you can work through them at your own pace. Each step will leave you with a functional environment (i.e. nothing will be "broken" such that you can't work on your website anymore).</p>
<p>You can see the steps in this post in action at <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/static-to-stratic">straticjs/static-to-stratic</a>. Each commit corresponds to a step in this post.</p>
<p>Let's get started!</p>
<h2>Initial setup</h2>
<p>The site we'll be converting is currently pretty simple. It has an <code>index.html</code> and a <code>projects.html</code>. Each of these includes <code>/css/main.css</code> and <code>/js/main.js</code>. Also, they both have a navigation section and a footer that are duplicated across each page. Each time Alyssa P. Hacker - the website's owner - makes a change to these (for example to fix the copyright year in the footer), she has to change both HTML files. The best way for her to add a new page will be to copy an existing HTML file and then change it. This is a little unideal.</p>
<p>Alyssa tracks her website on GitHub (in the example repository mentioned above). Here are links for the <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/static-to-stratic/blob/18a7a7da03a2f84f525f0b699a43005067428199/index.html"><code>index.html</code></a> and the <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/static-to-stratic/blob/18a7a7da03a2f84f525f0b699a43005067428199/projects.html"><code>projects.html</code></a> we'll be working with.</p>
<p>Here's a visual of the project layout:</p>
<pre><code>% tree .
.
├── css
│&nbsp;&nbsp; └── main.css
├── index.html
├── js
│&nbsp;&nbsp; └── main.js
└── projects.html

2 directories, 4 files
</code></pre>
<p>When Alyssa needs to preview her website, she manually runs <code>http-server .</code>.</p>
<p>Since Alyssa uses GitHub she publishes her website on GitHub Pages, so her website is in the <code>master</code> branch of her git repository. (Here we're assuming that the repository is called <code>aphacker.github.io</code> or something, instead of <code>static-to-stratic</code>.)</p>
<p>In addition to adding blog support, we'll improve Alyssa's website by reducing duplication while still allowing her to publish to GitHub Pages.</p>
<h2>Step 1 - adding gulp</h2>
<p>Before we do anything else, we need to add a build system. Stratic is designed to work with <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/">gulpjs</a>, so that's the one we'll be using.</p>
<p>Adding gulp is super easy. First, we need to create a <code>package.json</code>, so we do <code>npm init</code>:</p>
<pre><code>% npm init
This utility will walk you through creating a package.json file.
It only covers the most common items, and tries to guess sensible defaults.

See `npm help json` for definitive documentation on these fields
and exactly what they do.

Use `npm install &lt;pkg&gt; --save` afterwards to install a package and
save it as a dependency in the package.json file.

Press ^C at any time to quit.
name: (static-to-stratic)
version: (1.0.0)
description: Personal website of Alyssa P. Hacker
entry point: (index.js)
test command:
git repository: (https://github.com/straticjs/static-to-stratic.git)
keywords:
author: Alyssa P. Hacker &lt;alyssaphacker@example.net&gt;
license: (ISC) AGPL-3.0+
About to write to /Users/alex/Development/static-to-stratic/package.json:

{
  "name": "static-to-stratic",
  "version": "1.0.0",
  "description": "Personal website of Alyssa P. Hacker",
  "main": "index.js",
  "scripts": {
    "test": "echo \"Error: no test specified\" &amp;&amp; exit 1"
  },
  "repository": {
    "type": "git",
    "url": "git+https://github.com/straticjs/static-to-stratic.git"
  },
  "author": "Alyssa P. Hacker &lt;alyssaphacker@example.net&gt;",
  "license": "AGPL-3.0+",
  "bugs": {
    "url": "https://github.com/straticjs/static-to-stratic/issues"
  },
  "homepage": "https://github.com/straticjs/static-to-stratic#readme"
}


Is this ok? (yes) yes
</code></pre>
<p>A couple things to note here: in general, the defaults are fine to accept. We've provided a description and an author, but these are optional since this isn't actually going to be published on the npm registry. They're just kind of nice to have.</p>
<p>The same goes for the license, which in this case is the <a href="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/agpl-3.0.en.html">Affero GPL 3.0 or above</a> - however, as the copyright holder you are of course free to <a href="https://choosealicense.com/">choose whatever license</a> you want. (Or no license, although I'd discourage you from doing that.)</p>
<p>Once we have a <code>package.json</code>, we can go ahead and install gulp and another module we'll need, <code>ecstatic</code>:</p>
<pre><code>% npm install --save-dev gulp ecstatic
</code></pre>
<p>If you haven't used gulp previously, you'll also need to install <code>gulp-cli</code>:</p>
<pre><code>% npm install -g gulp-cli
</code></pre>
<p>At this point, we'll need to move some files around. Now that we have a build system, we can organize our repository however we want instead of putting stuff exactly where we want it in production.</p>
<p>You can do this however you want. The organization that you'll find most projects using, though, is to put stuff in a <code>src</code> directory. Let's make that right now.</p>
<pre><code>% mkdir src
% git mv *.html src
% git mv css src/styles
% git mv js src/scripts
</code></pre>
<p>Finally, create a file named <code>gulpfile.js</code> and put the following in it:</p>
<pre><code>var gulp = require('gulp'),
    http = require('http'),
    ecstatic = require('ecstatic');

gulp.task('build:html', function() {
    gulp.src('src/*.html')
        .pipe(gulp.dest('dist'));
});

gulp.task('build:css', function() {
    gulp.src('src/styles/*')
        .pipe(gulp.dest('dist/css'));
});

gulp.task('build:js', function() {
    gulp.src('src/scripts/*')
        .pipe(gulp.dest('dist/js'));
});

gulp.task('watch', ['build'], function() {
    gulp.watch('src/*.html', ['build:html']);
    gulp.watch('src/styles/*', ['build:css']);
    gulp.watch('src/scripts/*', ['build:js']);
});

gulp.task('serve', ['watch'], function() {
        http.createServer(
                ecstatic({ root: __dirname + '/dist' })
        ).listen(8080);
});

gulp.task('build', ['build:html', 'build:css', 'build:js']);

gulp.task('default', ['serve']);
</code></pre>
<p>This gives us a pretty good starting point. This gulpfile defines a couple tasks that simply copy source files into <code>dist</code>. The <code>watch</code> task watches for changes and rebuilds when they occur, and the <code>serve</code> task starts up a server, replacing Alyssa's usage of <code>http-server</code>. This provides exactly the same workflow as before: Alyssa runs one command and then she can look at her site on <code>localhost:8080</code>. You can use different task names if you want (for example, <code>html</code> instead of <code>build:html</code>, etc.), but these are what <code>generator-stratic</code> gives you.</p>
<p>However, there's one problem: Alyssa can't deploy her site anymore. If she pushed like this, visitors would have to visit e.g. <code>https://aphacker.github.io/src/projects</code> instead of <code>https://aphacker.github.io/projects</code>! That's no good.</p>
<p>In order to rectify this, we'll create a new git branch, <code>src</code>. <code>src</code> will contain the source files, and we'll put the final, built site in <code>master</code>, which is what's served by GitHub Pages. So:</p>
<pre><code>% git checkout -b src
% git push --set-upstream origin src
</code></pre>
<p>Great. Now, we need to add something to put the built files (i.e. the contents of <code>dist</code>) in <code>master</code>. We'll use the <code>gh-pages</code> module for this. First install it and a dependency we'll need:</p>
<pre><code>% npm install --save-dev gh-pages gulp-util
</code></pre>
<p>Next, make it available in the gulpfile by adding a line at the end of <code>require()</code> statements:</p>
<pre><code>var gulp = require('gulp'),
    http = require('http'),
    ecstatic = require('ecstatic');
</code></pre>
<p>And finally, add a <code>deploy</code> task somewhere in the gulpfile:</p>
<pre><code>gulp.task('deploy', ['build'], function(done) {
    ghpages.publish(path.join(__dirname, 'dist'), { logger: gutil.log, branch: 'master' }, done);
});
</code></pre>
<p>Now whenever Alyssa wants to deploy a new version of her website, she just runs <code>gulp deploy</code> and it'll be taken care of for her. (ProTip™: change the default branch to <code>src</code> on GitHub. That way visitors and new clones see the source files, not the build files generated by a program.)</p>
<p>The very last thing we need to do is add a <code>.gitignore</code> file since we're installing Node modules and have a build directory now. We'll just use GitHub's, adding a line for <code>dist/</code> at the end:</p>
<pre><code>% curl https://raw.githubusercontent.com/github/gitignore/master/Node.gitignore &gt; .gitignore
% echo "\ndist/\n" &gt;&gt; .gitignore
</code></pre>
<p>Now we've got a functionally equivalent development setup based on gulp. Success!</p>
<h2>Step 2: converting HTML to Pug</h2>
<p>The next step is to convert the HTML to <a href="https://pugjs.org">Pug</a>. Pug (formerly known as Jade) is a language that compiles to HTML. It lets you do useful things like inherit from a common layout as well as looping over JavaScript variables. If you're not familiar with Pug, you should go take a look at its syntax now.</p>
<p>The easiest way to do this conversion is to get a program to do it for you. <a href="http://html2jade.aaron-powell.com/">Here's the one I used</a> way back when; you may be able to find a better one. The generated Pug will be valid but not the prettiest - you may want to wait to clean it up since we're going to do some work to reduce the duplication soon.</p>
<p>Once you've got the converted Pug, you should rename the relevant HTML file to have a <code>.pug</code> extention, then replace the contents with the Pug. Do this for each HTML file.</p>
<p>The last step here is to make gulp build the Pug. Install <code>gulp-pug</code>:</p>
<pre><code>% npm install --save-dev gulp-pug
</code></pre>
<p>Then add <code>pug = require('gulp-pug')</code> to the end of the <code>var</code> declaration at the top of your gulpfile. Finally, change your <code>html</code> task to look like this:</p>
<pre><code>gulp.task('build:html', function() {
    gulp.src('src/*.pug')
        .pipe(pug({pretty: true}))
        .pipe(gulp.dest('dist'));
});
</code></pre>
<p>We'll also need to fix the <code>watch</code> task so it has:</p>
<pre><code>gulp.watch('src/*.pug', ['build:html']);
</code></pre>
<p>which will watch Pug files instead of HTML files.</p>
<p>That's it! Alyssa's site is now building with Pug instead of HTML.</p>
<h2>Step 3: splitting out the layout</h2>
<p>Pug's looping and flow control constructs will be very useful to us later on, but we can get some immediate productivity wins by splitting out the site layout so it's not duplicated across every Pug file.</p>
<p>There's one tricky thing about this: the navigation is mostly the same between pages, but not quite - the page the user is currently on shouldn't be a link. We'll solve this by using a <code>block</code> directivefor each link. That way, we can override just what needs to be changed, while introducing no duplication.</p>
<p>You'll have to figure out exactly what parts of your personal layout make sense to be split out. In Alyssa's case, there are three main things that are mostly or fully duplicated across pages:</p>
<ol>
<li>The navigation bar</li>
<li>The footer</li>
<li>Invisible metadata and script/style includes</li>
</ol>
<p>These are what we'll split out. First, we'll make a copy of <code>index.pug</code> and put it in <code>src/includes/layout.pug</code>. (Again, you can organize your files however you want - but in projects generated by <code>generator-stratic</code>, utility Pug files go in <code>src/includes</code>.) Next, edit out the page-specific content and replace them with <code>block</code> directives. Finally, edit each navigation bar item so it has its own <code>block</code> directive, leaving the old code as the default for the <code>block</code> directive.</p>
<p>Here's what this looks like when we do this to Alyssa's site:</p>
<pre><code>doctype html
html
  head
    meta(charset='UTF-8')
    link(href='/css/main.css', rel='stylesheet', type='text/css')
    block head
  body
    block heading
    nav
      ul
        block nav-homepage
          li
            a(href='/') Homepage
        block nav-projects
          li
            a(href='/projects') Projects

    block body

    footer
      p &amp;copy; Copyright 2016 Alyssa P. Hacker.
    script(src='/js/main.js', type='text/javascript')
</code></pre>
<p>Note how I've replaced the <code>h1</code> element (the contents of which vary per-page) with <code>block heading</code>, I've added a <code>block head</code> directive so we can specify the title per-page, I've made a <code>block</code> for each navigation link so we can override them if we want to individually (otherwise they'll have the default of being a link), and I've added <code>block body</code> for the main content. I've also cleaned out a bunch of the cruft the automatic converter put in there.</p>
<p>Now, we can edit <code>index.pug</code> so that it inherits from <code>layout.pug</code> - we'll use the <code>extends</code> keyword for this. Then we just fill in the content we want using block. Here's what this looks like after we're finished with Alyssa's site:</p>
<pre><code>extends includes/layout.pug

block head
  title Alyssa P. Hacker's homepage

block heading
  h1 Alyssa P. Hacker's homepage

block nav-homepage
  li Homepage

block body
  p This is the homepage of Alyssa P. Hacker. You can check out the projects I've worked on #[a(href='/projects') here].
</code></pre>
<p>You'll note that I've cleaned out some cruft here, too. We have one last thing to fix: if we change the layout, nothing will get rebuilt. We can fix this by changing the <code>watch</code> task again so that the line for watching Pug files reads:</p>
<pre><code>gulp.watch(['src/*.pug', 'src/includes/*.pug'], ['build:html']);
</code></pre>
<p>Sweet! <code>index.pug</code> is way shorter than what we had before and includes <em>just</em> the content now. We can do the same thing to <code>projects.pug</code>. Then Alyssa can, for example, correct the copyright year in <code>layout.pug</code> - i.e., once - and that change will go into both <code>index.html</code> <em>and</em> <code>projects.html</code>. I've gone ahead and made the change for her.</p>
<p>To give a high-level overview, here's what Alyssa's site looks like now:</p>
<pre><code>% tree -I node_modules .
.
├── dist
│&nbsp;&nbsp; ├── css
│&nbsp;&nbsp; │&nbsp;&nbsp; └── main.css
│&nbsp;&nbsp; ├── index.html
│&nbsp;&nbsp; ├── js
│&nbsp;&nbsp; │&nbsp;&nbsp; └── main.js
│&nbsp;&nbsp; └── projects.html
├── gulpfile.js
├── package.json
└── src
    ├── includes
    │&nbsp;&nbsp; └── layout.pug
    ├── index.pug
    ├── projects.pug
    ├── scripts
    │&nbsp;&nbsp; └── main.js
    └── styles
        └── main.css

7 directories, 11 files
</code></pre>
<h2>Next time...</h2>
<p>This post is long enough already, so I'll stop here. We've converted Alyssa's site to have a really solid base, so next time we'll build on top of this work to add superpowered blog features, powered by Stratic.</p>
<p>Now go apply this to your own site!</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/from-static-to-stratic-part-1</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/from-static-to-stratic-part-1</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[stratic]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2017 19:58:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[RSS and pagination on strugee.net]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>RSS and pagination are now enabled on strugee.net's blog, thanks to <a href="https://github.com/strugee/stratic-indexes-to-rss">stratic-indexes-to-rss</a> and <a href="https://github.com/strugee/stratic-paginate-indexes">stratic-paginate-indexes</a> respectively.</p>
<p>The pagination code is already pretty solid although there's always room for <a href="https://github.com/strugee/stratic-paginate-indexes/issues">improvement</a> - thanks to <a href="https://github.com/atungare">Ajay Tungare</a> for pairing with me at the <a href="https://recurse.com">Recurse Center</a> and helping me catch the bug! However, I'm not particularly confident in the RSS code, since RSS is actually somewhat tricky to properly handle. Because of that, I would seriously appreciate it if people tried adding the RSS feeds to their readers and seeing if anything breaks. If so, <a href="https://github.com/strugee/stratic-indexes-to-rss/issues/new">let me know</a>!</p>
<p>Cheers!</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/01/rss-and-pagination-on-strugee.net</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/01/rss-and-pagination-on-strugee.net</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 18:48:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[New project! thanksmaintainer.com]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>So I've been thinking about a new project recently. It's called thanksmaintainer.com, and it helps you say, "thanks, maintainer!"</p>
<p>Basically this idea came about from <a href="https://github.com/gulpjs/gulp/issues/1806">this GitHub thread</a> where some user comes and disparages the Gulp project for being "not actively developed" and complains that it's taking a long time to release despite the fact that a) Gulp 4 <em>is</em> being actively developed and b) the Gulp maintainers owe this ungrateful, presumptive person <em>nothing</em>. As @contra <a href="https://github.com/gulpjs/gulp/issues/1806#issuecomment-247416856">says</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>@rbatllet 4.0 is being worked - if you took more than five seconds to look you'd see it in other repos (for example: #1604). This repo has almost no code in it, it's a wrapper around the other modules so the contribution graph should be completely flat except for doc updates and major releases. We've responded to these tickets so many times - we have lives too.</p>
<p>I've had to move across the country 3 times since the tweet you linked - had my business unexpectedly fail (startups!), had relationships fail, deaths, travel, poverty, etc. - where the fuck am I supposed to find time to work on this while I'm trying to pay rent and put food in my stomach? The attitude people have towards open source authors is disgusting - I don't owe you anything, nobody does. Unless you've done something for the open source community (hint: you haven't!) then you aren't entitled to shit. If you want something to happen then help make it happen, otherwise log off.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I read this comment and thought, <em>that freaking <strong>sucks</strong></em>. I feel like there's a problem in the open source and freedom-respecting software community where consumers demand stuff from project maintainers like the maintainers <em>owe</em> them something or they <em>deserve</em> some feature/bugfix/etc. This is obviously complete and utter bullshit - most maintainers work on their projects in their spare time - and it can start to feel like maintaining a project is a waste of time because all you get from it is a drove of angry entitled haters.</p>
<p>thanksmaintainer.com is designed to solve this problem. Here's how you use it; it's very simple:</p>
<ol>
<li>You visit thanksmaintainer.com</li>
<li>You sign in with GitHub</li>
<li>You find projects that you use and are grateful for</li>
<li>You click the "thanks, maintainer!" button</li>
</ol>
<p>thanksmaintainer.com will keep track of all the good vibes people are sending towards projects. When it reaches a certain threshold, the website will (probably) find a way to contact the maintainers and let them know how many people's lives they've made better. Not sure how this last bit will work yet, or if it'll even work like that at all. But the core idea is there - hopefully it'll be an easy way to give some love back to maintainers who may really need it.</p>
<p>Some design notes: it'll only work with GitHub to begin with, but eventually I hope to expand support to e.g. GitLab. Also, the fact that it's focused on projects and not maintainers is intentional - being thankful for a person instead of a project isn't as meaningful because you're not specifying why you're thankful. In contrast, the project-centric design lets you say, "these <em>particular</em> lines of code impacted my life in a meaningful way." Plus, a lot of projects have more than one maintainer, and it seems foolish to only thank <em>some</em> of the project maintainers, and not others.</p>
<p>I would love to hear feedback on this idea. So, if you have any thoughts, <a href="https://strugee.net/contact">get in touch</a> with me and let me know.</p>
<p>Stay happy &lt;3</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/01/new-project-thanksmaintainer.com</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/01/new-project-thanksmaintainer.com</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 00:55:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pump.io 2.0.4 is available]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Greetings!</p>
<p>After a beta period of just over a week, pump.io 2.0.4 is now available on npm and GitHub. Whoohoo!</p>
<p>(This was originally going to be 2.0.0, but we had to do a couple patch releases due to some outdated documentation and several critical bugs. 2.0.4 is mostly the same thing as 2.0.0.)</p>
<h2>Changes</h2>
<p>Note that this release includes security improvements - namely, a newer Express version and a better TLS configuration - and therefore <strong>admins are encouraged to upgrade ASAP</strong>.</p>
<p>For the full list of changes, see <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/blob/master/CHANGELOG.md#201---2016-11-10">the change log</a>.</p>
<h3>Breaking changes</h3>
<p>(As I said in <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/">the beta announcement</a>:)</p>
<p>Pump.io 2.0.4 is a drop-in replacement for 1.0.0 <strong>unless</strong> you have any plugins configured or you modify the templates.</p>
<p>Plugins are likely to be affected by the upgrade to Express 3.x. The easiest way to migrate is probably to just run pump.io, test out the relevant parts of the app, and see where your plugin crashes. You might also want to look at the <a href="https://github.com/expressjs/express/blob/master/History.md#300--2012-10-23">Express 3 change log</a>.</p>
<p>If you modified the templates, you'll be affected by the templates' rewrite from utml into Jade. Migration should be relatively painless but has to be done manually. Your best bet will be to save a copy of the diff you created, undo your changes, upgrade, then use the diff you saved to reintroduce your changes. You'll have to run <code>npm run build</code> after making changes to Jade files.</p>
<h3>Non-breaking changes</h3>
<p>This release is actually relatively minor in terms of non-breaking changes; however, we <em>do</em> have some nice new improvements:</p>
<ul>
<li>A pump(1) manpage is now included</li>
<li>Any internal web UI link with a <code>data-bypass</code> attribute is now ignored by the routing logic (useful for e.g. custom pages added by the admin)</li>
<li>YouTube links in posts are now shown as  embeds by the web UI (<a href="https://github.com/expressjs/express/blob/master/History.md#300--2012-10-23">#1158</a>)</li>
<li>TLS connections now use Mozilla's "intermediate" cipher suite and forces server cipher suite preferences (<a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/issues/1061">#1061</a>)</li>
<li>Various minor fixes and improvements</li>
</ul>
<h2>Upgrading</h2>
<p>Upgrading is dead-simple. If you used our recommended install method, and installed from npm, you can upgrade with:</p>
<pre><code>sudo npm install -g pump.io@2
</code></pre>
<p>If you installed from source, you can upgrade with:</p>
<pre><code>git fetch
# If you modified templates, save the diff at this step
git checkout .
git checkout v2.0.4
npm install
# Restore your template changes
npm run lint:jade # Optional but recommended if you changed templates
npm run build
</code></pre>
<p>Both of these methods will work whether you're running 0.3.0, 1.0.0, or 2.0.0 beta. Make sure to restart pump.io after performing the upgrade.</p>
<h2>Getting help</h2>
<p>If you have any issues with the upgrade, get in touch with <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/wiki/Community">the community</a>. You can also email me at <a href="mailto:alex@strugee.net">alex@strugee.net</a>.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2016/11/pump.io-2.0.1-is-available</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2016/11/pump.io-2.0.1-is-available</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[pump.io]]></category><pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 07:49:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pump.io 2.0.0 beta is here]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Greetings!</p>
<p>As pump.io is gearing up for our 2.0.0 release, I just published a beta to npm. We'd love it if any interested admins could upgrade their nodes and report any bugs you may run in to. (All bug reports are helpful, but just so we're clear, we're likely to only fix regressions from 1.0.0.)</p>
<h2>Changes</h2>
<p>Pump.io 2.0.0 beta is a drop-in replacement for 1.0.0 <strong>unless</strong> you have any plugins configured or you modify the templates.</p>
<p>Plugins are likely to be affected by the upgrade to Express 3.x. The easiest way to migrate is probably to just run pump.io, test out the relevant parts of the app, and see where your plugin crashes. You might also want to look at the <a href="https://github.com/expressjs/express/blob/master/History.md#300--2012-10-23">Express 3 change log</a>.</p>
<p>If you modified the templates, you'll be affected by the templates' rewrite from utml into Jade. Migration should be relatively painless but has to be done manually. Your best bet will be to save a copy of the diff you created, undo your changes, upgrade, then use the diff you saved to reintroduce your changes. You'll have to run <code>npm run build</code> after making changes to Jade files.</p>
<p>For the list of non-breaking changes, see <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/blob/master/CHANGELOG.md#200-beta-1---2016-11-02">the change log</a>.</p>
<h2>Upgrading</h2>
<p>Upgrading is very easy. If you used our recommended install method, and installed from npm, you can upgrade to the beta with:</p>
<pre><code>sudo npm install -g pump.io@beta
</code></pre>
<p>If you installed from source, you can upgrade with:</p>
<pre><code>git fetch
# If you modified templates, save the diff at this step
git checkout .
git checkout v2.0.0-beta.1
npm install
# Restore your template changes
npm run lint:jade # Optional but recommended if you changed templates
npm run build
</code></pre>
<p>Make sure to restart pump.io after performing the upgrade.</p>
<h2>Getting help</h2>
<p>If you have any issues upgrading to or running the beta, please don't hesitate to get in touch with <a href="https://github.com/e14n/pump.io/wiki/Community">the community</a>. You can also email me at <a href="mailto:alex@strugee.net">alex@strugee.net</a>.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2016/11/pump.io-2.0.0-beta-is-here</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2016/11/pump.io-2.0.0-beta-is-here</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[pump.io]]></category><pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 03:05:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Webmention test receiver]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This post exists only to have a dedicated test URL to send example webmentions to until <a href="https://github.com/aaronpk/webmention.io/issues/77">webmention.io issue 77</a> is fixed (or in other words, I need a URL with a wide variety of webmention data associated with it so I can test the webmention styling you see at the bottom of all individual post pages).</p>
<p>It will be removed eventually, probably.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2016/11/webmention-test</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2016/11/webmention-test</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 06:34:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pump.io 1.0.0 is now available!]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/e14n/pump.io/releases/tag/v1.0.0">Pump.io 1.0.0</a> is officially available! Whoooo!</p>
<p>I just wanted to write up an announcement real quick to celebrate. Here's a sample what's gone into this release:</p>
<ul>
<li>Node 4.x support</li>
<li>Lots of security improvements including a better cross-site scripting scrubber and security-related headers that help protect the web UI (most notably, the web UI now declares a Content Security Policy)</li>
<li>Minor improvements to the API to make it (slightly) smarter</li>
<li><a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/librejs/">LibreJS</a> support</li>
<li>Numerous dependency upgrades, most notably Connect</li>
<li>And of course, tons of minor bugfixes and improvements</li>
</ul>
<p>For more details, see the brand-new <a href="https://github.com/e14n/pump.io/blob/master/CHANGELOG.md#100---2016-08-26">change log</a>.</p>
<p>And of course since we're now past 0.x.x releases, we're now officially making a commitment to the community to make only API-compatible changes going forward (or at least, until 2.0.0!).</p>
<p>As this release <em>does</em> improve security and fixes a lot of bugs, node administrators are encouraged to upgrade as soon as possible. If you have a global, npm-based install, you can upgrade with:</p>
<pre><code>sudo npm install -g pump.io
</code></pre>
<p>And with a source-based install:</p>
<pre><code>git pull
git checkout v1.0.0
npm install --production
</code></pre>
<p>If you're upgrading from 0.3.0, everything should Just Work(tm). Don't forget to restart your daemon!</p>
<p>One final note - the rumors are true. While we're not doing so <em>yet</em>, we are, in fact, planning to deprecate running under Node.js 0.10 and 0.12 very soon. Also, if you upgrade to Node.js 4.x early, the new, better XSS scrubber will be enabled - <em>however</em>, be aware that pump.io is far less tested under Node.js 4.x and you are likely to run into more bugs than you would under 0.10 or 0.12. This is an unfortunate situation, but sadly there's really nothing to be done about it. :(</p>
<p>Special thanks to Menno Vossen, Laura Arjona, Evan Prodromou, Jan Kusanagi and all the other volunteers who did so many different things to make this release happen. It truly wouldn't have happened without you.</p>
<p>Enjoy the release!</p>
<p>With &lt;3,</p>
<p>AJ</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2016/08/pump.io-1.0.0-is-now-available</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2016/08/pump.io-1.0.0-is-now-available</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[pump.io]]></category><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2016 06:37:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pump.io: call for testers, call for feedback]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>So in my <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2016/08/new-stuff-in-pump.io">last post</a>, I mentioned that I'd left a couple things for a second blog post. This is that post, and instead of being about all the cool stuff going on in the pumpiverse, it's about stuff that you - yes, <em>you</em>! - can do! It's super easy too.</p>
<h2>Call for testers</h2>
<p>So as I mentioned, the <code>utml-to-jade</code> branch is basically finished (see <a href="https://github.com/e14n/pump.io/pull/1170">PR #1170</a>). Since switching templating languages is a huge, huge change, by definition touching every single part of the Web UI, we want to make sure it's well-tested. This is especially critical given the fact that the Web UI unfortunately has <a href="https://github.com/e14n/pump.io/issues/147">very little test coverage</a>.</p>
<p>That's where pump.io system administrators come in. If you're a sysadmin and you're willing to test this change on your node, we'd very much appreciate it. There's very little risk, since I <em>think</em> I've squashed all the regressions that happened, but you should be willing to <a href="https://github.com/e14n/pump.io/issues">report bugs</a> if you <em>do</em> run into them. In particular, you should look out for:</p>
<ol>
<li>Links that seem to encompass too much text</li>
<li>Missing spaces - e.g. <code>Alex Jordanat [date]</code> instead of <code>Alex Jordan at [date]</code></li>
<li>HTML code showing up on the page - e.g. <code>Test note&lt;br /&gt;</code> instead of <code>Test note</code> followed by a line break</li>
</ol>
<p>Note that the <code>utml-to-jade</code> branch incorporates all changes in the <code>master</code> branch, so you may want to check out the advice in <a href="https://github.com/e14n/pump.io/wiki/Running-from-git-master">Running from Git master</a>.</p>
<p>Sound interesting? Want to take part in the development of pump.io? Installing is super easy:</p>
<pre><code>$ [sudo] npm install -g e14n/pump.io#utml-to-jade
</code></pre>
<p>This will work even if you already have a (non-source) install of pump.io - just make sure to restart the server afterwards.</p>
<p>Note that this command has some semi-terrible logic to build Jade templates on install (this is a workaround for a deficiency in npm). If you get a scary warning message from npm, please <a href="https://github.com/e14n/pump.io/issues">file an issue</a>, making sure to include the full log.</p>
<h2>Call for design feedback</h2>
<p>The other big thing that's happening is the pump.io 1.0.0 tshirt we're designing! I've spent quite a bit of time working on a variety of candidate designs which can be viewed in <a href="https://cloud.strugee.net/index.php/s/Ymw2RAdxyFZuuwu">this ownCloud share</a>. Obviously we want the coolest tshirt possible, so we're looking for any design feedback that people have. Anyone with some spare time can glance through the designs, and we'd be thrilled to get everyone's opinions.</p>
<p>If this sounds interesting, I'd welcome you to check out <a href="https://cloud.strugee.net/index.php/s/Ymw2RAdxyFZuuwu">the drafts</a>. As always, get in touch with the community through <a href="https://github.com/e14n/pump.io/wiki/Community#community-accounts-communication">our chatroom</a> or if you'd prefer, you can email me directly at <a href="mailto:alex@strugee.net">alex@strugee.net</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks so much! :)</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2016/08/pump.io-call-for-testers-call-for-feedback</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2016/08/pump.io-call-for-testers-call-for-feedback</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[pump.io]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2016 17:35:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[New stuff in pump.io]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>So I promised <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2016/05/stratic-part-one">a (long) while ago</a> that I'd blog about all the stuff going on in <a href="http://pump.io">pump.io</a>. And there is a <em>lot</em> going on. Where to even begin?</p>
<h2>LFNW talk</h2>
<p>I think the first thing I should mention is <a href="https://linuxfestnorthwest.org/2016/sessions/pumpio-community">the talk</a> I gave at LinuxFest Northwest this year. It went really, really well (even though I finished half the slides the night before), and people seemed to be really engaged, especially during questions. It starts off by covering the history behind pump.io: that includes the relevant protocols, like OStatus and <a href="http://activitystrea.ms">ActivityStreams</a>, but also the motivation behind abandoning StatusNet (aka current GNU Social) in favor of a brand-new network. Next I move on to the way that pump.io itself works, namely, its function as a generic ActivityStreams distribution engine. To put this another way, I explain why this quote from <a href="https://github.com/e14n/pump.io/blob/master/README.md">the README</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I post something and my followers see it. That's the rough idea behind the pump.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>is a pretty accurate way of describing what pump.io actually does. (I quote that quite a few times in the slides themselves.) I end with a discussion of the recent developments in the community, which are of course wonderful, and a short call-to-action for people to contribute - either directly to the software, or by joining the network and spreading pump.io.</p>
<p>Oh, and by the way - the talk was recorded! So you can watch it <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uQ6RVTFdYNc">on YouTube</a> or, even better, <a href="https://media.strugee.net/u/alex/m/linuxfest-northwest-2016-pump-io-the-community/">on my personal MediaGoblin</a>. Fitting, since (as I mention in the talk) MediaGoblin federation will soon be released, and it's based on (and fully interoperable with) the pump.io protocol!</p>
<h2>Conservancy application</h2>
<p>Pump.io is applying to the <a href="https://sfconservancy.org/">Software Freedom Conservancy</a>! This is super fantastic for us for a number of reasons. One of the biggest advantages is the fact that inside Conservancy (assuming our application is accepted), we'll be able to take donations much, much easier. This is primarily important because nodes in the pump.io network are volunteer-run, but they still require funds to operate. We're thinking about models wherein people will be able to donate to "pump.io", and then some (most?) of those funds will be used to pay for the network. (In particular, they'll be used to pay for the existing E14N nodes that Evan currently runs, which will become extremely useful once we transition those nodes to community owners). Conservancy also provides useful miscellaneous services, like owning our logo and making sure that if we encounter license violations, the license is properly enforced. But perhaps most importantly, becoming part of Conservancy cements pump.io even more in the community - both the group of people working on the software &amp; network, but also the larger free software world.</p>
<h2>ReadTheDocs</h2>
<p>We've started a <a href="http://pumpio.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">dedicated space</a> for project documentation, hosted on ReadTheDocs. We're plannning to move a bunch of content from the GitHub wiki into this project, and hopefully it'll become a thorough and central place for pump.io documentation - both for users and for deployers.</p>
<h2>Triage</h2>
<p>We've spent quite a bit of time going through open issues and prioritizing them. A lot of issues have a release target now, and it feels really nice to feel like our issue tracker is a bit more organized.</p>
<p>Special thanks to <a href="https://identi.ca/larjona">Laura Arjona</a> for driving this work.</p>
<h2>Various minor code improvements</h2>
<p>There have been a <em>bunch</em> of small bugfixes and improvements that have gone into the <code>master</code> branch - some of them user-facing, and some of them making the development experience better. Notable changes include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Migrating from Connect 1.x to Connect 2.x (this is just a start - Connect 2.x is still deprecated, but it gets us closer than we were to relying on a fully non-deprecated stack)</li>
<li>JSHint is now automatically run against <code>bin/</code> and <code>routes/</code> when <code>npm test</code> is run. This makes it super obvious when there are regressions in code quality, especially in Pull Requests (since Travis CI will fail if JSHint doesn't succeed.)</li>
<li>JSCS is now used to enforce code style. It's automatically run against the entire codebase (whoo!) when you run <code>npm test</code>, and it's awesome for the same reason - much of the style-related feedback that would've previously ended up in a Pull Request can now be dealt with directly on a local development machine, reducing PR review time for both the reviewer <em>and</em> the contributor.</li>
<li>LibreJS is now <a href="https://github.com/e14n/pump.io/pull/1058">supported</a></li>
<li>Tests now pass! Whooooooooo! (Thanks to Menno Vossen for sending <a href="https://github.com/e14n/pump.io/pull/1136">the enormous Pull Request</a> that made this happen.)</li>
</ul>
<p>Those are just the bigger ones, of course - there are a bunch of even smaller problems that got squashed as well. I'd also like to point out that quite a few of these were long-standing PRs which <em>finally</em> made it into core, which is awesome for everyone.</p>
<h2>Express 3.x migration</h2>
<p>I've been putting in a lot of work to migrate pump.io to Express 3.x. It's a huge amount of work, but when complete, it will bring us very, very close to being able to migrate onto Express 4.x, which is modern and fully-supported by upstream. Basically what I've been doing is just running the app, seeing where it crashes, going to the exception site, and fixing the problem. Rinse, repeat. You can check out this work on the <a href="https://github.com/e14n/pump.io/tree/express-3.x"><code>express-3.x</code></a> branch - currently, this branch can successfully start up the app, but will crash pretty soon after you try to do almost anything else.</p>
<p>This work, unfortunately, is on hold while another important project is completed: converting all the templates from utml to Jade.</p>
<h2>utml to Jade transition</h2>
<p>This is basically what it sounds like. Previously, the templates in pump.io were based on <a href="https://github.com/mikefrey/utml">utml</a>, which is essentially a thin wrapper around <a href="http://underscorejs.org/#template">Underscore.js's <code>_.template()</code></a> function. However, utml doesn't work with Express 3.x (and it's not really worth <em>making</em> it work), plus it's not the prettiest to work with. <a href="http://jade-lang.com/">Jade</a> is an extremely popular templating language in Node-land nowadays, so a couple months ago I spent somewhere between 14 and 18 hours going through and rewriting all the utml in Jade, which was absolutely brutal - but necessary. Then, of course, I had to fix the client-side templating logic to handle Jade instead of Underscore templates, which took quite a while, along with the fact that I made a very large number of minor (largely cosmetic) errors in my conversions.</p>
<p>As I said above, this was kind of awful work (<em>especially</em> the beginning), but it's necessary and great, as it paves the way for Express 3.x <em>and</em> massively improves the contributor experience.</p>
<p>You can check out the gory details of this work in <a href="https://github.com/e14n/pump.io/pull/1170">PR #1170</a>, and the original reasoning behind why we're doing this in <a href="https://github.com/e14n/pump.io/issues/1167">issue #1167</a>. This work is actually done, but I'm going to write a separate blog post about it, calling for testers.</p>
<h2>Upcoming 1.0.0 release</h2>
<p>Last but <strong>certainly</strong> not least, we're gearing up for our 1.0.0 release! From a codebase standpoint, this is really just a small bugfix release (although it will make a lot of things less broken and - if I recall correctly - fix the actual installation process), but more importantly, it means that we're now committing to <a href="http://semver.org/">semantic versioning</a>, which is a win for everyone (but especially administrators). The main thing that needs to be fixed before this goes out the door is the behavior of the XSS scrubber, which was accidentally made a little too aggressive. This is being tracked in <a href="https://github.com/e14n/pump.io/issues/1169">issue #1169</a>.</p>
<p>As a bonus, I'm also designing a t-shirt that (if there's sufficient interest) we may print as a celebration of this release - but more on this in my next post.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2016/08/new-stuff-in-pump.io</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2016/08/new-stuff-in-pump.io</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[pump.io]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2016 05:26:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Work on strugee.net]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I realized I forgot to blog about all the work I've done on the <code>strugee.net</code> build code recently! I want to get back to working on Stratic part two (aka pretty indexes), but I thought I'd really quickly take the time to point out what's been done.</p>
<p>First of all, even though I rewrote the code in <a href="http://jade-lang.com">Jade</a> about <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2014/12/new-blog-new-site">a year and a half ago</a>, there was still a huge amount of boilerplate code in each Jade file. Why? Because essentially the way I did that was by running each HTML file through an <a href="http://html2jade.aaron-powell.com/">HTML to Jade</a> converter, then manually fixing up the result to be, you know, less ugly. That meant that common stuff, like the navbar, footer, includes, etc. were all duplicated across all Jade files. And that sucks, because <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don't_repeat_yourself">Don't Repeat Yourself</a> is a thing.</p>
<p>Luckily, refactoring is a thing too! So a few weeks ago, I went and split out the common site layout into <a href="https://github.com/strugee/strugee.github.com/blob/c5ec1634a6b038eec25adb5abcd2b578a60ec4fd/src/includes/layout.jade">its own Jade file</a>, then made all the individual pages inherit from that common layout. The most difficult part of this was undoubtedly the navigation bar - I was pretty sure I'd have to just deal with the fact that the navbar was duplicated across pages (because each page has to have a different link deactivated), but then inspiration struck, and I ended up witht the solution I have now. Instead of treating the entire navigation as one block, I treat each <em>link</em> as a block that is overridable via Jade's <code>block</code> directive. And, since Jade <code>block</code>s can have defaults, each page only overrides exactly what it needs to, and the rest of the links are automatically there and properly clickable.</p>
<p>This has a couple nice side effects. The first is that the codebase that generates <code>strugee.net</code> is now <em>extremely</em> easy for me to change, regardless of what part of the site I touch (whereas before, individual pages were pretty easy but changing e.g. the navbar require editing each and every individual page). The second (and clearly the most important) is that Night Mode, which I implemented in a 45-minute class <em>over two years ago</em> now (back when I was still in high school - what a crazy thing to think about not being in high school anymore!) now works on every page across all of <code>strugee.net</code>. Whooo! Silly hacks are at the core of the web, right? Might as well make them work well.</p>
<p>Finally, I'd be remiss if I didn't mention that I now have a proper <a href="https://github.com/strugee/strugee.github.com/blob/c5ec1634a6b038eec25adb5abcd2b578a60ec4fd/gulpfile.js#L128"><code>deploy</code> task</a>, so I can abandon the sketchy and genuinely terrible deploy process that I used before. (For those curious: <code>gulp build &amp;&amp; git checkout master &amp;&amp; mv dist/*.html . &amp;&amp; git commit -m "Some bad commit message" &amp;&amp; git push &amp;&amp; git checkout src</code> - not shown here are the several attempts where I made some typo or possibly didn't think of some files in <code>dist/</code> that changed and so should have been <code>mv</code>'d, but weren't.) And, I now use root-relative includes now, e.g. <code>/js/main.js</code> instead of <code>js/main.js</code>, which is another win for DRY because now I don't have to maintain different header contents for subpages (which used to be the exact same, just with <code>../</code> prepended to all paths).</p>
<p>In conclusion: yay for progress! And yay for the fact that my codebase actually looks like someone competent wrote it! \o/</p>
<p>(Final note: I haven't forgotten my promise to blog about stuff happening in pump.io-land. But, not now.)</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2016/06/work-on-strugee-net</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2016/06/work-on-strugee-net</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2016 04:30:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Stratic part one is done!]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Whooooooooooo!</p>
<p>I am so, so, <em>so</em> thrilled to announce that the first part of <a href="https://github.com/strugee/generator-stratic">Stratic</a> is complete! And you can see the result right here on strugee.net, since this blog post was generated with Stratic!</p>
<p><strong>tl;dr</strong>:</p>
<pre><code>var rename = require('gulp-rename');
var markdown = require('gulp-markdown');
var parse = require('stratic-parse-header');
var straticToJson = require('stratic-post-to-json-data');
var jadeTemplate = require('gulp-jade-template');
var dateInPath = require('stratic-date-in-path');

gulp.task('posts', function() {
    return gulp.src('src/blog/*.md')
               .pipe(parse())
               .pipe(markdown())
               .pipe(dateInPath())
               .pipe(straticToJson())
               .pipe(jadeTemplate('src/blog/post.jade'))
               .pipe(rename({ extname: '.html' }))
               .pipe(gulp.dest('dist/blog'));
});
</code></pre>
<p>How <em>gorgeous</em> is that?? Let me explain how it works. (I'll assume the reader is familiar with <a href="https://github.com/gulpjs/gulp">Gulp</a> and <a href="https://nodejs.org/en/">Node.js</a>.)</p>
<p>So the <code>gulp.src()</code> call is pretty obvious. We just read all the blog posts into the stream. Note, however, that <code>gulp.src()</code> doesn't stream text, per se - it streams <a href="https://github.com/gulpjs/vinyl">Vinyl</a> file objects. This will become important later.</p>
<p>Now, the first piece of custom Stratic code that we use is the <code>stratic-parse-header</code> module. This module takes a Markdown file with a standard Stratic header (see <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2014/11/new-blog-new-site">my original announcement</a> for details), parses the header, strips it out, then returns the new, headerless Markdown. However, the new Vinyl file object has a couple of new properties from the parsing phase - specifically, <code>file.title</code>, <code>file.author</code>, <code>file.time</code>, and <code>file.categories</code> now exist. This is why the fact that Vinyl is used is important - now <em>any</em> Gulp plugin downstream from where <code>parse()</code> is run can use all of these values in whatever way it wants. (See <a href="https://github.com/strugee/stratic-parse-header/blob/master/README.md">the README</a> for more details.)</p>
<p>Now our Vinyl file object is <em>only</em> the content of the post, and it has additional Stratic metadata attached to it. Awesome! The next thing that we do is render the Markdown, just using a standard Gulp plugin for this. Easy breezy. After that, we pipe to the <code>stratic-date-in-path</code> module, which adds the year and month to paths. For example, without <code>stratic-date-in-path</code>, this blog post would be at <code>https://strugee.net/blog/stratic-part-one</code>. However, since I <em>do</em> use <code>stratic-date-in-path</code>, the post lives at <code>https://strugee.net/blog/2016/05/stratic-part-one</code> instead. Nice, right? Eventually I'll write code to generate pretty indexes for each year and month - that's what Stratic part 2 is for.</p>
<p>The next thing we do is pipe to the <code>stratic-post-to-json-data</code> module. This module is specifically designed to work with the <code>gulp-jade-template</code> module, which expects the file contents to be some JSON that will be given as data to a <a href="http://jade-lang.com/">Jade</a> template, whose rendered HTML becomes the new file contents. What sets up that JSON? You guessed it - <code>stratic-post-to-json-data</code>. That's all it does. It just creates an object that contains the metadata and the actual post text, runs it through <code>JSON.stringify()</code>, and sets the file contents equal to the result. Just how <code>gulp-jade-template</code> likes it.</p>
<p>And with that, we've successfully rendered a blog post. Whooooooooooo! I'm so pumped about this software. The call to <code>rename()</code> is just a little housekeeping, and then we write the whole thing back to disk with <code>gulp.dest()</code>. Awesome.</p>
<p>It's worth noting that the real beauty in this code isn't what the code actually does, but the extreme modularity of the whole thing. Unlike projects like <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a> or even <a href="http://wintersmith.io/">Wintersmith</a>, this isn't a giant, monolithic framework. It's all standard Node and Gulp. Note how (for example) we didn't need a custom plugin for Markdown - we just used the standard <code>gulp-markdown</code>. Don't like Markdown? No problem. Write something to extract post metadata from your preferred format, replace <code>parse()</code> with that and <code>markdown()</code> with a different renderer, and you're golden. All the rest will continue to work the <em>exact</em> same - adding dates to paths, rendering the template, etc. - because everything's decoupled from everything else. Each component can be trivially swapped out and replaced with something new and better, and the rest of the system continues to work. Gorgeous.</p>
<p>I've got to go now, but I'm not done blogging. I'll be back soon to talk about the work going on in <a href="http://pump.io/">pump.io</a>, and I'll be back (much?) later to talk about Stratic part two (aka, pretty indexes).</p>
<p>Whooooooooooooooooooooo!</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2016/05/stratic-part-one</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2016/05/stratic-part-one</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[stratic]]></category><pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2016 22:09:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Programming as an art form]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>The other day I described programming to someone. I pointed out that it's actually pretty easy to teach yourself programming languages, especially since after a while you start to carry over concepts from other languages. But what surprised me most about <em>my own explanation</em>(!) was when I compared programming to art: it's the kind of thing where you can just try stuff out and see what works and what doesn't, with no real consequences.</p>
<p>Since I said that, I've actually been thinking about it quite a bit. Programming is traditionally described as an activity closely related to mathematics, and to a certain extent, this makes a lot of sense, because of the logical skills that go into programming. You have to be able to reason your way through situations in order to effectively debug a program, which means logically eliminating possible points of failure. This is where math skills become very important.</p>
<p>But coding isn't just about logic. At <a href="http://opensourcebridge.org/">OSBRIDGE</a> this year, I attended a session about the beauty of code - it's hard to describe to someone who doesn't live and breathe code, but we all know it when we see it. We as a community value elegance in code; clever algorithms; thinking outside the box, and as I said in my <a href="https://strugee.net/presentation-just-do-it/#19">Just Do It slides</a>, the mere existance of Ruby proves this. So when I described programming as being like art, part of where I was getting that is the analogy I actually said (being able to easily mess around), but part of it was coming from my appreciation of the beauty of code. Part of it was coming from my sense of the aesthetic properties of programming.</p>
<p>I want us, as a community, in both our regular coding but also our educational outreach, to stop pretending that programming is so logical that it <em>is</em> math. Yes, there are elements of mathematics in coding. Lots of it, even. But to treat programming as a branch of mathematics is doing a disservice to the practice. So in addition to treating programming as a form of math, I want us to start treating programming as a form of art. There <em>is</em> such a thing as ugly code. The entire concept of refactoring would barely exist if that wasn't true. So let's start truly appreciating the aesthetic beauty of code, and let's start teaching that. To be honest, I'm not sure how you would teach that. But it couldn't hurt to try.</p>
<p>But even if we can and should treat it as both of those things, that doesn't mean that we should make that the be-all-end-all of how we describe programming. I truly believe that programming is not a branch of mathematics. And it's not an art form, either. Programming is neither of those things and both of those things; it is something entirely new, and we should treat it as such. If this isn't true, why do people swear by certain software? Why do people (including myself) aggressively sticker their laptops to showcase what software they use? And if this isn't true, how is it possible that people <em>love</em> their code?</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2015/11/programming-as-an-art-form</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2015/11/programming-as-an-art-form</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[musings]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 04:17:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[New blog, new site!]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I'm back! Sort of. Very sort of.</p>
<p>I've known for a while that I'm going to ditch Blogger. That's a large part of why I delayed posting stuff to my blog for so long: I didn't have blog software that I really wanted to use, but I didn't want to just put more data into Blogger. Eventually, though, I realized that it would take me a while to write software that a) built an actual blog from Markdown and b) worked the way I wanted it to, so I decided that I would just start cranking out posts and write the software to build them later. And then of course there was the week or three that I spent procrastinating on writing... oh well. I'm here now.</p>
<p>Anyway, it's <s>two</s> three AM as I write this, so I should go to sleep soon. I have a lot of stuff I want to write about, so I'll be brief.</p>
<h2>Summer</h2>
<p>I haven't written anything publicly since <a href="http://ramblingsfromalex.blogspot.com/2014/06/reset-net.html">Reset the Net</a>, way back in June. So I should probably cover some of the things I've been doing.</p>
<p>First, I ran a <a href="https://www.cryptoparty.in/">CryptoParty</a>! It was hosted at <a href="http://blackcoffeecoop.com/">Black Coffee</a>'s old location on Pine, and it was absolutely fantastic. We had a small group of people but it was really fun, anyway. The slides are <a href="https://github.com/strugee/cryptoparty-seattle">on GitHub</a> - and speaking of which, I've switched to <a href="https://github.com/markdalgleish/bespoke.js">Bespoke.js</a> for all my presentations. Hell yeah HTML5!</p>
<p>Right after the CryptoParty was over, I actually had the opportunity to drive down to Portland for <a href="http://debconf14.debconf.org/">DebConf '14</a>, which was one of the most fantastic experiences of my entire life. I met a lot of really cool people there, I got my new <a href="https://strugee.net/gpg">key</a> (also generated over the summer) signed by a lot of Debian folks, and I played a lot of evening games (not Werewolf - the other one). One of the coolest parts was the fact that I actually got to meet two of my heros - Linus Torvalds came and did a Q&amp;A with us (video of it is available <a href="https://youtu.be/1Mg5_gxNXTo">here</a>) and John Sullivan, Executive Director of the FSF, did a BoF-style talk on how we can get to a point where Debian is on the FSF free distribution list. I got a chance to talk to both of them afterwards, which was undoubtedly one of the coolest things that has ever happened to me thus far.</p>
<h2>Robotics</h2>
<p>Yes, the school year started and I'm a junior now. It's rough.</p>
<p>I'm on 5619 this year at robotics (Gabe, our main mentor, actually called me at DebConf to talk about it). I was a little annoyed to not be on 2856 at first, but it's worked out for the best. We're actually doing really well this year, and I'm so proud of the work we've been doing on the robot. It's difficult - it's much more complicated this year than last year, and there's basically no room on the thing. We had to move <em>wires</em> out of the way to make room for our scissor lift to come down properly. Speaking of which, we have a working scissor lift, which has never been accomplished at SAAS before, at least not during a season! So that's awesome.</p>
<p>We had a rough time our second competition, due to a lot of things - the Field Control System lag was bothering our driver, Wilson, so I wrote up something quick to fix it. I went to test it, and as soon as I ran our scissor lift up, one of the bars - which (of course) we made out of wood - snapped. So we had to rush to fix it before we had to go on the field in three matches or something. And because the bar broke, I didn't get to test the new teleop, and when Wilson tried to drive with it on the field, it broke horribly. Luckily we did pretty well in the first competition, and that gave us a nice buffer to make up for our losses the second time. I can't claim that we're doing well, but we're not doing horribly, either. <a href="https://youtu.be/gJzJUveTyyo">Here's a video</a> showcasing the first competition, and <a href="https://youtu.be/bdcG_WOOLwU">here's a second one</a> of the work the club did beforehand to prepare. Please excuse the weird camera angle of me intensely working on the code because of the time crunch of FTC competition.</p>
<h2>Patching Firefox</h2>
<p>Over Thanksgiving break, I wrote my first Firefox patch! There was a bit of the DevTools that was bugging me, so I fixed it, in true free and open source software fasion. Unfortunately I'm having some trouble writing tests for it, and I haven't had time to track down the information that I need, so the patch hasn't made it into the tree yet. Soon, though! It's on my list of things to do during break. You can see everything over in <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1106353">bug 1106353</a>.</p>
<h2>Mail</h2>
<p>I've spent hours of work, spread out over a number of months, working on steevie's mail subsystem. And I'm proud to say that as of a couple weeks ago, I'm finally done. I had to buy a block of static IPs for it, which I felt really cool for doing. There's still a lot of work to do - SPF, outbound DKIM signing, better TLS, Roundcube, ManageSieve, antispam, moving to LDAP from MySQL... the list goes on and on and on, but the system works. And I'm really proud of it. Anyway, I have a new email now: <a href="mailto:alex@strugee.net">alex@strugee.net</a>. I've even set up the customary names to forward to me: you can email <a href="mailto:postmaster@strugee.net">postmaster</a> for email trouble, <a href="mailto:webmaster@strugee.net">webmaster</a> for problems with the web server, and even <a href="mailto:hostmaster@strugee.net">hostmaster</a> for general stuff. Or root, if you're APT or cron or somesuch. It'll all reach me.</p>
<h2>Christmas</h2>
<p>It was Christmas yesterday! Merry Christmas, Internet! I got a bunch of books, including The C Programming Language, Second Edition (yes, this is <em>the</em> book that K&amp;R C is sort of named after), which was <em>very</em> exciting for me. I also got a budget for steevie approved, so now I can buy a bunch of hardware that I need. Hello, RAID 10 array!</p>
<h2>Stratic</h2>
<p>So, finally onto the juicy development part. <a href="https://github.com/strugee/generator-stratic">Stratic</a> is the name of my new pet project. Stratic is the STReaming stATIC site builder. It's like <a href="https://wintersmith.io/">Wintersmith</a>, except that it runs on <a href="http://gulpjs.com">Gulp</a>, which I've fallen in love with over the summer. Because of that, it's a little weird - there'll be some custom components used to support it, but the main body of code is actually... a Yeoman generator.</p>
<p>There hasn't been much activity in the repo because I'm using the <a href="https://github.com/strugee/strugee.github.com">strugee.github.com repository</a>, which still runs strugee.net even though I'm not on GitHub Pages anymore, as a testbed for Stratic. Once I've ironed out all the kinks, then I'll land all my work in the <a href="https://github.com/strugee/generator-stratic">generator-stratic repository</a>.</p>
<p>I'm very tired, and I want to go to bed, but before I do I figure I should explain the format of this post. Yes, this is Stratic format. It's pure Markdown, but with some additional semantics that Stratic will use to build out the blog. I figure that not many people will use &lt;h1&gt;s in their posts, so the Markdown equivalent (#) is used to distinguish the actual post text from what is essentially a header. I did something unusual, though, because even though the header is essentially for Stratic - who authored the post and when, what it's called, etc. - I wanted the Markdown to be at least somewhat readable in source form. Therefore, you're actually allowed to put anything you want in the header section. The values are distinguished by double quotation marks. Stratic will figure out what they mean based on their position. The first set of quotation marks contain the title, the second set contains the date, the third set contains the author, and the fourth set contains a comma-separated list of categories that the blog post should go in. The date looks a little weird - it's seconds since the epoch plus an optional UTC offset. It could be made more human-readable, but then you've got to parse stuff and it just turns into a nightmare. So I opted to sacrifice readability for elegance.</p>
<p>So! This is a blog post without a blog. Soon, I'll finish up Stratic and this will no longer remain solely in source form. I'm excited! I've already rewritten strugee.net in Jade, and used the opportunity to refresh <a href="https://strugee.net/services">the services page</a>. Time to get crackin'.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2014/12/new-blog-new-site</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2014/12/new-blog-new-site</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[stratic]]></category><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2014 11:44:42 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>