<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[strugee.net blog - 2018]]></title><description><![CDATA[strugee.net blog - 2018]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2018</link><generator>stratic-indexes-to-rss</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 03:35:57 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://strugee.net/blog/2018/index.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><copyright><![CDATA[© Copyright 2012-2017 AJ Jordan. Available under the GNU Affero GPL.]]></copyright><webMaster><![CDATA[AJ Jordan <alex@strugee.net>]]></webMaster><item><title><![CDATA[Tell your PR reviewers they're wrong]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever submitted a Pull Request and had the maintainer give you feedback that says something is wrong? This is of course, perfectly natural, and is why we do Pull Request reviews in the first place. But have you ever thought it was actually the <em>maintainer</em> doing the review who was wrong?</p>
<p>I'm the maintainer of a number of open source/free software projects and I have a message for you: <strong><em>tell this to the maintainer</em>, even if you're new, even if you feel like you have no idea what you're doing</strong>.</p>
<p>I'm sure to some people more experienced this sounds like obvious advice, but when you're new to this stuff getting feedback can be really scary. Maintainers have often spent years in the free software community and are super comfortable with how things work, not to mention that they might be more experienced in the language or framework their project uses. So it's super easy to just take their word as gospel. But I think it's super important to remember that everyone's human just like everyone else, and <em>everyone</em> has something to learn.</p>
<p>As a concrete example, take <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/pull/1310#issuecomment-291554491">this comment</a> on a Pull Request I received. If you read it and the following comment, I seem like an expert on <code>eval()</code>, but what you don't see until you read all the way to the bottom is that I spent about 20 minutes composing that comment because I had to double-check MDN to make sure I was actually correct. And honestly, that was <em>great</em>. That Pull Request forced me to recheck what I thought about the way <code>eval()</code> worked, <em>and</em> the contributor learned from it too! So it ended up being a win-win. Even if I was wrong, that would have been great too, since I would've learned something new. Sometimes the thing being discussed is just a really tough or confusing problem, and getting feedback on a PR can be a really awesome chance for both you <em>and</em> the maintainer to collaborate more closely and figure it out together!</p>
<p>I'm sure this won't work in every community. But honestly, if it doesn't, the maintainer you're running into is probably an ass and not worth bothering with anyway. This is what doing things in the open is all about - <a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html">freedom 1</a>, after all, is "the freedom to study the source code and make changes", the operative word being "study". The fact that knowledge is shared out in the open with anyone who wants it is one of the most amazing parts of this community, and I want to encourage you to stay curious and ask lots of questions.</p>
<p>So if you've ever walked away from a Pull Request review feeling like something wasn't quite right, consider this your permission slip to politely <em>tell your reviewer you think they're wrong</em>[1] - just make sure to be polite and explain why you think so! And remember, whatever they say, they're not criticizing you personally. I hope you embrace it as an opportunity to grow.</p>
<p>Footnotes:</p>
<p>[1]: Phrasing this as "I think you're wrong" instead of "you're wrong" is great for a lot of reasons, but one notable and less obvious one is that if the maintainer <em>does</em> end up being right, you won't feel silly.</p>
<p><em>Edited to clarify that I'm not advocating inpoliteness, to change the phrasing to "I</em> think <em>you're wrong", and to add some nice framing around a chance to collaborate on a difficult problem. Thanks to the Recurse Center folks whose feedback turned into these changes, particularly <a href="https://www.harihareswara.net/">Sumana Harihareswara</a> and <a href="https://jvns.ca/">Julia Evans</a>.</em></p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2018/01/tell-your-pr-reviewers-theyre-wrong</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2018/01/tell-your-pr-reviewers-theyre-wrong</guid><category><![CDATA[tips]]></category><category><![CDATA[culture]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 03:04:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[pump.io 5.1 stable published to npm]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Last night I officially published pump.io 5.1 to npm as a stable release!</p>
<p>As I wrote in the beta announcement, this release contains a variety of improvements:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/08/zero-downtime-restarts-have-landed">Zero-downtime restarts</a>, which allows administrators to seamlessly roll over to new configurations and codebases</li>
<li>The daemon now generates startup log warnings on bad configurations, including insecure <code>secret</code> values and internal parameters</li>
<li>An official <code>Dockerfile</code> is now included with the release</li>
<li>The logged-out mobile homepage's menu icon is no longer incorrectly styled as black</li>
<li>An authorization problem with SockJS connections has been fixed</li>
</ul>
<p>5.1 stable <em>does</em> include one change the beta didn't: a bump to the version of the <code>gm</code> npm package which we depend on. This bump was done as a precautionary measure, as previous versions of <code>gm</code> depended on a version of the <code>debug</code> module which was vulnerable to denial-of-service security bugs.</p>
<p>As a project, we addressed these bugs <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/10/denial-of-service-security-fixes-now-available">back in October</a> when we issued security releases for all supported release branches, and at the time we confirmed that the vulnerable function wasn't used by <code>gm</code>. Today's <code>gm</code> bump does <em>not</em> constitute a security release; instead, we're just bumping the version as a precautionary measure in case we missed something in October's assessment of the situation.</p>
<p>Aside from the <code>gm</code> bump, there are (as usual) miscellaneous version bumps included in this release. We've also started tracking test suite coverage information as well as overhauled our <a href="https://pumpio.readthedocs.io/">documentation on ReadTheDocs</a>, moving most of the in-repository documentation there.</p>
<p>If you want even more details of this release, you can also check out <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/blob/master/CHANGELOG.md#510---2018-01-05">the changelog</a>.</p>
<p>pump 5.1 is a drop-in replacement for 5.0. That means if you're using our recommended installation method and installing from npm, you can upgrade with <code>npm install -g pump.io@5.1</code>. If you have a source-based install, you should merge and/or switch to the <code>v5.1.0</code> tag. And as always, if you encounter any problems, please feel free to reach out to the <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/wiki/Community">community</a> or <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/issues">file bugs you find</a>.</p>
<p>Finally, I would be remiss if I didn't point out that pump.io has a <strong>brand-new announcement mailing list</strong>! While the blog is great for announcing new releases, not everyone finds it convenient to check. Also, if we issue new betas in the middle of a release cycle, these aren't typically announced on the blog. Therefore in the future <em>all</em> new releases will be announced on the mailing list, not just initial betas. If you want to subscribe to the mailing list, you may do so <a href="https://lists.strugee.net/mailman/listinfo/pumpio-announce">here</a> - you'll get announcements of new features only, not e.g. feature announcements as seen on this blog. I hope people find this service useful!</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2018/01/pump.io-5.1-stable-published-to-npm</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2018/01/pump.io-5.1-stable-published-to-npm</guid><category><![CDATA[pump.io]]></category><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[releases]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2018 04:09:43 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>