<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[strugee.net blog - December - 2016]]></title><description><![CDATA[strugee.net blog - December - 2016]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2016/12</link><generator>stratic-indexes-to-rss</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 20:56:43 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://strugee.net/blog/2016/12/index.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><copyright><![CDATA[© Copyright 2012-2017 Alex Jordan. Available under the GNU Affero GPL.]]></copyright><webMaster><![CDATA[Alex Jordan <alex@strugee.net>]]></webMaster><item><title><![CDATA[Where we're headed (a.k.a. I'm worried)]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>(These are some thoughts I've had after reading <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2016/12/14/nyregion/donald-trump-democrats-lawsuits.html?_r=0">To Combat Trump, Democrats Ready a G.O.P. Tactic: Lawsuits</a> in the New York Times.)</p>
<p>I'm worried.</p>
<p>I'm worried about my country.</p>
<p>Believe it or not, I'm not talking about Trump. Of course he's horrible, and he's something to be seriously worried about, but I think he's really only a symptom of a much deeper issue in America, which is this: we are in an arms race with ourselves. (One might also describe it as civil war.)</p>
<p>I mean, think about it. Republicans (I'll get to Democrats in just a sec) have spent the last 8 years creating and perfecting tools to block legislation from going through. Government is about compromise, and they refuse to compromise. They shut down the government for cheap political points[1], continually and covertly passed <em>almost</em>-but-not-quite-unconstitutional antiabortion laws, and topped it all off with a taxpayer-funded lawsuit againt President Obama - just to name a few malicious maneuvers they've used.</p>
<p>Now that Republicans control both Congress <em>and</em> the White House, Democrats are gearing up to use those exact same tactics against Republicans. It's shameful behavior, and it's unbefitting for a democracy. This country is supposed to be about elected officials finding ways to compromise with each other so that everyone's as happy as possible, but instead it's turned into a situation where everyone is laser-focused on pushing through their full political agenda, no matter how unproductive it is and no matter what the cost.</p>
<p>Here's the big problem: I may think it's shameful behavior, but that doesn't mean I don't support the Dems. I completely support it, because the incoming administration's agenda is completely horrific to me. I support the Democrats' intent to utilize lawsuits because I don't think politics is just a game; it's life-or-death. Somewhere out there, there's a kid who's <em>dying</em> because conversion therapy has pushed them to the brink of suicide. It's a glaring human rights abuse, and Mike Pence wants to <em>fund</em> it.</p>
<p>Republicans may have invented the do-nothing Congress, but now they can't put the genie back in the bottle. The Democrats and the Republicans are now <em>stuck</em> in a legal arms race, and neither of them can turn back because then the other side would <em>destroy</em> them. And that makes me very worried, because if we're in an arms race, that begs the question: what's the breaking point? And what happens when we hit it?</p>
<p>I don't have the answer to these questions. I don't know how to stop us from reaching that breaking point. I dunno, maybe if we were all just... more patient? But sadly, that seems extremely unlikely. Sometimes I wonder if there simply isn't anything to be done - if America is the great experiment in democracy, maybe this is just the inevitable failure of that experiment.</p>
<p>All I really know is that we need to do something, and soon. Because if we don't, we will grind ourselves out of existence.</p>
<p>Footnotes:</p>
<p> [1]: we actually know for a fact - from staff present at an early meeting - that none of those orchestrating the shutdown believed it would accomplish anything. They just wanted to score points with their base. This is <em>fact</em>.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2016/12/where-were-headed-aka-im-worried.md</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2016/12/where-were-headed-aka-im-worried.md</guid><category><![CDATA[musings]]></category><category><![CDATA[politics]]></category><pubDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2016 08:43:35 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>