<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[strugee.net blog - 'personal' category]]></title><description><![CDATA[strugee.net blog - 'personal' category]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/category/personal</link><generator>stratic-indexes-to-rss</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 09:58:56 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://strugee.net/blog/category/personal/index.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><copyright><![CDATA[© Copyright 2012-2017 AJ Jordan. Available under the GNU Affero GPL.]]></copyright><webMaster><![CDATA[AJ Jordan <alex@strugee.net>]]></webMaster><item><title><![CDATA[Winter break priorities, 2017-18]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>So I just wanted to write something up real fast to document my development priorities over my upcoming winter break (which starts tomorrow, whoohoo!). This is just generally useful to have, because I'm forgetful, but will also help keep me accountable since the list is public.</p>
<p>So, here are the projects I want to get done, in rough order of priority:</p>
<ol>
<li>Polish up an <a href="https://github.com/nodejs/node/pull/14164#issuecomment-325553163">outstanding Node.js Pull Request</a> that automatically generates manpages for every module shipped with Node core</li>
<li>Deal with GPG key signing which I have been procrasinating on for, well, years now</li>
<li>Push some Debian packaging work forward (I've done some work to get the <a href="https://tracker.debian.org/pkg/profanity">Profanity packaging</a> up-to-date, and I want to get <a href="https://github.com/strugee/filter-other-days">filter-other-days</a> into Debian as well)</li>
<li>Finish up v1 of <a href="https://github.com/strugee/lazymention">lazymention</a> - high-priority since it's so close to being done!</li>
<li>Finally push through and implement <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/issues/1241">ActivityPub in pump.io core</a></li>
<li>Clear <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/pulls">the backlog of PRs</a> sent to pump.io</li>
</ol>
<p>I also am setting a goal of writing at least two blog posts per week, and I want to try to get some editing done on a paper I'm planning to try to get published (though I'm not sure if I'll end up doing this, honestly).</p>
<p>That seems like a lot, honestly, and yet I feel like I must have missed something - I will update this list if I think of anything else!</p>
<p>Cheers, and happy holidays everyone! \o/</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/12/winter-break-priorities-2017-18</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/12/winter-break-priorities-2017-18</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 22:44:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Not going to today's HWC San Francisco]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Testing whether my new Webmention implementation, <a href="https://github.com/strugee/lazymention">lazymention</a> (which will ship Real Soon Now™), will send a Webmention to note that I will <data class="p-rsvp" value="no">NOT be attending</data> today's <a href="http://tantek.com/2017/319/e1/homebrew-website-club" class="u-in-reply-to">Homebrew Website Club San Francisco</a>! Though let's be honest, I really want to.</p>
<p>(With &lt;3 for <a href="https://chat.indieweb.org/social/2017-11-15#t1510774596509000">Tantek</a>)</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/11/not-going-to-todays-hwc-san-fransisco-2017</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/11/not-going-to-todays-hwc-san-fransisco-2017</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2017 19:43:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Going to IndieWeb Summit 2017]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I'll be <data class="p-rsvp" value="yes">attending</data> the <a href="https://2017.indieweb.org/" class="u-in-reply-to">IndieWeb Summit</a> this year (well, the first day). Hopefully I'll write a way to actually post notes and RSVPs properly on this site, instead of sketchily writing the HTML by hand, which is what I did for this RSVP.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/06/going-to-indieweb-summit-2017</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/06/going-to-indieweb-summit-2017</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2017 09:09:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Graduation 2017: reflections on 365 days of gap yearing]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Tonight marks the end of the high school careers for everyone in Seattle Academy's Class of 2017. Congratulations to everyone who graduated tonight - you deserve it, seriously. To my friends in particular, I'm so proud of you guys! You're completely amazing, you've done such incredible things and I love you very much.</p>
<p>Attending the Class of 2017's graduation was <em>super</em> strange for me too, honestly, because I'm such a radically different person than back when I was on that stage.</p>
<p>This year I put out <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2016/08/pump.io-1.0.0-is-now-available">several</a> <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2016/11/pump.io-2.0.1-is-available">major</a> <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/04/pump.io-4.0-in-beta">releases</a> (and a couple minor ones too) of <a href="http://pump.io">pump.io</a>, the decentralized social networking software I maintain; I <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/05/pump.io-accident">became an Invited Expert</a> at the World Wide Web Consortium and I wrote the software that powers this blog - <a href="https://github.com/straticjs">Stratic</a> - from scratch. I spoke at some major technical conferences on <a href="https://media.libreplanet.org/u/libreplanet/m/pump-io-the-federated-extensible-social-network/">pump.io</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a9l-FmSgyt8">Stratic</a>, too. But mostly what I was thinking about tonight was all the personal development I went through. As some who are close to me in real life know (particularly those who were there), a year ago I was relatively seriously depressed. There were actually a <em>lot</em> of reasons for this, but one of the most important was the trouble I had dealing with change - the biggest change, of course, being leaving high school: somewhere familiar, somewhere with friends.</p>
<p>I vividly remember sitting in the seats just under the stage in McCaw Hall the day of graduation as the SAAS people running the show showed us where to walk and what to do. I leaned over to my friend and said, "I don't think I'll understand what's happening here for a very long time," to which she said, "what, like where we walk and stuff?" I chuckled and said nevermind, because what I was really referring to was what was happening in a grander sense - what this event really meant and was for, on the scale of years and decades (I couldn't find words for this at the time).</p>
<p>I don't really know what it felt like to walk out on stage for other people (both this year and last year) but for me, it seemed almost trivial, like a non-event. It didn't feel nearly as momentous as it seemed like it should. Based on my description my therapist would later refer to it as a foregone conclusion, a description that stuck with me given how accurately it seemed to verbalize what I was feeling. It just didn't feel big, but I <em>knew</em> that it <em>was</em>. In the grand sense, I just really didn't understand what was happening.</p>
<p>Tonight, watching the Class of 2017, I think I started to get it. The crux of my personal development was being at the <a href="https://recurse.com">Recurse Center</a>. In fact, applying to and attending the Recurse Center was without a shadow of a doubt the highlight of not just my year but my entire <em>life</em>. I love my friends and teachers at SAAS very deeply, and I still think going to SAAS was a great choice. But at the Recurse Center, I felt at home, like I belonged, in a way I just never felt in high school. Plus, it felt pretty great to live on my own in New York City, feeling like I knew my way around the subway system[1], how to get food for myself (whether at the supermarket to cook or from nearby restaurants), and just what it <em>felt</em> like to live in such an amazing place.</p>
<p>There was a moment in senior year, in Jason's English class, when I was thinking about my then-sophomore friends and wondering if I'd see them in ten or even twenty years. After all, they'd probably have separate class reunions. And right as I started to wonder what we'd all even <em>be</em> like then, it hit me that the idea of "growing up" is bullshit. No one is ever truly "grown up"; people just slide along a scale from toddler to wise elder. Every human always will be and always has been a work in progress - always growing, always changing. I am incredibly proud of all the technical work I did this year. I am unbelievably grateful and happy to have made so many amazing friends at the Recurse Center, and I feel very lucky to have such good mental health - mentally I'm probably in the best place I've ever been in my whole life. But even with all that, I know I'm still young. I still have lots of room to grow and there are more exciting opportunities ahead of me than ever.</p>
<p>When everyone's in the middle of something, I think they get lost in the moment. In my senior year, my whole life was structured around being in senior year; at the Recurse Center, my whole life revolved around the Recurse Center. Essentially, I'm describing the act of putting your head down and concentrating on something. So maybe what graduation (and important events like it) is really about is a chance to suspend time; to not be lost in the moment. A chance to, just for a second, not have your life revolve around anything in particular and instead, look at yourself and the way you've changed and continue to change over your lifetime. Like a character arc. It really is amazing, and in a way, isn't that implicitly what graduation's saying anyway? Graduation is an event designed to celebrate everything that the people on stage have accomplished - and in order to celebrate something, you have to sit back and look at it.</p>
<p>It was honestly <em>wild</em> to watch the people on stage talk about each other and their lives for the past four years, recalling both the time when I felt the <em>exact same way</em> they do now as well as just how much I, and my perspective, have changed. To the Class of 2017, as someone who was in your shoes a year ago - I know I sound stupid and clichéd, but your world is about to become so much bigger than you can imagine. SAAS, which once seemed like such a monumental, immovable part of your life, will instead become small (though still important). At least, that's what happened to me. I hope it does for you, too. And I'm really excited for you guys.</p>
<p>Congratulations once again. You guys freaking did it.</p>
<p>Footnotes:</p>
<p> [1]: the operative word being "feeling", because I almost certainly didn't know my way around <em>nearly</em> as well as I felt I did</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/06/graduation-2017-reflections-on-365-days-of-gap-yearing</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/06/graduation-2017-reflections-on-365-days-of-gap-yearing</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[musings]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2017 07:46:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[How I accidentally started maintaining a social network with thousands of users]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>As some of my readers (particularly Recursers) know, a couple of weeks ago I became an Invited Expert at the <a href="https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg">Social Working Group</a> at the <a href="https://www.w3.org/">W3C</a> (World Wide Web Consortium). The W3C is a standards body. That means it's responsible for defining things like how things work on the web, such as how web pages are styled using CSS and how web developers can protect their apps from security vulnerabilities using <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/CSP3/">Content Security Policy</a>.</p>
<p>My first thought when I got the email that my application had been accepted was, "<em><strong>WHOOOOOOOOO!</strong></em>" It was probably one of the most thrilling moments of my whole life. My second thought was, "how in the <em>world</em> did I get here!?" The truth is, it was almost an accident.</p>
<p>It started when I got involved in the <a href="http://pump.io">pump.io</a> project. pump.io, for those who haven't heard me talk about this endlessly (e.g. at RC), is a decentralized social network. That means that there can be multiple servers run by different people that are part of the social network, but the users on those servers can interact with each other in just the same way they could if it was just one big centralized server[1]. I first got involved in the pump.io project in August 2015. I was experimenting with different social networking software and decided to <a href="https://pump.strugee.net/">deploy</a> pump.io on my server. When I did I realized that pump... well, it didn't work very well. The web UI was kinda basic[2], everything was pretty buggy, and there were a lot of problems with the overall user experience. In fact, I know the exact day I set up pump.io (August 12th) because all throughout the experience <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/issues/1093">I</a> <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/issues/1094">was</a> <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/issues/1095">filing</a> <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/issues/1096">bugs</a> on things needing improvement. It was a shame, I thought, because this software seemed really neat. I thought it had a lot of potential.</p>
<p>After about two weeks it became clear that there was no activity in the upstream pump.io project. So after some deliberation, I ended up forking it (briefly). You can watch <a href="https://media.libreplanet.org/u/libreplanet/m/pump-io-the-federated-extensible-social-network/">this talk</a> around 16:00 to hear me talk about this a bit, though to be honest it's kind of just a footnote in the project's history. In the end Evan Prodromou, pump.io's author, ended up handing off some commit rights to community members.</p>
<p>Well, I thought, that was the end of that. Everything's smooth sailing from here on out! There were some big problems, though: the people who now had commit rights all were involved in other things and, more importantly, none of them knew JavaScript or Node.js! This makes me chuckle to this day, honestly.</p>
<p>So I started triaging issues. When people sent Pull Requests, I'd review them since it seemed like no one else was going to do it. <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/pull/1114">#1114</a> was, as far as I can tell (or remember), the very first of these "unofficial" PR reviews. I kept going; I even reviewed Menno Vossen's <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/pull/1136">epic PR which fixed all the tests</a> (fixing the tests being a feat which, having tried to start that work myself, I am to this day in awe of and <em>incredibly</em> thankful for). For that last one in particular, you'll note that <em>I</em> merged it, not Chris Webber. At some point in January(?), he asked me in <code>#pump.io</code> on IRC if I'd like write access to the repository, to which I said (paraphrased) "heck yes!" So he made it happen.</p>
<p>I never really intended for that to happen. However, I <em>was</em> the one doing almost all of the work. After a while it just made sense. This is what, among other things, I find so incredible about freedom-respecting software: you can just <em>do</em> things. I didn't ask anyone for permission to do those reviews. I just saw the need for a reviewer, and decided I'd help out.</p>
<p>Fast-forward to today, and I'm now an owner of the pump.io organization on GitHub. I make technical decisions about what to prioritize and what should go into pump.io core. I do a lot of the day-to-day work running the project, too, and setting up technical and policy infrastructure (with a lot of help from the community, of course, plus input from Evan). That, too, just made sense, as did my becoming an Invited Expert - I was pretty deeply engaged with the SocialWG's <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/">ActivityPub</a> specification already since it's based on the pump.io protocol, and I was really excited about said protocol being standardized. So I was participating pretty heavily and I think it just made sense to people in the Working Group for me to join. In fact, that also kinda happened by accident. I couldn't get edit access to the W3C wiki so we were speculating in <code>#social</code> on the W3C IRC server that it might be because I wasn't a "W3C member" or something. So some people at W3C were pinging the sysops team, etc., trying to mark me as a "trusted" user when someone - <a href="https://www.w3.org/People/Sandro/">Sandro Hawke</a>, I believe - said, "the other option is for you to just join the Working Group." To which I said, "well, but I'd have to join as an Invited Expert, and I don't think I qualify as an expert." Chris Webber's response? "You're just as much of an expert as me when I joined!"</p>
<p>tl;dr how in the world did I get here? I tried some software and got annoyed at it, so I just kind of <em>"did some stuff"</em> that led to me doing code reviews. That led to me getting involved in the decentralized social web which led to me <em>"doing some more stuff"</em> that got me involved in standards. Then because of that, I tried to edit a wiki and ended up being invited to apply as a W3C Invited Expert.</p>
<p>I mean, what the hell? Honestly. I can't emphasize enough that I didn't plan ANY of this. It just sort of... happened. And that, I think, is what's so cool about the free software community. It isn't about who you are, where you come from, or what your goals are. It's only about, do you show up? Do you show up and do awesome stuff?</p>
<p>I showed up, kind of by accident, and I now run a decentralized social network with thousands of users called pump.io.</p>
<p>What will happen if <em>you</em> show up?</p>
<p><em>Thanks so much to <a href="https://github.com/anjakefala">Anja</a> and <a href="http://jvns.ca/">Julia</a> for providing feedback on a draft version of this post.</em></p>
<p>[1]: I really hope this explanation makes sense and if it doesn't, I apologize - I use diagrams to explain this in real life.</p>
<p> [2]: Still is, but that should improve now that the technical debt work I've been focusing on for the past year is now <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/express-4.x-in-pump.io-core">basically done</a>!</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/05/pump.io-accident</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/05/pump.io-accident</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[pump.io]]></category><pubDate>Sat, 13 May 2017 03:51:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[RC week 11]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This is week 11 of being at the <a href="https://recurse.com">Recurse Center</a>. </p>
<script async="" defer="" src="https://www.recurse-scout.com/loader.js?t=3d49e64361d4b897ffd2fd56dcd93ca4"></script>
<h2>Day 7</h2>
<p>Arrived ~13:30, departed ~22:45, total time at RC 9h15m.</p>
<p>Brought in cookies and spent a lot of time discussing things on Zulip, honestly. Also figured out when I'm teaching things for Web Dev 101. Spent most of the day, however, writing about <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/default-secure-systems">default-secure systems</a>.</p>
<h2>Day 8</h2>
<p>Arrived ~16:15, departed ~21:00, total time at RC 4h45m.</p>
<p>Arrived super late today because I woke up in the morning, saw the blizzard outside my window, and said "hell no." When I <em>did</em> go in, the blizzard was still going, so I put on snow pants, snow boots, a thick sweater and my winter jacket, and my hat and gloves. Which took a while.</p>
<p>Spent some time discussing 10 different reasons not to put arsenic in the milk with <a href="https://jmeggesto.github.io/">Jackie</a> and <a href="https://github.com/andrewrk">Andrew</a>, which she later wrote a blog post about <a href="https://jmeggesto.github.io/blog/2017/03/poisonmilk">here</a>. Spent the rest of the day doing <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/RFCs/issues/2">maintenance</a> on some Stratic modules. Also spent a little time on the phone with my dad diagnosing my server's disk problems. I had him reseat the SATA cables, with no effect, unfortunately.</p>
<h2>Day 9</h2>
<p>Arrived ~12:15, departed ~23:25, total time at RC 11h10m.</p>
<p>Didn't do a lot of new stuff, but took care of some miscellaneous business. In particular I did some work on polishing <a href="https://github.com/hubot-scripts/hubot-seen">hubot-seen</a>, including putting out a 1.0.0 release (and then a 1.0.1 release when that turned out to have broken the world). In the evening, <em>finally</em> found the bug preventing us from upgrading pump.io to Express 4.x, which was unbelievably satisfying. Turned out that the bug was in some test code, not the application itself, and so I had been misreading the stack trace for <em>months</em>. (The top item was a test file, but I incorrectly assumed that that was just some test code invoking a bunch of internal stuff. Nope.) Also has a meeting with some of the other Winter 1s about feelings and the end of the batch and stuff.</p>
<p>Last but not least, caught up on weekly blogging. (I've been really bad for a while now...)</p>
<h2>Day 10</h2>
<p>Arrived ~11:45, departed ~00:00, total time at RC 12h15m.</p>
<p>Did a ton of pump.io work. I merged the Express 4.x branch, then went in and did a bunch of other more minor dependency upgrades. Also went to a soldering workshop run by <a href="https://github.com/eeclaire">Claire</a> immediately before presenting HTTPS Part 2 in the afternoon.</p>
<p>In the evening, went to presentations and then game night, where I spent the entire time playing poker. I put in $3 and got back $7.95 (read: $8). Sick.</p>
<h2>Friday</h2>
<p>Arrived ~13:30, departed ~21:45, total time at RC 8h15m. As always, Friday doesn't count as a day because RC is technically not in session.</p>
<p>Did some work on improving pump.io's dependency situation. The result is a system that is very, very close to being 100% up-to-date, which I'm <em>super</em> proud of to be honest. That also let me turn on dependency security monitoring through <a href="https://nodesecurity.io/orgs/pumpio/projects/32213bb8-f9a6-4dd0-8fc6-5caa8ea5f8fc">Node Security Platform</a>, with plans to enable <a href="https://greenkeeper.io">Greenkeeper</a> as well. Had the monthly meeting in the middle of all that which went really well and was very productive.</p>
<p>In the evening, went to Bottle Share, then put pump.io on the Linux Foundation's <a href="https://bestpractices.coreinfrastructure.org">best practices badge app</a>, the result of which you can find <a href="https://bestpractices.coreinfrastructure.org/projects/804">here</a>.</p>
<h2>Executive summary</h2>
<p>Well, I got a lot done on pump.io (and Stratic) this week. So it was relatively productive. But I did basically nothing that was personally productive (i.e. that pushed me forward as a programmer). Hopefully next week will go better.</p>
<p>Total time at RC 45 hours 40 minutes; cumulative time 510 hours 30 minutes.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/rc-week-11</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/rc-week-11</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 02:49:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[RC week 10]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This is week 10 of being at the <a href="https://recurse.com">Recurse Center</a>.</p>
<script async="" defer="" src="https://www.recurse-scout.com/loader.js?t=3d49e64361d4b897ffd2fd56dcd93ca4"></script>
<h2>Day 35</h2>
<p>Arrived ~13:00, departed ~21:30, total time at RC 8h30m.</p>
<p>Decided (in the morning) to sleep in because honestly, I was just really behind on sleep.</p>
<p>Didn't do a whole lot today. Took care of the monthly pump.io release, but spent most of the day writing <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/driftless-at-1000-mph">Driftless at 1,000 mph</a>. In the evening (i.e. after the Iron Blogger meeting) I spent some time fixing ejabberd's configuration to use the new access control syntax (I'd rewritten the config a while back, but hadn't deployed it yet because it broke logins).</p>
<h2>Day 36</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:40, departed ~23:40, total time at RC 13h0m.</p>
<p>Spent basically all day working on <a href="https://github.com/strugee/realtime.recurse.com">realtime.recurse.com</a>. I (mostly) finished up the bits that watch the filesystem and dispatch events (including the "periodic" submission logic), then started in on an automatic update mechanism. I'm pretty pleased with how it's turning out - I think it's pretty elegant. And, it's secure - updates are required to be cryptographically signed by yours truly. Went out to Black Burger with a <em>bunch</em> of people before going to Fat Cat in the evening. Then came back, worked on the updater a little more, and went home.</p>
<h2>Day 37</h2>
<p>Arrived ~14:40, departed ~23:20, total time at RC 8h40m.</p>
<p>Overslept by accident this morning. Spent a bit of time in the afternoon dealing with email, then focused on realtime.recurse.com - basically I was just working on the autoupater I started yesterday. My Python is <em>definitely</em> improving!</p>
<p>I'm actually really pleased with the updater. It's pretty elegant, I think. Basically whenever the server sees a request coming from the client, it checks the <code>User-Agent</code> header to see if the client's out of date and, if so, sends back an <code>X-Requires-Upgrade</code> header. Upon receiving this header the client will go fetch version information, which it'll use to download and verify an update bundle cryptographically signed by me. Yay for secure updates, and yay for simplicity! (Note that this design basically just reuses the connections the client is already making to the server, so it doesn't have to poll for updates all the time.)</p>
<p>I also spent a couple hours talking with Mikhail, discussing a lot of things - ranging from how Node.js's event loop works to the <code>is</code> keyword in Python to static site generator architecture compared to dynamic site architecture.</p>
<h2>Day 38</h2>
<p>Arrived ~9:50, departed ~23:00, total time at RC 13h10m.</p>
<p>Woke up, completely naturally, around 7 AM despite going to sleep at 3 AM. This was so surprising - and this is a true story - that I thought I had woken up at 7 PM and missed the entire day, including Security Club, Abstract Salad Factory, and Thursday night presentations. I was <em>really</em> mad, honestly. But then I looked at my watch and realized that I was on 24-hour time but it didn't say "19:00" and also my alarms were in the future and my phone was in 24-hour time too and also Anja on Zulip said "?" when I said I'd slept through Security Club. Despite the overwhelming evidence in the end, though, I still had a weird feeling that it was 7 PM. So that's the story of how, for a good 5 or 10 minutes, I genuinely believed I'd slept through the entire day.</p>
<p>Once I got to RC, I spent the morning finally(!) merging in a bunch of upstream <code>ejabberd.yml</code> config changes to steevie's ejabberd configuration, which got me closer to fixing the awful spam problem I have. Then I went to Abstract Salad Factory, followed by Security Club. Then in the afternoon (and after presentations) I started reading <a href="https://www.freebsd.org/">FreeBSD</a> documentation since that's what I'm running my new Tor relay on - as I discovered a couple days ago, my old one apparently got hung during boot and was consuming 100% CPU due to the kernel image being corrupted or something. I chose FreeBSD because a) it's a rock-solid system, b) it's a good opportunity to gain experience with administrating a BSD, and c) it increases the diversity of the Tor network. Also, had a conference call in the afternoon with the <a href="https://www.eff.org/">EFF</a> and Paul from <a href="https://ta3mseattle.org/index.php/Main_Page">TA3M Seattle</a> about TA3M Seattle joining the EFF's <a href="https://www.eff.org/electronic-frontier-alliance">Electronic Frontier Alliance</a>, which was exciting for everyone.</p>
<h2>Friday</h2>
<p>Arrived ~13:00, departed ~22:30, total time at RC 9h30m. As always, Friday doesn't count as a day because RC is technically not in session.</p>
<p>Didn't do a whole lot of coding. Spent a while helping <a href="https://jxself.org/">Jason</a> debug <a href="https://datamost.com/">Datamost</a>'s 3.0.0 upgrade (which apparently broke uploads). Attended presentations for the RC Game Jam, then fixed the documentation that caused Jason's problems. Spent a little bit of time polishing the website and README, too.</p>
<p>In the evening, fixed people being banned from ejabberd MUCs, then proceeded to fix my spam problem. Whoooooo! Then I kept working on my Tor relay.</p>
<h2>Executive summary</h2>
<p>Like any week, this had moments where I wasn't very productive. But overall I think it was pretty good - I made a lot of progress on realtime.recurse.com (and improved my Python in the process), and I made a lot of progress on setting up my Tor relay again (and learned a bunch about FreeBSD in the process). Also, I fixed my ejabberd spam problem. I learned nothing from that, but thank <em>god</em> I did it because the spam problem was honestly <em>awful</em>. The one issue was that I just didn't do a very good job getting up and making it to checkins.</p>
<p>Total time at RC 52 hours 50 minutes; cumulative time 464 hours 50 minutes.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/rc-week-10</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/rc-week-10</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[tor]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2017 23:42:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[RC week 9]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This is week 9 of being at the <a href="https://recurse.com">Recurse Center</a>.</p>
<script async="" defer="" src="https://www.recurse-scout.com/loader.js?t=3d49e64361d4b897ffd2fd56dcd93ca4"></script>
<h2>Day 31</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:30, departed ~15:15, arrived ~17:30, departed ~1:30, total time at RC 8h45m.</p>
<p>There were only two people in my checkin group this morning, and one of them was me. We thought about joining another checkin group, but it was confusing so we did it with just us.</p>
<p>Didn't really do a whole lot for the rest of the day. I fixed up a couple minor problems on strugee.net. Also I finally(!) fully caught up on blogging and went out to lunch with a bunch of people, including <a href="https://www.recurse.com/residents#Nelson-Elhage">Nelson</a>, the new resident. He's awesome. We had some seriously interesting discussions about the recent CloudFlare incident, as well as the work he did while at Ksplice.</p>
<p>Left early to do laundry, then came back for Nelson's talk.</p>
<p>Spent a lot of time in the evening cleaning up the <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/">pump.io homepage</a> - I removed a bunch of duplicated content, reordered the remaining text to put the important stuff first, and imported all the pump.io-related posts on my personal blog into <a href="http://pump.io/blog/">http://pump.io/blog/</a>.</p>
<h2>Day 32</h2>
<p>Arrived ~11:30, departed ~21:40, total time at RC 10h10m.</p>
<p>Missed my checkin by a wide margin because a) after I realized I just couldn't make it by 10:30 I gave up and had a nice relaxed breakfast and b) I looked at checkins.recurse.com and realized that I was the only one in my checkins group.</p>
<p>Went out to Taim for lunch relatively soon after that. Didn't do a whole lot for the rest of the day, honestly - although I did go for a walk to a park with some folks. Also, tested out the Signal videocalling beta with <a href="https://matthewkelsey.com/">Matt</a>, which worked pretty damn well, I gotta say.</p>
<h2>Day 33</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:40, departed ~1:45, total time at RC 15h5m.</p>
<p>I kinda tried to make it in for checkins this morning, but not really because I still hadn't fixed the "I'm the only one in my checkin group" problem. Didn't really do much today, honestly.</p>
<p>Went out to lunch with <a href="https://github.com/ant6n">Ant6n</a> and <a href="https://github.com/andrewrk">Andrew</a> and had a lot of interesting discussions with them, ranging all the way from <a href="http://ziglang.org/">Zig</a> to x86 hardware - did you know that internally x86 is actually essentially a VM implementation?</p>
<p>Spent a lot of time keeping Eliana company in Hopper late in the evening.</p>
<h2>Day 34</h2>
<p>Arrived ~11:05, departed ~17:55, total time at RC 6h50m.</p>
<p>Went to Nelson's "my first kernel module" talk immediately upon arriving at RC, which was <em>awesome</em>. I had some interesting conversations with him afterward, too, where I confirmed a theory I had about some weird btrfs-related behavior I'd seen a long time ago (where I <code>kill -9</code>'d an obviously hung <code>btrfs</code> process, which refused to die anyway). We also spent some time trying to figure out why <a href="http://unix.stackexchange.com/q/345285/29146">benchmarking loopback network performance</a> gave some weird results, which was quite informative.</p>
<p>Didn't do a whole lot after lunch. Left halfway through presentations to go to a play with Ant6n which unfortunately (due to a water incident with the subway system) I didn't quite make it to.</p>
<h2>Friday</h2>
<p>Arrived ~15:10, departed ~23:10, total time at RC 8h0m. As always, Friday doesn't count as a day because RC is technically not in session.</p>
<p>Woke up at a decent time but didn't really bother to get up or do anything, so I arrived relatively late to RC. Spent some time reading TOTP in preparation for the RFC reading group meeting (which ended up not happening) and then went to the RC Game Jam kickoff. Spent most of the rest of the day discussing game design with my team before getting dinner and hanging out in Babbage for Bottle Share Friday, even though there weren't that many of us (particularly since James was doing stuff in Babbage) and we didn't have any bottles to share. Oh well - it was still fun.</p>
<p>Talked with <a href="https://github.com/ebb-tide">Deniz</a> and <a href="http://www.aberke.com/">Alex</a> and some other folks (I've forgotten who, to be honest) before heading home.</p>
<h2>Executive summary</h2>
<p>Most of the "interesting" stuff that happened this week had to do with the resident. Got a little done codewise, but not that much. I'd say this week was 50/50 in terms of productivity.</p>
<p>Total time at RC 48 hours 50 minutes; cumulative time 412 hours 0 minutes.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/rc-week-9</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/rc-week-9</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2017 23:39:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Driftless at 1,000 mph]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Last week I published <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/how-i-passed-2k-github-contributions">How I passed 2k GitHub contributions</a>. This post is, in some ways, the antithesis of that, and it will be very emotional and messy. Here be dragons.</p>
<hr>
<p>Throughout my time at RC I've noticed only one thing is consistently difficult for me: focusing on hard things. Intellectually I love the idea of challenging myself. And I find that when I start to work on things that are new and not easy, it feels good and I tend to keep working on those things, because they're interesting. But starting is something that I just don't do frequently enough, and so I find that I haven't progressed as a programmer nearly as much as I would like to have.</p>
<p>What is productivity?</p>
<p>Merriam-Webster defines it like this:</p>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>
<p>the quality or state of being productive</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>the rate per unit area or per unit volume at which biomass consumable as food by other organisms is made by producers</p>
</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>And "productive" is defined like so:</p>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>
<p>having the quality or power of producing, especially in abundance</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>effective in bringing about</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>a) yielding results, benefits, or profits; b) yielding or devoted to the satisfaction of wants or the creation of utilities</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>continuing to be used in the formation of new words or constructions</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>raising mucus or sputum (as from the bronchi)</p>
</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>By definitions 1-3 I certainly seem to have been productive; I've written a lot of code, much of which is useful. But useful to <em>whom</em>, and for what purpose?</p>
<p>I sometimes feel as if I'm just generating more and more code without any guiding process, as though I'm wasting my time even though concretely I'm getting a <em>lot</em> of things done - driftless even though I'm churning out work at an extremely high rate. Is this <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome">imposter syndrome</a>? Or are my worries legitimate?</p>
<p>Maybe a better way to frame this question is to split it in two - am I being productive for myself, and am I being productive for the community - the two things that are currently important to me personally.</p>
<p>I think I am failing at being productive for myself, in some really important ways. I'm also succeeding in some - for example, I used to wish I had an engine to run my blog, and now I have <a href="https://github.com/straticjs">such an engine</a>. But in others I am failing.</p>
<p>What is the purpose of RC? Why am I here?</p>
<hr>
<p>recurse.com <a href="https://www.recurse.com/about#who-comes-to-the-recurse-center">says this</a> about people who come to RC:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The Recurse Center is for people who want to become better programmers. We are not startup school nor are we a bootcamp: Our focus is helping people become better programmers, not building prototypes, and we're not a training program for web developers.</p>
<p>Because there is no certification or grading, the only reason to come to the Recurse Center is to become a better programmer. As such, you will find kindred spirits and tremendous energy. We look for smart, friendly, self-directed, intellectually curious people who enjoy programming and want to get dramatically better.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>More directly, <a href="https://www.recurse.com/manual">the manual</a> has this to say:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You should be here primarily because you want to become a better programmer and spend the majority of your time here programming and doing things directly related to programming.</p>
<p>Well, we could ask you to be respectful of speakers and keep conversations on-topic in the Recurse Center space during the day (i.e. if you want to take a break and chat about your weekend, go grab a coffee).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>However, as <a href="https://haroldtreen.com">Harold</a> points out, that <a href="https://haroldtreen.com/tech/recurse/2017/01/27/recurse-center-return-statement/">isn't necessarily an accurate picture</a> of what RC is about. I think a lot of what it's really about is the people who are in the space with you. I've sure had a wonderful time with the people. Does that mean I'm "succeeding"?</p>
<p>Then there's the teaching.</p>
<hr>
<p><img src="/images/anja-teaching.jpg" alt="Screenshot of a Zulip message where Anja says &quot;thank you AJ for teaching us so many things. :)&quot;"></p>
<p>This is referring to the fact that I teach at Security Club every week, plus my volunteering to run a workshop or two for Beginner's Club and Web Dev 101.</p>
<p>Practically speaking, I get very, very little out of teaching at RC. Sometimes it helps solidify (or just plain remind me of) the concepts I teach, but this is the exception, not the norm. So in that sense by spending time teaching, I'm "failing" at being productive for myself. But it seems clear to me that people get a lot out of the time I spend, so I seem to be very productive for the community.</p>
<p>Equally importantly I <em>love</em> teaching. I qualified the previous paragraph with "practically speaking" because emotionally teaching is something that's very beneficial to me. Does that mean I'm "succeeding"? Does it mean I'm "failing" and "succeeding" at the same time?</p>
<p>I honestly don't know.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/driftless-at-1000-mph</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/driftless-at-1000-mph</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2017 21:27:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[RC week 8]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This is week 8 of being at the <a href="https://recurse.com">Recurse Center</a>. </p>
<script async="" defer="" src="https://www.recurse-scout.com/loader.js?t=3d49e64361d4b897ffd2fd56dcd93ca4"></script>
<h2>Day 27</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:35, departed ~0:30, total time at RC 13h55m.</p>
<p>Had a nice discussion about Stratic in my checkin group this morning. After that I went to the Capture The Flag introduction workshop, then spent essentially the entire rest of the day finishing up <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/from-static-to-stratic-part-1">static to Stratic</a> (which included, in a truly horrifying fashion, me rewriting and force-pushing the demo repository's history a good four times or so) so I'd have a post up for the iron bloggers meeting. Also spent some time fixing some bugs in <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/generator-stratic">generator-stratic</a> and published the beta 2 release with those fixes. Closed out the evening by digging into a remark problem where <code>&lt;script&gt;</code> tags would be stripped from posts. Ended up just asking on Gitter.</p>
<h2>Day 28</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:30, departed ~20:40, total time at RC 10h10m.</p>
<p>Continued to investigate the remark problem based on replies received overnight - turns out it was a bug in remark fixed in a release that had gone out the door literally the same day I asked. After that I spent the day upgrading <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/generator-stratic">generator-stratic</a> (which, remember, was originally scaffolded <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2014/12/new-blog-new-site">years ago</a>) to newer and newer releases of <code>yeoman-generator</code> until it used <code>yeoman-generator@latest</code>. Then I spent time adding some basic tests - they're kind of just smoketests for now (are the correct files generated, does <code>gulp serve</code> work) but I <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/generator-stratic/issues/11">intend</a> to expand them. Also moved over some issues to the new <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/RFCs">straticjs/RFCs</a> repository and attended Casual Presentations.</p>
<h2>Day 29</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:50, departed ~20:35, total time at RC 9h45m.</p>
<p>Didn't do a whole lot codewise today. However, I did teach Unix fundamentals for Beginner Club, which went pretty well - I just spent the entire time in the commandline, demonstrating different commands. We spent a little time talking about shell scripting, but not much. I forgot to cover conditionals, which was dumb since they're pretty weird in shell scripting. Spent some time in the afternoon starting a draft of <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/how-i-passed-2k-github-contributions">How I passed 2k GitHub contributions</a></p>
<p>Watched Kiki's Delivery Service in the evening.</p>
<h2>Day 30</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:35, departed ~00:05, total time at RC 13h30m.</p>
<p>Finished and published <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/how-i-passed-2k-github-contributions">How I passed 2k GitHub contributions</a>. Presented <a href="https://strugee.net/presentation-cryptography-basics">cryptography basics</a> at Security Club, then spent a lot of time fixing miscellaneous items on steevie. In particular ejabberd was apparently configured to use a standalone certificate bundle (instead of symlinking to something in <code>/etc/letsencrypt/live</code>) - this was because ejabberd requires the private key and the full chain to be in the same file. TLS certificate renewal didn't properly update this bundle, so XMPP client connections weren't working. ZNC was broken in the same way, so I fixed both of those. I also spent some time setting up a system to publish everything custom in <code>/usr/local</code> <a href="https://github.com/strugee/steevie-usr-local">on GitHub</a> so that it's public and version-controlled. So that's nice.</p>
<h2>Friday</h2>
<p>Arrived ~15:50, departed ~1:00, total time at RC 9h10m. As always, Friday doesn't count as a day because RC is technically not in session.</p>
<p>Came in super late (though I woke up earlier). Almost immediately after that I attended an initial meeting about starting an RFC reading group (an idea I floated on Zulip a couple days ago). Spent most of the day poking at IETF things as well as responding to <a href="https://github.com/hubot-scripts/hubot-seen">hubot-seen</a> PR comments. I just got write access! \o/</p>
<p>Closed out the evening by attending Bottle Share Friday, where I had a long discussion with <a href="http://www.aberke.com/">Alex</a> about running my own email server (which spun off into a discussion of how completely terrible and busted email is), followed by a long discussion about whether Apple's release schedule for Safari and attitude towards new web features and third-party iOS rendering engines is justifiable.</p>
<h2>Saturday</h2>
<p>Arrived ~11:15, departed ~23:30, total time at RC 12h15m. Saturday doesn't count as a day because RC is not in session.</p>
<p>Marathoned Lord of the Rings today. The showing was small and people drifted in and out but most of the time there were a couple people watching, which was fun. The original plan was to watch the director's cut versions, watching The Return of the King on Sunday, but we ended up watching the regular versions because you can't rent the director's cuts off Amazon, and I wasn't about to pay $30 for movies that I <em>already own</em> on DVD back home. We probably would've still watched on Sunday, except that I went out to get pizza for dinnr and found out that it was pouring rain (with thunder/lightning and everything). So I decided we'd watch The Return of the King and wait for the rain to let up, which worked beautifully.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/Husseinfarah93">Hussein</a> came in just as I was about to leave and stated that he almost had a heart attack because he sprinted literally from his apartment to Duane Reade, which truthfully was absolutely <em>hilarious</em>. We had some fun wandering around Duane Reade trying to find soap (which I needed to buy) before we both headed home.</p>
<p>(As a side note, my favorite brand of mac 'n' cheese by far is Annie's, which my local supermarket does not carry. But apparently Duane Reade does!? Wat???)</p>
<h2>Executive summary</h2>
<p>This week was weirdly divided - some parts were hyper-productive and some parts were pretty terrible. I certainly got a lot of work done on Stratic, and I taught a lot. But I didn't really do a good job of working on stuff that pushed my programming abilities forward.</p>
<p>Total time at RC 68 hours 45 minutes; cumulative time 363 hours 10 minutes.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/rc-week-8</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/rc-week-8</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 19:11:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[RC week 7]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This is week 7 of being at the <a href="https://recurse.com">Recurse Center</a>.</p>
<script async="" defer="" src="https://www.recurse-scout.com/loader.js?t=3d49e64361d4b897ffd2fd56dcd93ca4"></script>
<h2>Day 23</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:00, departed ~21:45, total time at RC 11h45m.</p>
<p>Didn't get a whole lot done today, mostly because we were all welcoming the Spring 1s - I went out to lunch with some of them and participated in Code Dojo in the afternoon (<a href="https://github.com/adityavkk">Aditya</a> and I solved the challenge in <code>bash</code>, which was pretty interesting an also hilarious[1]). However, I did do some maintenance on <a href="https://gplenforced.org">gplenforced.org</a>. I did, however, start a project to display activity in 455 Broadway in realtime which I'm pretty exited about.</p>
<p> [1]: Aditya asked me "so can you just cast a string to an integer in <code>bash</code> or...?" and when I said no he looked at me and asked how in the world we could complete this task - not realizing that the correct question is, of course, "does <code>bash</code> have a type system?" The answer to which is no, no it does not.</p>
<h2>Day 24</h2>
<p>Arrived ~14:30, departed ~1:10, total time at RC 10h40m.</p>
<p>Spent most of today working on realtime.recurse.com - I got the basic API working, so you can POST to the server and it'll handle expiry properly. Also spent a lot of time blogging for the Iron Blogger meeting (in which I got sentenced to use <code>vim</code> for the week instead of Emacs for not writing a post a couple weeks ago).</p>
<h2>Day 25</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:30, departed ~19:10, total time at RC 8h40m.</p>
<p>Spent the day catching up on various things, notably putting out a new pump.io beta that backported some regression fixes. In the evening I spent most of my time finishing up a mid-year college application form before videocalling with a friend in college.</p>
<h2>Day 26</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:35, departed ~1:05, total time at RC 14h30m.</p>
<p>Spent some time working on server stuff today. Other than that though I didn't do much of anything.</p>
<h2>Friday</h2>
<p>Arrived ~16:20, departed ~1:45, total time at RC 9h25m. As always, Friday doesn't count as a day because RC is technically not in session.</p>
<p>Worked on <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/generator-stratic">generator-stratic</a> today. I fixed some bugs and disabled some functionality that wasn't complete (and was non-trivial to complete). Published a beta 0 in the evening.</p>
<h2>Executive summary</h2>
<p>This week was... <em>okay</em> in terms of productivity. It started off relatively good, slipped a fair amount in the middle, and then somewhat came back at the end of the week. I did, however, check off some semi-longstanding issues on my todo list. So that's nice.</p>
<p>Total time at RC 55 hours 0 minutes; cumulative time 294 hours 25 minutes.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/rc-week-7</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/rc-week-7</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 20:14:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[How I passed 2k GitHub contributions]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>So the other day I logged into GitHub and saw something crazy:</p>
<p><img src="/images/github-2k-contributions.jpg" alt="Screenshot of my GitHub contribution graph showing 2,054 contributions over the past year"></p>
<p>How in the hell did I end up with that many contributions? Well, I think I know why - it happened because of a couple related, small habits I have. I thought I'd share them with everyone else as a sort of trivia - maybe you can adopt these habits too! (Although hopefully because you think they're good ideas, not because you just want to make yourself look cool on GitHub.)</p>
<h2>Fix typos</h2>
<p>If projects are freedom-respecting, that means that anyone is welcome to contribute if they're able to offer something valuable. How many times have you seen a typo in some docs? GitHub makes it super, super easy to fix these (just click the pencil icon in the upper-right of GitHub file views), and they're a fantastic way to contribute a little back to projects. Even if you aren't reading docs on GitHub, it often doesn't take that much time to find where they're hosted (which is frequently GitHub anyway). Really good docs will even have a link to their source right on the generated page.</p>
<p>So whenever I see a typo, I send a Pull Request. It's become an automatic response to seeing something that needs fixing, and is pretty routine for me nowadays.</p>
<p>Oftentimes there are changes that aren't as easy as a typo, but are still super easy to fix. Take <a href="https://github.com/Homebrew/brew/pull/1634">this Homebrew PR</a> - I authored it on a tablet and it took me under 3 minutes to make the suggested change[1]. That's not a lot of effort, and it'll help lots of people looking for the Homebrew change log. The next time you find yourself thinking "it kinda sucks that..." ask yourself - can I fix this myself? And if you can, go for it! Even if you screw up, I promise most projects will want to help you out instead of making fun of you[2] - as someone who runs several freedom-respecting projects, I know that getting new contributors is very, very valuable and because of that I'll do a lot to make contributing a good experience. I would encourage everyone to, as Mike McQuaid puts it in that Homebrew PR, "be the change you want to see in the world."</p>
<p> [1]: of course, that's partly because I'm pretty good at git and grok things like <code>rebase -i</code>. But even if that's not you and it would take you longer, it sounds like a great opportunity to improve your git skills to me!</p>
<p> [2]: I feel obligated to point out that not every project is like this - there are some projects that have a terrible culture (*coughcough*Linuxkernel*cough*). Screw them. They're not that common in my experience and it's their loss, anyway. Don't let them deter you from trying to improve things outside of their bubble of suck.</p>
<h2>File issues</h2>
<p>I just talked about making small changes whenever you see something you can improve with a couple minutes' time. But what if you're in a hurry, or it would take longer?</p>
<p>Filing issues is a super easy way to solve this. Get into the habit of filing issues for everything that irks you[3] - you're not allowed to say "such-and-such a project sucks because it's buggy!" when you haven't told the developers about the bug you're experiencing!</p>
<p>Filing issues also takes very little time and is super helpful to the developer. Probably a lot of the people who read this blog are software developers, so I'm betting you can understand how great it is to receive an issue that gives you lots of details that you can then use to fix a bug or a design problem. So why not give the gift of issues? Just make sure to search for duplicates! (This accounts for a significant amount of those 2,000 contributions on my GitHub profile. Over the course of my time on GitHub, I've filed 619 issues, 438 of which were on other people's projects. Of course, that's just on GitHub - I also do this frequently <em>outside</em> of GitHub.)</p>
<p>Again, every time you find yourself saying, "why doesn't it..." or "I wish it..." or "it's so annoying when...", let the developer know! You'll help them make their project better.</p>
<p>  [3]: this is not to suggest that you file ridiculous issues that don't really say anything or just complain. But a focused bug report describing something concrete that's problematic is awesome.</p>
<h2>Publish by default</h2>
<p>This is the last and biggest habit I have that I think led to those 2k contributions: I publish everything by default, no matter what. It doesn't matter how bad or hacky or ugly I think a software project is, I just publish it. Because honestly, why not?</p>
<p>Keeping projects public doesn't get in anyone's way. It's not like someone will look at your GitHub and be <em>annoyed</em> that you give so much software to the world. And there's even a chance that your hacky script may actually be <em>useful</em> to someone. Even if I think a project is "bad" I'll still publish it because the reality is that no one is going to go around GitHub specifically trying to find people to make fun of.</p>
<p>Publishing projects also gives me incentive to clean them up - write a README, write tests, and keep a change log (if relevant). My standards are higher because I know all my work is all in the open - not because I'm afraid of other people telling me I'm doing it wrong, but because I want to create high quality code that has a better chance of being useful to the wider community.</p>
<h2>In summary</h2>
<p>All of these habits are related. The tl;dr is this: engage by default. Get used to being involved instead of shrugging off a problem and moving on. Put your work out there for other people to see. The open source/freedom-respcting software community belongs to everyone - and that means we can all contribute to improving it. We just have to start.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/how-i-passed-2k-github-contributions</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/how-i-passed-2k-github-contributions</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 17:46:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[RC week 6]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This is week 6 of being at the <a href="https://recurse.com">Recurse Center</a>. </p>
<p>(I feel obligated to point out that this is being published a week later than it's supposed to be because I got behind. I am, however, very confident that the following is accurate. I used GitHub history and location data to help me remember the parts that were fuzzy.)</p>
<script async="" defer="" src="https://www.recurse-scout.com/loader.js?t=3d49e64361d4b897ffd2fd56dcd93ca4"></script>
<h2>Day 19</h2>
<p>Not at RC. Total time at RC 0h0m.</p>
<p>Traveled back from <a href="https://fosdem.org/2017/">FOSDEM</a>.</p>
<h2>Day 20</h2>
<p>Arrived ~16:45, departed ~22:10, total time at RC 5h25m.</p>
<p>Somewhat unproductive day. Spent most of it just trawling the web. I was completely exhausted since I got back to my apartment from the airport at 3 in the morning. (My flight got in late, I waited at the airport for a while to see my sister, and at 12:30 I got on my train away from the AirTrain station except that it was in the wrong direction. Also, fun fact, subways and trains run <em>really</em> infrequently at 1 AM. Who knew!?)</p>
<p>I did, however, write the slides for the next day's Security Club presentation on the basics of cryptography. Started them pretty late, though, and mostly finished them at home, which was unfortunate since I was up real late again.</p>
<h2>Day 21</h2>
<p>Arrived ~13:00, departed ~22:00, total time at RC 9h0m.</p>
<p>Arrived with a little time to spare before teaching Cryptography Basics for Security Club. Didn't do much in the afternoon before leaving to walk down to the waterfront with 15 people or so, which took an hour and was really, really lovely, honestly. Especially since the Winter 1 batch is ending so soon.</p>
<h2>Day 22</h2>
<p>Arrived ~12:00, departed ~5:00, total time at RC 17h00m.</p>
<p>Spent the morning and early afternoon pairing with <a href="https://github.com/Jmeggesto">Jackie</a> on <a href="https://github.com/strugee/icalc">icalc</a>. We fixed a maddeningly weird bug where, when the user input an incorrect value, the operation type prompt would be displayed twice. You can see the fix <a href="https://github.com/strugee/icalc/commit/fb20487c5385cb0ae6192cd6540c98fbd82ff2d0#diff-2045016cb90d1e65d71c2407a2570927">here</a> - the problem was that <code>getchar()</code> was retrieving the newline used to "submit" the operation type when the function was called again (recursively). In other words, the stdin stream had <em>two</em> characters on it - the incorrect character, and the newline. The solution was to just use a different function from libc that did this correctly. The entire process was pretty educational, since it required delving into C strings, the libc manpages, etc. After fixing that, Jackie and I paired on <a href="https://github.com/Jmeggesto/bank-prettify">a JavaScript project</a> that will display Bank of America account balances on the commandline (a non-trivial problem, since Bank of America requires JavaScript).</p>
<p>In the late afternoon, switched gears a bit to review a PRISM Break PR.</p>
<p>In the evening, I gave a presentation at Thursday night presentations entitled "Mercurial for Git folks". I put zero effort into slides and instead simply opened up a bunch of tabs and terminal windows with content I wanted to point to while I was talking. Then I got up there and just... talked about why Mercurial is neat. At the beginning I asked who used Git (most hands, including mine, went up) and who hated Git (a fair number of hands, including mine, went up). So that was pretty amusing. I talked about how the design was pretty similar to Git, how Mercurial has extensions (because it's written in Python), how that plays into its "disable confusing/dangerous stuff like the staging area and rebase by default" philosophy, and how I've been learning it by just using <a href="https://hg-git.github.io/">hg-git</a> with GitHub. I thought it went pretty badly, because I didn't feel like it was very coherent. But the people I asked about it said it was actually pretty good, so that feels nice.</p>
<p>After that, we had the end-of-batch/goodbye Rose party. :'(</p>
<p>I spent a lot of time discussing politics and education with <a href="https://github.com/steph-rage">Stephanie</a>, which was lovely, and had some other long and interesting conversations that I wish I remember but don't, truthfully. Spent quite a bit of time with <a href="https://github.com/inytar">Pieter</a>, <a href="https://github.com/heatherbooker">Heather</a>, and David L messing around on top of the desk chairs, which completely filled Hopper. Eventually ended up sitting in Babbage with Rose, James, Heather, and some other folks (can't remember, honestly) just hanging out. We jacked the space heater way up so it felt like a sauna (aka reeeeeeal nice) and just talked about stuff. Around the 2-3 AM mark Heather and I got bundled up and went out to go to the pharmacy (which turned out to actually be literally right next door) and buy chocolate and nail polish. And then I spent somewhere between 1.5 to 2 hours painting my nails a fabulously sparkly red color called "Devil's Stare" from a brand called "Sinful Colors" - a combination which strikes me as being nothing short of <em>wild</em>.</p>
<p>At around 5 AM, everyone decided to go to sleep. I was the only person to go home, and honestly the only reason I did so was because I knew I'd want a shower in the morning. So I spent about 15 minutes trying to find the stupid switch to turn off the kitchen lights, finally gave up and went home, and fell asleep a short while after the sun rose.</p>
<h2>Friday</h2>
<p>Arrived ~18:00, departed ~1:15, total time at RC 7h15m. As always, Friday doesn't count as a day because RC is technically not in session.</p>
<p>Arrived exceedingly late since I woke up around, you know, 5. Got to RC and did very little before noticing a very large party leaving for dinner, which I joined and ate with (despite saying before I left that I'd had breakfast recently, so I "wasn't going to get anything"). We went out to get Chinese food, then went to a place that served Asian dessert of some kind (I've forgotten). It was beyond lovely, honestly.</p>
<p>(I also mentioned at dinner that I'd missed a week of blogging, so during a discussion with <a href="https://github.com/chirs">Chris</a> about it I posted to a Zulip topic named "shame AJ" soliciting ideas for a punishment as well as moving the regular Iron Blogger meeting to Tuesday due to the Spring 1 introduction day.)</p>
<h2>Executive summary</h2>
<p>This week was particularly unproductive. I only did a little bit of work on icalc, my C project, and other than that the only really RC-related project I did was my security club presentation on cryptography basics. This was mostly because my sleep schedule was super messed up from Brussels, and then got messed up again (just as it was getting back to normal) on Thursday.</p>
<p>This week was also very emotional, since it was the Winter 1s' last week. To all my Winter 1 friends: you made my time at RC amazing and welcoming and exciting and wonderful and I loved being around you all. And I will miss you for a very long time. &lt;3</p>
<p>(*<em>starts crying a lil bit</em>*)</p>
<p>Total time at RC 38 hours 40 minutes; cumulative time 239 hours 25 minutes.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/rc-week-6</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/rc-week-6</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2017 07:42:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Gender representation at RC]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>So I want to talk (real quick) about gender representation in tech. Specifically, the fact that it's abysmal. Women[1] usually account for, at most, <a href="https://www.cnet.com/news/women-in-tech-the-numbers-dont-add-up/">30% of the employees in a company</a> and that number is often much lower. Even at the companies where it's 30%, that number is misleading because it doesn't adress management positions which are often much lower. (For reference, women accounted for about 59% of the overall workforce as of 2015, when the article I pulled those numbers from was published.) <a href="http://fortune.com/2014/10/02/women-leave-tech-culture/">Here's an article</a> that says that on average, women leave the industry within 7 years of being in it. Let me repeat that, because I didn't say they leave their jobs, or take a break. They completely leave the <em>entire technology industry</em>. And unfortunately it makes sense, since incidents of sexism in tech are <a href="http://geekfeminism.wikia.com/wiki/Category:Incidents">rampant</a>.</p>
<p>Unlike (most of) the rest of the tech world, the <a href="https://recurse.com">Recurse Center</a> is mostly (completely?) gender-balanced. I want to point out that while for years I've believed in diversity, it didn't become clear to me how much <a href="https://www.opensocietyfoundations.org/voices/implicit-bias-and-social-justice">implicit bias</a> I held until I joined RC. I find that, having previously spent significant amounts of time in environments that were predominantly white, cis and male, <strong>I find myself needing to self-correct discriminatory and gender-based unconscious assumptions significantly less frequently at RC</strong>. In other words, my subconscious is making less incorrect, gender-based suggestions about what people are like that I then have to consciously reject. I would attribute this almost 100% to the fact that at RC I'm surrounded by lots of people who are a) super talented and know their shit and b) aren't male.</p>
<p>If I have a point to this blog post (and I'm not sure that I do), it'd be to underscore what many have said before me: representation and role models are important. Advocating for gender equality is good and important, but in the end what really matters is what's actually in people's heads. That's mostly influenced by what they see in their immediate lives, and that's why representation is so important - believing in equality is great, but presenting actual evidence to your subconscious that its biases are incorrect is a much more powerful way to improve the way you perceive the world.</p>
<p>If folks have any comments or different perspectives, I'd love to hear them <a href="https://strugee.net/contact">privately</a> or via <a href="https://webmention.net/">WebMention</a>.</p>
<p> [1]: I'm focusing on women here because I'm not aware of any statistics about non-binary people in tech. But it's worth noting that it's a huge problem for them, too.</p>
<p><strong>Update February 22nd:</strong> the lovely <a href="https://twitter.com/rhonorv">Rachel Vincent</a> from RC faculty says this about RC's gender-balancing:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Of the folks who are currently in-batch (Winter 2's and Spring 1's), ~36% identify as women. It's roughly the same for the community as a whole (~33%), though we don't have super accurate numbers because we don't update information on folks' gender. The most gender balanced batches were a little over 40% women. We're always pushing for 50/50, though. 😊 Our overall strategy is to try to get an applicant pool that is as gender balanced as possible, and we don't do any kind of balancing during the admissions process itself.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/gender-representation-at-rc</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/gender-representation-at-rc</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[musings]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2017 22:01:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[RC week 5]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This is week 5 of being at the <a href="https://recurse.com">Recurse Center</a>.</p>
<script async="" defer="" src="https://www.recurse-scout.com/loader.js?t=3d49e64361d4b897ffd2fd56dcd93ca4"></script>
<h2>Day 15</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:20, departed ~16:30, arrived ~20:00, departed ~23:30, total time at RC 9h40m.</p>
<p>Somehow managed to get up early and arrive at my checkin early, despite being dead-tired (I couldn't get to sleep so I was running on ~5 hours of sleep). Spent most of today working on my HTTPS presentation, but took 30 minutes to an hour or so off to make a couple small improvements to my website - mostly just trimming the projects page and adding information to the contact page about how to communicate securely with me. Left for a while to have dinner with a friend and returned via the subway[1] to work on my HTTPS presentation some more.</p>
<p>(Note 1/31: I felt quite productive today, but in hindsight really didn't get a whole lot done since I was just so tired.)</p>
<p> [1]: which truthfully made me feel unreasonably accomplished since my phone died right as I looked up directions, but I got on the right subway and figured out I could transfer and take a closer line halfway through and eventually made it back anyway</p>
<h2>Day 16</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:20, departed ~23:10, total time at RC 12h50m.</p>
<p>Spent - no joke - basically all of today working on my HTTPS presentation, which in addition to actually writing the content entailed reminding myself of how things like e.g. TLS False Start actually work. Reminding and/or properly learning (for False Start in particular I had a vague idea of how it worked before, but didn't really understand it).</p>
<p>Took about an hour off in the evening to help repaint a large stretch of wall in the space as part of the cleaning party. Then went back to HTTPS. Highly productive day.</p>
<h2>Day 17</h2>
<p>Arrived ~11:30, departed ~17:40, total time at RC 6h10m.</p>
<p>Caught up with some GitHub stuff in the morning before teaching HTTPS. We went for an hour and a half and <em>still</em> skipped the entire section on TLS performance because HTTPS is complicated and hacky and also <em>really</em> terrible. (As <a href="https://github.com/eeclaire">Claire</a> put it, "I'm now terrified of browsing the web." Me too, Claire. Me too.) I think it went really well, even though it was a little overwhelming for everyone at times.</p>
<p>Spent a bit of time watching YouTube videos on how Diffie-Hellmann works and how Elliptic-Curve Diffie-Hellman (ECDHE) works - we'd touched on both of these during the presentation and I needed to put them in Zulip. The one on plain Diffie-Hellmann was just a refresher, but the one on ECDHE was something I'd previously tried to watch <em>several</em> times and had always been too confused. But, this time I got it! Whooo! So that felt awesome.</p>
<p>Left early to go home and sqeeze in some laundry before closing out the evening by going to an RC-organized talk on <a href="https://crystal-lang.org/">Crystal</a>.</p>
<h2>Day 18</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:30, departed ~14:30, total time at RC 4h0m.</p>
<p>Did just a smidge of work on pump.io before going to Abstract Salad Factory, then heading home to catch my flight to Brussels.</p>
<h2>Friday</h2>
<p>Not at RC. Total time at RC 0h0m.</p>
<p>In Brussels for <a href="https://fosdem.org/2017/">FOSDEM</a>.</p>
<h2>Executive summary</h2>
<p>This week had its ups and downs. I was really productive on the HTTPS stuff, but other than that I didn't reeeally get a lot done.</p>
<p>Total time at RC 32 hours 40 minutes; cumulative time 230 hours 45 minutes.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/rc-week-5</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/rc-week-5</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 07:23:28 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>