<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[strugee.net blog - 'personal' category]]></title><description><![CDATA[strugee.net blog - 'personal' category]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/category/personal</link><generator>stratic-indexes-to-rss</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Dec 2018 09:00:39 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://strugee.net/blog/category/personal/index.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><copyright><![CDATA[© Copyright 2012-2018 AJ Jordan. Available under the GNU Affero GPL.]]></copyright><webMaster><![CDATA[AJ Jordan <alex@strugee.net>]]></webMaster><item><title><![CDATA[Legacy]]></title><description><![CDATA[<!-- Written to a subset of the World of Goo soundtrack -->
<p>Recently I turned 20 years old. As the days continue to go by, I have been struggling with the concept of time.</p>
<p>Probably this feeling started with me seeing photos of this year's SAAS robotics teams. I was on the robotics team for four years (I've <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2014/12/new-blog-new-site">written about it a little before</a>) but recently I found that all of a sudden, I know barely anyone in the photos. Fifteen people in robotics graduated[1] high school last year, people I've largely known since they were freshmen (or in the case of <a href="https://jessewalling.com/">Jesse</a> and <a href="https://matthewkelsey.com/">Matt</a>, even longer). Some of them are very close friends. And I have found that the way I think about <a href="http://www.redshiftrobotics.org/">Redshift Robotics</a> has changed: I don't quite think of it as something I used to be a part of, at least not that simply. Instead I think of it as my legacy.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>legacy: <em>n.</em> something handed down from an ancestor or a predecessor or from the past</p>
</blockquote>
<p><cite>- from The American Heritage® Dictionary of the English Language, 4th Edition, via <a href="https://www.wordnik.com/words/legacy">Wordnik</a></cite></p>
<p>I don't belong there anymore. FIRST Tech Challenge has changed since I've left. They play a different game than I did, they run their GitHub differently than I envisioned when I set it up, they have different mentors and leadership than we did, and I'm sure they practice and compete differently than we did. That's okay. But it's weird. I know exactly what they're thinking because I thought it too, years and years ago - to them, I am a vague echo in someone else's past; an accumulation of events that has shaped what the club is today but that they would never be able to name. I'm someone they've vaguely heard of, maybe, but never really known. What happens next is all in their hands and there's nothing I can or want to do about it; I witnessed a former mentor of SAAS robotics turn the entire club around and that's history they'll never have seen, and maybe will never even know about. But whatever is happening there now is something <em>I'll</em> never see, either.</p>
<p>Pretty soon there will be no students left at SAAS I still know. Two more very close friends graduate this year. It'll only take a year or two more after that before the last student I know personally is gone.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>There are places I remember all my life</br>
Though some have changed<br/>
Some forever, not for better<br/>
Some have gone and some remain.<br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p><cite>- The Beatles, In My Life</cite></p>
<p>I think maybe as time goes on I'm getting better at watching people grow and change. I'm on year two of college and already I see it happening - last year a close group of friends and I were just freshmen, bright-eyed and bushy-tailed. This year one's an RA, two are First-year Fellows[2] and I'm a D'Lion[3]. The rest are living their lives in upper-class housing. As I was sitting in the dining hall earlier tonight I thought, how lucky we are that we even met last year. We're all scattered around now, generally in wildly different departments, and we're all focusing on different next steps. Most of us live in different buildings from all the others, and I can't help but wonder if we would all have met later. I think the answer is probably no. Causality is a strange thing to me; the circumstances that brought us together are dead and gone and yet the friendship lives on. Legacy.</p>
<p>I see the world changing too. There was a point in my life where it seemed like nothing big and cosmic would ever change; it seemed like the world would adjust itself only in small details. But at some point that stopped being the case, when I wasn't watching. <a href="https://www.jamesporter.me/">James Porter</a>, who's part of the faculty at the <a href="https://www.recurse.com/">Recurse Center</a>, once told me that whenever new batches came in he was always super sad to see so many people he'd made friends with leave to be replaced by strangers he didn't know yet. But, he said, he never quite noticed the point where people in-batch switched from strangers to friends. That feeling of not noticing is how I feel about the world right now. And it just boggles the mind that I'm at an age now where I can actually say yeah, I've seen those things change. I see people even just a year or two younger than me so much more attached to their phones; I say "back in the day" unironically when I talk about tech things.</p>
<p>The traffic in Seattle has gotten worse, almost unbearable compared to what it once was. We didn't used to hear about wildfires like we do now; the country and the planet are <em>burning</em>. And above all else, <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2016/12/where-were-headed-aka-im-worried">the country is angrier</a>. So much angrier.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I turned 20 today. A question for people older and wiser than I: I feel incredibly weird to not be a "teenager" anymore, what the hell do I do???</p>
</blockquote>
<p><cite>- me, a couple days ago, on <a href="https://pump.strugee.net/alex/note/VRge4hnIQ1WM-Z1cJxwifA">pump.io</a> and on <a href="https://twitter.com/strugee2/status/1036789205245018112">Twitter</a></cite></p>
<p>Footnotes:</p>
<p>[1]: and we all know how I feel about <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/06/graduation-2017-reflections-on-365-days-of-gap-yearing">graduations</a>.</p>
<p>[2]: upper-class student at University of Rochester who lives with first-years and helps them with academic stuff (especially course registration)</p>
<p>[3]: like a First-year Fellow except instead of academic stuff, they help bring their hall together and make sure everyone's having a good time and making friends, etc.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2018/09/legacy</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2018/09/legacy</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 23:01:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Going to IndieWeb Summit 2018]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Once again, I'll be <data class="p-rsvp" value="yes">attending</data> the <a href="https://2018.indieweb.org/" class="u-in-reply-to">IndieWeb Summit</a> this year. Probably I'll work on <a href="https://github.com/strugee/lazymention">lazymention</a> and the <a href="https://github.com/strugee/strugee.github.com/tree/social-stream"><code>social-stream</code> branch</a> of this website. Maybe I'll work on <a href="https://stratic.js.org/">Stratic</a> too! I'm super excited.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2018/05/going-to-indieweb-summit-2018</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2018/05/going-to-indieweb-summit-2018</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 18:14:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[New temporary signing keys]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>So unfortunately, recently I have lost my Nitrokey, which I liked very much. In addition to this being fairly upsetting, I am now left with the sticky situation of not being able to sign code - while I have a master key (from which I can generate new subkeys), I'm currently at college and my copy of the key is sitting 3,000 miles away at home.</p>
<p>To get around this situation, I've generated a temporary signing keypair. This keypair is set to expire after 3 months (and I don't intend to renew it). When I have access to my master keypair, I will revoke the old subkeys, generate new subkeys (it was probably time, anyway) and revoke the temporary keypair.</p>
<p>The new fingerprint is <code>D825FD54D9B940FF0FFFB31AA4FDB7BE12F63EC3</code>. I have uploaded the key to <a href="https://github.com/strugee.gpg">GitHub</a> as well as the Ubuntu keyserver and <code>keys.gnupg.net</code> (just as my original was). The key is also incorporated into my Keybase account so that you can bootstrap trust in it, if you want to verify software signatures or whatever.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2018/04/new-temporary-signing-keys</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2018/04/new-temporary-signing-keys</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[security]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2018 23:01:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Winter break retrospective & spring semester goals]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Tonight I'll have been back at college for a full week, and I wanted to write up a little retrospective of winter break to see what I accomplished (and in particular, which <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/12/winter-break-priorities-2017-18">goals</a> I completed or missed).</p>
<p>You may wish to skip directly to the <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/#executive-summary">executive summary</a>.</p>
<h1>Resolved goal: Node.js manpage PR</h1>
<p>I didn't <em>complete</em> this goal per se, but I did at least resolve it <a href="https://github.com/nodejs/node/pull/14164#issuecomment-357909699">by closing the Pull Request</a>. I felt pretty bad about it (especially because I kept saying I intended to finish it) but honestly, it became clear to me that I'd just lost the motivation to keep going with it. I would love it if this was included in Node.js core, but I just consistently have higher priorities. So rather than leave it hanging and cluttering up the Pull Requests view, I just closed it to reflect reality. I made sure not to delete the branch though, in case someone (distant future me?) wants to pick it up again.</p>
<h1>Failed goal: deal with GPG keysigning</h1>
<p>I did nothing to push this goal forward. While I made <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2018/01/improving-gpg-security">numerous improvements to my GPG setup</a>, I did not actually sign anyone's key, which was what this goal was about. This feels unfortunate. (I also do not have access to the private key material in college, and am <em>certainly</em> not about to ask that it be shipped to me.)</p>
<h1>Partially completed goal: push Debian packaging work forward</h1>
<p>There were two components to this: <a href="https://tracker.debian.org/pkg/profanity">Profanity packaging</a> upgrades and getting the new <a href="https://github.com/strugee/filter-other-days">filter-other-days</a> packaging into Debian. I made no progress on the Profanity packaging. However, I did <a href="https://github.com/strugee/dots/commit/2b477a7079de9ff675fd4e2d22f58938ffbb7bc9">fix a misconfiguration in my <code>.reportbugrc</code></a> (which annoyingly had previously sent my incredibly detailed email about Profanity packaging to <code>/dev/null</code>) and then submitted <a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=886310">an ITP</a> (Intent To Package bug, which is a Debian thing) for filter-other-days. I then used that ITP bug number <a href="https://github.com/strugee/filter-other-days/commit/d09943c6ac4eea07720cc88596bed3594c3f4644">to fix the last <code>.deb</code> Lintian warning</a> (although see below). Then I paired with <a href="https://github.com/anjakefala">Anja</a> who is, as always, an angel, and we figured out the weirdness that is <code>dput</code> and <a href="https://mentors.debian.net/">mentors.debian.net</a>. Finally I was able to upload filter-other-days(!) BUT I was in for a rude awakening - apparently Lintian checks for <code>.deb</code>s and <code>.dsc</code>s are different. So while my binary package was Lintian-clean, my source package unfortunately wasn't. This is something I will need to work on in the weeks to come. That being said, I'm still pretty proud of what I've accomplished here! I've made significant progress on this front.</p>
<h1>Completed goal: lazymention v1</h1>
<p>One of the first things I did was ship lazymention 1.0.0 - and I wrote <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/12/announcing-lazymention-elegant-outbound-webmention-for-static-sites">an announcement blog post</a> to accompany it! (In fact, I syndicated that blog post to <a href="https://news.indieweb.org/">IndieNews</a> <em>using lazymention</em>, which felt pretty damn awesome.) I got some great feedback on it from the IndieWeb community, and my <a href="https://lobste.rs/s/kip3yk/announcing_lazymention_elegant">lobste.rs submission</a> - which also got some great engagement - even made the front page, which was pretty unreal! I still have a lot more work to do with lazymention - in particular, it doesn't actually respect edits (so it'll resend Webmentions with every job submission) - but for now it works well. I'm super pleased with it, and have integrated it into my site deployment workflow. I even wrote <a href="https://github.com/strugee/ping-lazymention/">a module</a> so other people can do this, too!</p>
<h1>Failed goals: ActivityPub in pump.io core, pump.io PR review</h1>
<p>No progress on this front. I did start hacking on a <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/telemetry">telemetry server</a> which will eventually be helpful for our ActivityPub rollout, but that did not in any way <em>directly</em> help fulfill these goals. I also <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2018/01/pump.io-5.1-stable-published-to-npm">released 5.1 stable</a>, but that's pretty routine by this point.</p>
<h1>Partially completed goal: two blog posts per week</h1>
<p>I stuck with this goal all the way up until the final week, where I didn't write any. (Although I wrote about my <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2018/01/improving-gpg-security">GPG keys</a> around the time I actually flew back to college.) The first week, I wrote about <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/12/shell-script-is-one-of-the-purest-forms-of-human-expression">my thoughts on shell script</a> and about <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/12/announcing-lazymention-elegant-outbound-webmention-for-static-sites">lazymention</a>; the second, I wrote about the <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2018/01/pump.io-5.1-stable-published-to-npm">pump.io 5.1 stable release</a> and about <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2018/01/tell-your-pr-reviewers-theyre-wrong">talking to Pull Request reviewers if you think they're wrong</a>.</p>
<h1>Failed stretch goal: paper editing</h1>
<p>I did absolutely no editing on the paper I intend to get published (which I originally wrote for a writing class). This was a stretch goal though, so that's totally fine.</p>
<h1>Additional activity: steevie maintenance</h1>
<p>After I finally found the cable I needed, I swapped out the cable that connects steevie's motherboard with the drives' SATA ports. This seemed to significantly improve disk performance, although there are still noticeable performance problems. I'm very, <em>very</em> happy to have finally gotten this done.</p>
<h1>Additional activity: Tor relay migration from Amazon EC2 to DigitalOcean</h1>
<p>After getting some advice on <a href="https://lists.torproject.org/cgi-bin/mailman/listinfo/tor-relays">tor-relays</a>, I <em>finally</em> sat down and looked into moving my relay away from Amazon Web Services. This is because AWS bills by usage, which for a Tor relay ends up being incredibly inefficient. It turned out to actually be way easier than I thought, which only served to make me mad that I hadn't done it sooner. In any case, I now save approximately $240/year AND I can push 1000GB/month as opposed to the 10GB/month I pushed before. In the words of <a href="https://github.com/strugee/torrc/commit/8b9fe85378adc834b8b7a9953de45f508b76bc3e">the commit where I made this change</a>: "this change made possible by the fact that I'm no longer getting billed up the wazoo by Amazon Web Services." Here's a of <a href="https://atlas.torproject.org/#details/C3CFCC9B5993A6F0D1349858C598C4A78AFE51F9">a Tor Metrics graph</a> (captured today) that shows the jump:</p>
<p><img src="/images/tor-relay-graph.svg" alt="Tor Metrics graph"></p>
<p>Anyway, I'm super happy I can contribute more to the Tor network <em>and</em> save lots of money in the process. That being said I am pretty damn salty I didn't realize this in the four <em>years</em> I've been running a Tor relay.</p>
<h1>Additional activity: offandonagain.org maintenance</h1>
<p>After turning on <a href="https://nodesecurity.io/">NodeSecurity</a> monitoring for <a href="https://offandonagain.org">offandonagain.org</a>, I found out that the module that underlies it, <a href="https://github.com/strugee/node-serve-random">node-serve-random</a>, had some vulnerable dependencies. Not only did I fix this, I wrote a large test suite for the module and found (and fixed!) <a href="https://github.com/strugee/node-serve-random/blob/master/CHANGELOG.md#200---2018-01-13">several bugs</a> in the process. Writing a test suite also allowed me to turn on <a href="https://greenkeeper.io/">Greenkeeper</a> for the module, which will be a huge help to me in keeping the module up-to-date.</p>
<h1>Additional activity: Stratic work</h1>
<p>First off, I released <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/generator-stratic/blob/master/CHANGELOG.md#100-beta-7---2017-12-3">beta 7</a> of <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/generator-stratic">generator-stratic</a>! Nothing major, just some polishing stuff. Stratic is getting very close to the point where I might want to start promoting it more aggressively, or declaring it stable, and (with a <em>lot</em> of super-helpful feedback from my family) I worked on something that's super important before we get there: <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/RFCs/issues/22">a logo</a>!</p>
<p>Here are two of my favorites so far:</p>
<div class="two-image-container">
<p><img src="/images/stratic-logo-asteroid-with-pipe.svg" alt="Yellow background with a centered black file icon and a asteroid coming up from earth in the midddle and a pipe to the right"> <img src="/images/stratic-logo-rocket-with-pipe.svg" alt="Yellow background with a centered black file icon and a rocket coming up from earth in the midddle and a pipe to the right"></p>
</div>
<p>These are based off the JS logo, in case you hadn't seen it before:</p>
<p><img src="/images/js-logo.svg" alt="Black JS text in the bottom-right corner of a yellow background"></p>
<p>Anyway, I have to post another iteration in the <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/RFCs/issues/22">GitHub issue</a> based on some feedback from <a href="http://saul.pw/">Saul</a> (who I had a lovely lunch with) - he thinks I should reverse it so the pipe is on the left, so it looks like the file is coming out of the pipe. But anyway you should comment there if you have feedback!</p>
<h1>Additional activity: IndieWeb stuff</h1>
<p>I attended Homebrew Website Club in San Fransisco, which was <em>incredible</em>. I got to meet a bunch of new people, as well as say hi to <a href="http://snarfed.org/">Ryan</a> and <a href="http://tantek.com/">Tantek</a> again, which was so nice - it's always just <em>better</em> to talk in real life. Tantek said (at least if I recall correctly) that my laptop was one of the best-stickered laptops he'd ever seen, which made me feel just unbelievably special. He also gave me a <a href="http://microformats.org/">microformats</a> sticker (and helped me figure out where to put it), which I had on my old laptop and had been really missing, as well as a <a href="https://letsencrypt.org/">Let's Encrypt</a> sticker. The latter was so special I elected to put it on the inside of my laptop, which I reserve only for <em>really</em> special things (basically a <a href="https://www.recurse.com/">Recurse Center</a> refucktoring sticker and a sticker of <a href="https://github.com/SwartzCr">Noah</a> in <a href="https://www.eff.org/encrypt-the-web">this video</a>, which he handed to me like a business card the first time we met). Anyway, every time I look at the Let's Encrypt sticker I just feel so happy. I love Let's Encrypt so damn much.</p>
<p>Homebrew Website Club was super inspiring, so when I got back to where I was staying (at my mom's boyfriend's house) I started implementing an <a href="https://indieweb.org">IndieWeb</a>-style social stream for strugee.net. It still needs some polishing but is actually pretty close to being done. Who knows when I'll have time to finish it, but it's getting there! I'm so freaking excited, honestly. Also, I added proper timestamp mf2 metadata to my site, as well as a visual display for post edits, and I expanded what type of Webmentions the display code recognizes too!</p>
<!-- TODO nuke this when I actually do proper header anchors -->
<p><span id="executive-summary"></span></p>
<h1>Executive summary</h1>
<p>I resolved or completed 2 goals, partially completed 2 goals, failed 3 goals, and failed 1 stretch goal. Additionally I did significant work in 5 other areas. Out of the goals I set for myself, I completed 51% (Debian packaging work is ~2/5 complete; blog posts were written 2/3 of the time); not counting the stretch goal, I completed 61.2%. I'm pretty happy with what I got done during this period; however, while I was productive, the numbers show that I did a mediocre job sticking to my goals. In the future I should focus on making more realistic goals and then sticking to them (though not too much - it is a break, after all!).</p>
<p>Speaking of which, partway through break I felt like I was on the edge of burnout, which to me was a <em>very</em> clear sign that I was pushing myself way too hard during a time I should have been unwinding. Because of that I cut what I was doing a <em>lot</em>, which helped pretty dramatically. In fact, I think without that I wouldn't have been able to do some of the later stuff, like all the IndieWeb work. So that's another reason I have to find a way to balance sticking to goals and just relaxing (which doesn't necessarily mean not coding, just doing whatever coding I feel like in the moment) - I feel like I was pushing myself too hard to meet my goals (and then getting distracted and not meeting them) and that's what led to the feeling. Obviously there are different constraints for e.g. schoolwork; here I'm referring <em>only</em> to free time like breaks.</p>
<h1>Spring semester goals</h1>
<p>With that in mind, I want to set some very broad goals for spring semester. I may update this list as time goes on, but for now I have four overarching goals I want to accomplish (besides the usual day-to-day code maintenance stuff):</p>
<ul>
<li>Finish editing the paper I wrote last semester on freedom-respecting software and intersectionality, and get it published</li>
<li>Make <em>some</em> measurable progress on my <a href="https://github.com/strugee/draft-webpush-2fa">Push-based Two-factor Authentication IETF draft</a></li>
<li>Get access to the University of Rochester darkroom and start developing/printing photos again</li>
<li>Start pushing the University of Rochester library (and <em>maybe</em> the journalism department?) to start adopting Tor technologies</li>
</ul>
<p>I'm excited to see how it goes!</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2018/01/winter-break-retrospective</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2018/01/winter-break-retrospective</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2018 20:51:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Improving GPG security]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Recently I've been putting some effort into improving the security of my <a href="https://strugee.net/gpg">GPG key</a> setup, and I thought I would take a moment to document it since I'm really excited!</p>
<h1>Nitrokey</h1>
<p>First, and most importantly, I have recently acquired a <a href="https://www.nitrokey.com/">Nitrokey Storage</a>. After I initialized the internal storage keys (which took a <em>really</em> long time), I used <code>gpg --edit-key</code> to edit my local keyring. I selected my first subkey, since in my day-to-day keyring the master key's private component is stripped, and issued <code>keytocard</code> to move the subkey to the Nitrokey. Then I repeated the process for the other subkey.</p>
<p>In the middle of this I <em>did</em> run into an annoying issue: GPG was giving me errors about not having a pinentry, even though the <code>pinentry-curses</code> and <code>pinentry-gnome3</code> packages were <em>clearly</em> installed. I had been dealing with this issue pretty much since I set up the system, and I had been working around it by issuing <code>echo "test" | gpg2 --pinentry-mode loopback --clearsign &gt; /dev/null</code> every time I wanted to perform a key operation. This worked because I was forcing GPG to not use the system pinentry program and instead just prompt directly on the local TTY; since I had put in the password, <code>gpg-agent</code> would then have the password cached for a while so I could do the key operation without GPG needing to prompt for a password (and thus without the pinentry error). However, this didn't seem to work for <code>--edit-key</code>, which I found supremely annoying.</p>
<p>However this turned out to be a good thing because it forced me to <em>finally</em> deal with the issue. I tried lots of things in an effort to figure out what was going on: I ran <code>dpkg-reconfigure pinentry-gnome3</code>, <code>dpkg-reconfigure gnupg2</code>, and I even manually ran <code>/usr/bin/pinentry</code> to make sure it was working. Turns out that, like many helpful protocols, the pinentry protocol lets you send <code>HELP</code>, and if you do so you'll get back a really nice list of possible commands. I played around with this and was able to get GNOME Shell to prompt me for a password, which was then echoed back to me in the terminal!</p>
<p>Despite feeling cool because of that, I still had the pinentry problem. So finally I just started searching all the GPG manpages for mentions of "pinentry". I looked at <code>gpg(1)</code> first, which was unhelpful, and then I looked at <code>gpgconf(1)</code>. That one was also <em>mostly</em> unhelpful, but the "SEE ALSO" section <em>did</em> make me think to look at <code>gpg-agent(1)</code>, where I hit upon the solution. Turns out <code>gpg-agent(1)</code> has a note about pinentry programs right at the very top, in the "DESCRIPTION" section:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Please make sure that a proper pinentry program has been installed under the default filename (which is system dependent) or use the option <code>pinentry-program</code> to specify the full name of that program.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The mention of the <code>pinentry-program</code> option led me pretty immediately to my solution. I had originally copied my <code>.gnupg</code> directory from my old MacBook Pro, and apparently GPGTools - a Mac package that integrated GPG nicely with the environment (as well as providing a GUI I never used) - had added its own <code>pinentry-program</code> line to <code>gpg-agent.conf</code>. That line pointed at a path installed by GPGTools, which of course didn't exist on my new Linux system. As soon as I removed the line, <code>--edit-key</code> worked like a charm. (I've also just added <code>gpg-agent.conf</code> to my <a href="https://github.com/strugee/dots/blob/master/.gnupg/gpg-agent.conf">dotfiles</a> so I notice this kind of thing in the future.)</p>
<p>So far, I'm really enjoying my Nitrokey. It works really well and the app is pretty good, although the menu can be pretty glitchy sometimes. I've used the password manager for a couple high-security passwords (mostly bank passwords) which is great, and I've switched my two-factor authentication for GitHub from FreeOTP on my phone to the Nitrokey since GitHub is a super important account and I really want to make sure people can't push code as me.</p>
<p>There are only two problems I've had with the Nitrokey so far. The first is that it's slow. I notice a significant pause when I do any crypto operation, probably somewhere between a half a second to a second. This hits me quite often since I sign all my Git commits; however I suspect I'll get used to this, and the security benefits are well worth the wait anyway. The other problem is that the Nitrokey doesn't support FIDO U2F authentication. This wasn't a surprise (I knew it wouldn't when I was shopping models) but is nevertheless a problem I would like to deal with (which means getting a second device). The basic reason is just that U2F is newer than the Nitrokey I have. Other than those, though, I would highly recommend Nitrokey. The device is durable, too - I just carry it around in my pocket. (I briefly considered putting it on my keychain - for those of you who haven't met me in person, I have my keychain on an easily-detachable connector attached to a belt loop - but I decided against it because my keychain is kinda hefty.)</p>
<h1>Keybase</h1>
<p>In addition to the Nitrokey, I've also finally started using <a href="https://keybase.io/">Keybase</a>!</p>
<p>For a long time I wasn't too sure about Keybase. I felt like people should really be meeting in person and doing keysigning parties, and I didn't like that they encourage you to upload a private key to them, even if it's password-protected. Eventually I softened my position a little bit and got an invite from <a href="https://keybase.io/yawnbox">Christopher Sheats</a> (back then you needed an invite) but I only made it halfway through the install process before getting distracted and forgetting about it for, you know, several years.</p>
<p>This time, though, I decided to finally get my act together. Do I still kinda think it's a bummer that Keybase encourages private key uploads? Sure. Are real-life keysignings better? <em>Absolutely</em>. But even though they're better, a lot of experience trying to do them and teach them has thoroughly convinced me that they're just too impractical. There are lots of people who might need to at least have <em>some</em> trust in my key - for example, to verify software signatures - and this is a pretty decent solution for them. Not to mention a novel and interesting solution. Plus, it's possible to use Keybase in such a way that you're not compromising security in any way, which is the way I do it.</p>
<p>So tl;dr: I'm on the Keybase bandwagon now. <a href="https://keybase.io/strugee">My profile</a> is also now linked to from my <a href="https://strugee.net/gpg">GPG keys</a> page.</p>
<h1>Safe for master key</h1>
<p>Finally, my dad's wife's safe has recently been moved into our house and is conveniently sitting next to my computer. Currently, I keep my master key in a file on a flash drive with an encrypted LUKS container. When I need to access my master key, this file gets unlocked with <code>cryptsetup</code> and then mounted somewhere on my laptop, and I pass the <code>--homedir</code> option to <code>gpg</code> to point it at the mount location. This is better than just keeping the master lying around day-to-day, but still pretty unideal as I'm exposing it to a potentially compromised, non-airgapped computer. Therefore I plan to get a Raspberry Pi (or something similar) and put it in the safe so I can use it as a fully trusted computer that's never been connected to the internet (and is therefore <em>very</em> hard to compromise). I'll keep the Pi in the safe to provide greater assurance that it hasn't been tampered with, as well as to provide a physical level of redundancy for the key material's security. This will hopefully happen Real Soon Now™ - I can't wait!</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2018/01/improving-gpg-security</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2018/01/improving-gpg-security</guid><category><![CDATA[security]]></category><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2018 23:01:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Winter break priorities, 2017-18]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>So I just wanted to write something up real fast to document my development priorities over my upcoming winter break (which starts tomorrow, whoohoo!). This is just generally useful to have, because I'm forgetful, but will also help keep me accountable since the list is public.</p>
<p>So, here are the projects I want to get done, in rough order of priority:</p>
<ol>
<li>Polish up an <a href="https://github.com/nodejs/node/pull/14164#issuecomment-325553163">outstanding Node.js Pull Request</a> that automatically generates manpages for every module shipped with Node core</li>
<li>Deal with GPG key signing which I have been procrasinating on for, well, years now</li>
<li>Push some Debian packaging work forward (I've done some work to get the <a href="https://tracker.debian.org/pkg/profanity">Profanity packaging</a> up-to-date, and I want to get <a href="https://github.com/strugee/filter-other-days">filter-other-days</a> into Debian as well)</li>
<li>Finish up v1 of <a href="https://github.com/strugee/lazymention">lazymention</a> - high-priority since it's so close to being done!</li>
<li>Finally push through and implement <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/issues/1241">ActivityPub in pump.io core</a></li>
<li>Clear <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/pulls">the backlog of PRs</a> sent to pump.io</li>
</ol>
<p>I also am setting a goal of writing at least two blog posts per week, and I want to try to get some editing done on a paper I'm planning to try to get published (though I'm not sure if I'll end up doing this, honestly).</p>
<p>That seems like a lot, honestly, and yet I feel like I must have missed something - I will update this list if I think of anything else!</p>
<p>Cheers, and happy holidays everyone! \o/</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/12/winter-break-priorities-2017-18</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/12/winter-break-priorities-2017-18</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 17:44:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Not going to today's HWC San Francisco]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Testing whether my new Webmention implementation, <a href="https://github.com/strugee/lazymention">lazymention</a> (which will ship Real Soon Now™), will send a Webmention to note that I will <data class="p-rsvp" value="no">NOT be attending</data> today's <a href="http://tantek.com/2017/319/e1/homebrew-website-club" class="u-in-reply-to">Homebrew Website Club San Francisco</a>! Though let's be honest, I really want to.</p>
<p>(With &lt;3 for <a href="https://chat.indieweb.org/social/2017-11-15#t1510774596509000">Tantek</a>)</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/11/not-going-to-todays-hwc-san-fransisco-2017</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/11/not-going-to-todays-hwc-san-fransisco-2017</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2017 14:43:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Going to IndieWeb Summit 2017]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I'll be <data class="p-rsvp" value="yes">attending</data> the <a href="https://2017.indieweb.org/" class="u-in-reply-to">IndieWeb Summit</a> this year (well, the first day). Hopefully I'll write a way to actually post notes and RSVPs properly on this site, instead of sketchily writing the HTML by hand, which is what I did for this RSVP.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/06/going-to-indieweb-summit-2017</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/06/going-to-indieweb-summit-2017</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2017 02:09:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Graduation 2017: reflections on 365 days of gap yearing]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Tonight marks the end of the high school careers for everyone in Seattle Academy's Class of 2017. Congratulations to everyone who graduated tonight - you deserve it, seriously. To my friends in particular, I'm so proud of you guys! You're completely amazing, you've done such incredible things and I love you very much.</p>
<p>Attending the Class of 2017's graduation was <em>super</em> strange for me too, honestly, because I'm such a radically different person than back when I was on that stage.</p>
<p>This year I put out <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2016/08/pump.io-1.0.0-is-now-available">several</a> <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2016/11/pump.io-2.0.1-is-available">major</a> <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/04/pump.io-4.0-in-beta">releases</a> (and a couple minor ones too) of <a href="http://pump.io">pump.io</a>, the decentralized social networking software I maintain; I <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/05/pump.io-accident">became an Invited Expert</a> at the World Wide Web Consortium and I wrote the software that powers this blog - <a href="https://github.com/straticjs">Stratic</a> - from scratch. I spoke at some major technical conferences on <a href="https://media.libreplanet.org/u/libreplanet/m/pump-io-the-federated-extensible-social-network/">pump.io</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a9l-FmSgyt8">Stratic</a>, too. But mostly what I was thinking about tonight was all the personal development I went through. As some who are close to me in real life know (particularly those who were there), a year ago I was relatively seriously depressed. There were actually a <em>lot</em> of reasons for this, but one of the most important was the trouble I had dealing with change - the biggest change, of course, being leaving high school: somewhere familiar, somewhere with friends.</p>
<p>I vividly remember sitting in the seats just under the stage in McCaw Hall the day of graduation as the SAAS people running the show showed us where to walk and what to do. I leaned over to my friend and said, "I don't think I'll understand what's happening here for a very long time," to which she said, "what, like where we walk and stuff?" I chuckled and said nevermind, because what I was really referring to was what was happening in a grander sense - what this event really meant and was for, on the scale of years and decades (I couldn't find words for this at the time).</p>
<p>I don't really know what it felt like to walk out on stage for other people (both this year and last year) but for me, it seemed almost trivial, like a non-event. It didn't feel nearly as momentous as it seemed like it should. Based on my description my therapist would later refer to it as a foregone conclusion, a description that stuck with me given how accurately it seemed to verbalize what I was feeling. It just didn't feel big, but I <em>knew</em> that it <em>was</em>. In the grand sense, I just really didn't understand what was happening.</p>
<p>Tonight, watching the Class of 2017, I think I started to get it. The crux of my personal development was being at the <a href="https://recurse.com">Recurse Center</a>. In fact, applying to and attending the Recurse Center was without a shadow of a doubt the highlight of not just my year but my entire <em>life</em>. I love my friends and teachers at SAAS very deeply, and I still think going to SAAS was a great choice. But at the Recurse Center, I felt at home, like I belonged, in a way I just never felt in high school. Plus, it felt pretty great to live on my own in New York City, feeling like I knew my way around the subway system[1], how to get food for myself (whether at the supermarket to cook or from nearby restaurants), and just what it <em>felt</em> like to live in such an amazing place.</p>
<p>There was a moment in senior year, in Jason's English class, when I was thinking about my then-sophomore friends and wondering if I'd see them in ten or even twenty years. After all, they'd probably have separate class reunions. And right as I started to wonder what we'd all even <em>be</em> like then, it hit me that the idea of "growing up" is bullshit. No one is ever truly "grown up"; people just slide along a scale from toddler to wise elder. Every human always will be and always has been a work in progress - always growing, always changing. I am incredibly proud of all the technical work I did this year. I am unbelievably grateful and happy to have made so many amazing friends at the Recurse Center, and I feel very lucky to have such good mental health - mentally I'm probably in the best place I've ever been in my whole life. But even with all that, I know I'm still young. I still have lots of room to grow and there are more exciting opportunities ahead of me than ever.</p>
<p>When everyone's in the middle of something, I think they get lost in the moment. In my senior year, my whole life was structured around being in senior year; at the Recurse Center, my whole life revolved around the Recurse Center. Essentially, I'm describing the act of putting your head down and concentrating on something. So maybe what graduation (and important events like it) is really about is a chance to suspend time; to not be lost in the moment. A chance to, just for a second, not have your life revolve around anything in particular and instead, look at yourself and the way you've changed and continue to change over your lifetime. Like a character arc. It really is amazing, and in a way, isn't that implicitly what graduation's saying anyway? Graduation is an event designed to celebrate everything that the people on stage have accomplished - and in order to celebrate something, you have to sit back and look at it.</p>
<p>It was honestly <em>wild</em> to watch the people on stage talk about each other and their lives for the past four years, recalling both the time when I felt the <em>exact same way</em> they do now as well as just how much I, and my perspective, have changed. To the Class of 2017, as someone who was in your shoes a year ago - I know I sound stupid and clichéd, but your world is about to become so much bigger than you can imagine. SAAS, which once seemed like such a monumental, immovable part of your life, will instead become small (though still important). At least, that's what happened to me. I hope it does for you, too. And I'm really excited for you guys.</p>
<p>Congratulations once again. You guys freaking did it.</p>
<p>Footnotes:</p>
<p> [1]: the operative word being "feeling", because I almost certainly didn't know my way around <em>nearly</em> as well as I felt I did</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/06/graduation-2017-reflections-on-365-days-of-gap-yearing</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/06/graduation-2017-reflections-on-365-days-of-gap-yearing</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[musings]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2017 00:46:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[How I accidentally started maintaining a social network with thousands of users]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>As some of my readers (particularly Recursers) know, a couple of weeks ago I became an Invited Expert at the <a href="https://www.w3.org/wiki/Socialwg">Social Working Group</a> at the <a href="https://www.w3.org/">W3C</a> (World Wide Web Consortium). The W3C is a standards body. That means it's responsible for defining things like how things work on the web, such as how web pages are styled using CSS and how web developers can protect their apps from security vulnerabilities using <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/CSP3/">Content Security Policy</a>.</p>
<p>My first thought when I got the email that my application had been accepted was, "<em><strong>WHOOOOOOOOO!</strong></em>" It was probably one of the most thrilling moments of my whole life. My second thought was, "how in the <em>world</em> did I get here!?" The truth is, it was almost an accident.</p>
<p>It started when I got involved in the <a href="http://pump.io">pump.io</a> project. pump.io, for those who haven't heard me talk about this endlessly (e.g. at RC), is a decentralized social network. That means that there can be multiple servers run by different people that are part of the social network, but the users on those servers can interact with each other in just the same way they could if it was just one big centralized server[1]. I first got involved in the pump.io project in August 2015. I was experimenting with different social networking software and decided to <a href="https://pump.strugee.net/">deploy</a> pump.io on my server. When I did I realized that pump... well, it didn't work very well. The web UI was kinda basic[2], everything was pretty buggy, and there were a lot of problems with the overall user experience. In fact, I know the exact day I set up pump.io (August 12th) because all throughout the experience <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/issues/1093">I</a> <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/issues/1094">was</a> <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/issues/1095">filing</a> <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/issues/1096">bugs</a> on things needing improvement. It was a shame, I thought, because this software seemed really neat. I thought it had a lot of potential.</p>
<p>After about two weeks it became clear that there was no activity in the upstream pump.io project. So after some deliberation, I ended up forking it (briefly). You can watch <a href="https://media.libreplanet.org/u/libreplanet/m/pump-io-the-federated-extensible-social-network/">this talk</a> around 16:00 to hear me talk about this a bit, though to be honest it's kind of just a footnote in the project's history. In the end Evan Prodromou, pump.io's author, ended up handing off some commit rights to community members.</p>
<p>Well, I thought, that was the end of that. Everything's smooth sailing from here on out! There were some big problems, though: the people who now had commit rights all were involved in other things and, more importantly, none of them knew JavaScript or Node.js! This makes me chuckle to this day, honestly.</p>
<p>So I started triaging issues. When people sent Pull Requests, I'd review them since it seemed like no one else was going to do it. <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/pull/1114">#1114</a> was, as far as I can tell (or remember), the very first of these "unofficial" PR reviews. I kept going; I even reviewed Menno Vossen's <a href="https://github.com/pump-io/pump.io/pull/1136">epic PR which fixed all the tests</a> (fixing the tests being a feat which, having tried to start that work myself, I am to this day in awe of and <em>incredibly</em> thankful for). For that last one in particular, you'll note that <em>I</em> merged it, not Chris Webber. At some point in January(?), he asked me in <code>#pump.io</code> on IRC if I'd like write access to the repository, to which I said (paraphrased) "heck yes!" So he made it happen.</p>
<p>I never really intended for that to happen. However, I <em>was</em> the one doing almost all of the work. After a while it just made sense. This is what, among other things, I find so incredible about freedom-respecting software: you can just <em>do</em> things. I didn't ask anyone for permission to do those reviews. I just saw the need for a reviewer, and decided I'd help out.</p>
<p>Fast-forward to today, and I'm now an owner of the pump.io organization on GitHub. I make technical decisions about what to prioritize and what should go into pump.io core. I do a lot of the day-to-day work running the project, too, and setting up technical and policy infrastructure (with a lot of help from the community, of course, plus input from Evan). That, too, just made sense, as did my becoming an Invited Expert - I was pretty deeply engaged with the SocialWG's <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/">ActivityPub</a> specification already since it's based on the pump.io protocol, and I was really excited about said protocol being standardized. So I was participating pretty heavily and I think it just made sense to people in the Working Group for me to join. In fact, that also kinda happened by accident. I couldn't get edit access to the W3C wiki so we were speculating in <code>#social</code> on the W3C IRC server that it might be because I wasn't a "W3C member" or something. So some people at W3C were pinging the sysops team, etc., trying to mark me as a "trusted" user when someone - <a href="https://www.w3.org/People/Sandro/">Sandro Hawke</a>, I believe - said, "the other option is for you to just join the Working Group." To which I said, "well, but I'd have to join as an Invited Expert, and I don't think I qualify as an expert." Chris Webber's response? "You're just as much of an expert as me when I joined!"</p>
<p>tl;dr how in the world did I get here? I tried some software and got annoyed at it, so I just kind of <em>"did some stuff"</em> that led to me doing code reviews. That led to me getting involved in the decentralized social web which led to me <em>"doing some more stuff"</em> that got me involved in standards. Then because of that, I tried to edit a wiki and ended up being invited to apply as a W3C Invited Expert.</p>
<p>I mean, what the hell? Honestly. I can't emphasize enough that I didn't plan ANY of this. It just sort of... happened. And that, I think, is what's so cool about the free software community. It isn't about who you are, where you come from, or what your goals are. It's only about, do you show up? Do you show up and do awesome stuff?</p>
<p>I showed up, kind of by accident, and I now run a decentralized social network with thousands of users called pump.io.</p>
<p>What will happen if <em>you</em> show up?</p>
<p><em>Thanks so much to <a href="https://github.com/anjakefala">Anja</a> and <a href="http://jvns.ca/">Julia</a> for providing feedback on a draft version of this post.</em></p>
<p>[1]: I really hope this explanation makes sense and if it doesn't, I apologize - I use diagrams to explain this in real life.</p>
<p> [2]: Still is, but that should improve now that the technical debt work I've been focusing on for the past year is now <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/express-4.x-in-pump.io-core">basically done</a>!</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/05/pump.io-accident</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/05/pump.io-accident</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[pump.io]]></category><pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2017 19:51:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[RC week 11]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This is week 11 of being at the <a href="https://recurse.com">Recurse Center</a>. </p>
<script async="" defer="" src="https://www.recurse-scout.com/loader.js?t=3d49e64361d4b897ffd2fd56dcd93ca4"></script>
<h2>Day 7</h2>
<p>Arrived ~13:30, departed ~22:45, total time at RC 9h15m.</p>
<p>Brought in cookies and spent a lot of time discussing things on Zulip, honestly. Also figured out when I'm teaching things for Web Dev 101. Spent most of the day, however, writing about <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/default-secure-systems">default-secure systems</a>.</p>
<h2>Day 8</h2>
<p>Arrived ~16:15, departed ~21:00, total time at RC 4h45m.</p>
<p>Arrived super late today because I woke up in the morning, saw the blizzard outside my window, and said "hell no." When I <em>did</em> go in, the blizzard was still going, so I put on snow pants, snow boots, a thick sweater and my winter jacket, and my hat and gloves. Which took a while.</p>
<p>Spent some time discussing 10 different reasons not to put arsenic in the milk with <a href="https://jmeggesto.github.io/">Jackie</a> and <a href="https://github.com/andrewrk">Andrew</a>, which she later wrote a blog post about <a href="https://jmeggesto.github.io/blog/2017/03/poisonmilk">here</a>. Spent the rest of the day doing <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/RFCs/issues/2">maintenance</a> on some Stratic modules. Also spent a little time on the phone with my dad diagnosing my server's disk problems. I had him reseat the SATA cables, with no effect, unfortunately.</p>
<h2>Day 9</h2>
<p>Arrived ~12:15, departed ~23:25, total time at RC 11h10m.</p>
<p>Didn't do a lot of new stuff, but took care of some miscellaneous business. In particular I did some work on polishing <a href="https://github.com/hubot-scripts/hubot-seen">hubot-seen</a>, including putting out a 1.0.0 release (and then a 1.0.1 release when that turned out to have broken the world). In the evening, <em>finally</em> found the bug preventing us from upgrading pump.io to Express 4.x, which was unbelievably satisfying. Turned out that the bug was in some test code, not the application itself, and so I had been misreading the stack trace for <em>months</em>. (The top item was a test file, but I incorrectly assumed that that was just some test code invoking a bunch of internal stuff. Nope.) Also has a meeting with some of the other Winter 1s about feelings and the end of the batch and stuff.</p>
<p>Last but not least, caught up on weekly blogging. (I've been really bad for a while now...)</p>
<h2>Day 10</h2>
<p>Arrived ~11:45, departed ~00:00, total time at RC 12h15m.</p>
<p>Did a ton of pump.io work. I merged the Express 4.x branch, then went in and did a bunch of other more minor dependency upgrades. Also went to a soldering workshop run by <a href="https://github.com/eeclaire">Claire</a> immediately before presenting HTTPS Part 2 in the afternoon.</p>
<p>In the evening, went to presentations and then game night, where I spent the entire time playing poker. I put in $3 and got back $7.95 (read: $8). Sick.</p>
<h2>Friday</h2>
<p>Arrived ~13:30, departed ~21:45, total time at RC 8h15m. As always, Friday doesn't count as a day because RC is technically not in session.</p>
<p>Did some work on improving pump.io's dependency situation. The result is a system that is very, very close to being 100% up-to-date, which I'm <em>super</em> proud of to be honest. That also let me turn on dependency security monitoring through <a href="https://nodesecurity.io/orgs/pumpio/projects/32213bb8-f9a6-4dd0-8fc6-5caa8ea5f8fc">Node Security Platform</a>, with plans to enable <a href="https://greenkeeper.io">Greenkeeper</a> as well. Had the monthly meeting in the middle of all that which went really well and was very productive.</p>
<p>In the evening, went to Bottle Share, then put pump.io on the Linux Foundation's <a href="https://bestpractices.coreinfrastructure.org">best practices badge app</a>, the result of which you can find <a href="https://bestpractices.coreinfrastructure.org/projects/804">here</a>.</p>
<h2>Executive summary</h2>
<p>Well, I got a lot done on pump.io (and Stratic) this week. So it was relatively productive. But I did basically nothing that was personally productive (i.e. that pushed me forward as a programmer). Hopefully next week will go better.</p>
<p>Total time at RC 45 hours 40 minutes; cumulative time 510 hours 30 minutes.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/rc-week-11</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/rc-week-11</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2017 22:49:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[RC week 10]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This is week 10 of being at the <a href="https://recurse.com">Recurse Center</a>.</p>
<script async="" defer="" src="https://www.recurse-scout.com/loader.js?t=3d49e64361d4b897ffd2fd56dcd93ca4"></script>
<h2>Day 35</h2>
<p>Arrived ~13:00, departed ~21:30, total time at RC 8h30m.</p>
<p>Decided (in the morning) to sleep in because honestly, I was just really behind on sleep.</p>
<p>Didn't do a whole lot today. Took care of the monthly pump.io release, but spent most of the day writing <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/driftless-at-1000-mph">Driftless at 1,000 mph</a>. In the evening (i.e. after the Iron Blogger meeting) I spent some time fixing ejabberd's configuration to use the new access control syntax (I'd rewritten the config a while back, but hadn't deployed it yet because it broke logins).</p>
<h2>Day 36</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:40, departed ~23:40, total time at RC 13h0m.</p>
<p>Spent basically all day working on <a href="https://github.com/strugee/realtime.recurse.com">realtime.recurse.com</a>. I (mostly) finished up the bits that watch the filesystem and dispatch events (including the "periodic" submission logic), then started in on an automatic update mechanism. I'm pretty pleased with how it's turning out - I think it's pretty elegant. And, it's secure - updates are required to be cryptographically signed by yours truly. Went out to Black Burger with a <em>bunch</em> of people before going to Fat Cat in the evening. Then came back, worked on the updater a little more, and went home.</p>
<h2>Day 37</h2>
<p>Arrived ~14:40, departed ~23:20, total time at RC 8h40m.</p>
<p>Overslept by accident this morning. Spent a bit of time in the afternoon dealing with email, then focused on realtime.recurse.com - basically I was just working on the autoupater I started yesterday. My Python is <em>definitely</em> improving!</p>
<p>I'm actually really pleased with the updater. It's pretty elegant, I think. Basically whenever the server sees a request coming from the client, it checks the <code>User-Agent</code> header to see if the client's out of date and, if so, sends back an <code>X-Requires-Upgrade</code> header. Upon receiving this header the client will go fetch version information, which it'll use to download and verify an update bundle cryptographically signed by me. Yay for secure updates, and yay for simplicity! (Note that this design basically just reuses the connections the client is already making to the server, so it doesn't have to poll for updates all the time.)</p>
<p>I also spent a couple hours talking with Mikhail, discussing a lot of things - ranging from how Node.js's event loop works to the <code>is</code> keyword in Python to static site generator architecture compared to dynamic site architecture.</p>
<h2>Day 38</h2>
<p>Arrived ~9:50, departed ~23:00, total time at RC 13h10m.</p>
<p>Woke up, completely naturally, around 7 AM despite going to sleep at 3 AM. This was so surprising - and this is a true story - that I thought I had woken up at 7 PM and missed the entire day, including Security Club, Abstract Salad Factory, and Thursday night presentations. I was <em>really</em> mad, honestly. But then I looked at my watch and realized that I was on 24-hour time but it didn't say "19:00" and also my alarms were in the future and my phone was in 24-hour time too and also Anja on Zulip said "?" when I said I'd slept through Security Club. Despite the overwhelming evidence in the end, though, I still had a weird feeling that it was 7 PM. So that's the story of how, for a good 5 or 10 minutes, I genuinely believed I'd slept through the entire day.</p>
<p>Once I got to RC, I spent the morning finally(!) merging in a bunch of upstream <code>ejabberd.yml</code> config changes to steevie's ejabberd configuration, which got me closer to fixing the awful spam problem I have. Then I went to Abstract Salad Factory, followed by Security Club. Then in the afternoon (and after presentations) I started reading <a href="https://www.freebsd.org/">FreeBSD</a> documentation since that's what I'm running my new Tor relay on - as I discovered a couple days ago, my old one apparently got hung during boot and was consuming 100% CPU due to the kernel image being corrupted or something. I chose FreeBSD because a) it's a rock-solid system, b) it's a good opportunity to gain experience with administrating a BSD, and c) it increases the diversity of the Tor network. Also, had a conference call in the afternoon with the <a href="https://www.eff.org/">EFF</a> and Paul from <a href="https://ta3mseattle.org/index.php/Main_Page">TA3M Seattle</a> about TA3M Seattle joining the EFF's <a href="https://www.eff.org/electronic-frontier-alliance">Electronic Frontier Alliance</a>, which was exciting for everyone.</p>
<h2>Friday</h2>
<p>Arrived ~13:00, departed ~22:30, total time at RC 9h30m. As always, Friday doesn't count as a day because RC is technically not in session.</p>
<p>Didn't do a whole lot of coding. Spent a while helping <a href="https://jxself.org/">Jason</a> debug <a href="https://datamost.com/">Datamost</a>'s 3.0.0 upgrade (which apparently broke uploads). Attended presentations for the RC Game Jam, then fixed the documentation that caused Jason's problems. Spent a little bit of time polishing the website and README, too.</p>
<p>In the evening, fixed people being banned from ejabberd MUCs, then proceeded to fix my spam problem. Whoooooo! Then I kept working on my Tor relay.</p>
<h2>Executive summary</h2>
<p>Like any week, this had moments where I wasn't very productive. But overall I think it was pretty good - I made a lot of progress on realtime.recurse.com (and improved my Python in the process), and I made a lot of progress on setting up my Tor relay again (and learned a bunch about FreeBSD in the process). Also, I fixed my ejabberd spam problem. I learned nothing from that, but thank <em>god</em> I did it because the spam problem was honestly <em>awful</em>. The one issue was that I just didn't do a very good job getting up and making it to checkins.</p>
<p>Total time at RC 52 hours 50 minutes; cumulative time 464 hours 50 minutes.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/rc-week-10</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/rc-week-10</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[tor]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2017 18:42:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[RC week 9]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This is week 9 of being at the <a href="https://recurse.com">Recurse Center</a>.</p>
<script async="" defer="" src="https://www.recurse-scout.com/loader.js?t=3d49e64361d4b897ffd2fd56dcd93ca4"></script>
<h2>Day 31</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:30, departed ~15:15, arrived ~17:30, departed ~1:30, total time at RC 8h45m.</p>
<p>There were only two people in my checkin group this morning, and one of them was me. We thought about joining another checkin group, but it was confusing so we did it with just us.</p>
<p>Didn't really do a whole lot for the rest of the day. I fixed up a couple minor problems on strugee.net. Also I finally(!) fully caught up on blogging and went out to lunch with a bunch of people, including <a href="https://www.recurse.com/residents#Nelson-Elhage">Nelson</a>, the new resident. He's awesome. We had some seriously interesting discussions about the recent CloudFlare incident, as well as the work he did while at Ksplice.</p>
<p>Left early to do laundry, then came back for Nelson's talk.</p>
<p>Spent a lot of time in the evening cleaning up the <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/">pump.io homepage</a> - I removed a bunch of duplicated content, reordered the remaining text to put the important stuff first, and imported all the pump.io-related posts on my personal blog into <a href="http://pump.io/blog/">http://pump.io/blog/</a>.</p>
<h2>Day 32</h2>
<p>Arrived ~11:30, departed ~21:40, total time at RC 10h10m.</p>
<p>Missed my checkin by a wide margin because a) after I realized I just couldn't make it by 10:30 I gave up and had a nice relaxed breakfast and b) I looked at checkins.recurse.com and realized that I was the only one in my checkins group.</p>
<p>Went out to Taim for lunch relatively soon after that. Didn't do a whole lot for the rest of the day, honestly - although I did go for a walk to a park with some folks. Also, tested out the Signal videocalling beta with <a href="https://matthewkelsey.com/">Matt</a>, which worked pretty damn well, I gotta say.</p>
<h2>Day 33</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:40, departed ~1:45, total time at RC 15h5m.</p>
<p>I kinda tried to make it in for checkins this morning, but not really because I still hadn't fixed the "I'm the only one in my checkin group" problem. Didn't really do much today, honestly.</p>
<p>Went out to lunch with <a href="https://github.com/ant6n">Ant6n</a> and <a href="https://github.com/andrewrk">Andrew</a> and had a lot of interesting discussions with them, ranging all the way from <a href="http://ziglang.org/">Zig</a> to x86 hardware - did you know that internally x86 is actually essentially a VM implementation?</p>
<p>Spent a lot of time keeping Eliana company in Hopper late in the evening.</p>
<h2>Day 34</h2>
<p>Arrived ~11:05, departed ~17:55, total time at RC 6h50m.</p>
<p>Went to Nelson's "my first kernel module" talk immediately upon arriving at RC, which was <em>awesome</em>. I had some interesting conversations with him afterward, too, where I confirmed a theory I had about some weird btrfs-related behavior I'd seen a long time ago (where I <code>kill -9</code>'d an obviously hung <code>btrfs</code> process, which refused to die anyway). We also spent some time trying to figure out why <a href="http://unix.stackexchange.com/q/345285/29146">benchmarking loopback network performance</a> gave some weird results, which was quite informative.</p>
<p>Didn't do a whole lot after lunch. Left halfway through presentations to go to a play with Ant6n which unfortunately (due to a water incident with the subway system) I didn't quite make it to.</p>
<h2>Friday</h2>
<p>Arrived ~15:10, departed ~23:10, total time at RC 8h0m. As always, Friday doesn't count as a day because RC is technically not in session.</p>
<p>Woke up at a decent time but didn't really bother to get up or do anything, so I arrived relatively late to RC. Spent some time reading TOTP in preparation for the RFC reading group meeting (which ended up not happening) and then went to the RC Game Jam kickoff. Spent most of the rest of the day discussing game design with my team before getting dinner and hanging out in Babbage for Bottle Share Friday, even though there weren't that many of us (particularly since James was doing stuff in Babbage) and we didn't have any bottles to share. Oh well - it was still fun.</p>
<p>Talked with <a href="https://github.com/ebb-tide">Deniz</a> and <a href="http://www.aberke.com/">Alex</a> and some other folks (I've forgotten who, to be honest) before heading home.</p>
<h2>Executive summary</h2>
<p>Most of the "interesting" stuff that happened this week had to do with the resident. Got a little done codewise, but not that much. I'd say this week was 50/50 in terms of productivity.</p>
<p>Total time at RC 48 hours 50 minutes; cumulative time 412 hours 0 minutes.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/rc-week-9</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/rc-week-9</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2017 18:39:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Driftless at 1,000 mph]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Last week I published <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/how-i-passed-2k-github-contributions">How I passed 2k GitHub contributions</a>. This post is, in some ways, the antithesis of that, and it will be very emotional and messy. Here be dragons.</p>
<hr>
<p>Throughout my time at RC I've noticed only one thing is consistently difficult for me: focusing on hard things. Intellectually I love the idea of challenging myself. And I find that when I start to work on things that are new and not easy, it feels good and I tend to keep working on those things, because they're interesting. But starting is something that I just don't do frequently enough, and so I find that I haven't progressed as a programmer nearly as much as I would like to have.</p>
<p>What is productivity?</p>
<p>Merriam-Webster defines it like this:</p>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>
<p>the quality or state of being productive</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>the rate per unit area or per unit volume at which biomass consumable as food by other organisms is made by producers</p>
</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>And "productive" is defined like so:</p>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>
<p>having the quality or power of producing, especially in abundance</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>effective in bringing about</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>a) yielding results, benefits, or profits; b) yielding or devoted to the satisfaction of wants or the creation of utilities</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>continuing to be used in the formation of new words or constructions</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>raising mucus or sputum (as from the bronchi)</p>
</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>By definitions 1-3 I certainly seem to have been productive; I've written a lot of code, much of which is useful. But useful to <em>whom</em>, and for what purpose?</p>
<p>I sometimes feel as if I'm just generating more and more code without any guiding process, as though I'm wasting my time even though concretely I'm getting a <em>lot</em> of things done - driftless even though I'm churning out work at an extremely high rate. Is this <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome">imposter syndrome</a>? Or are my worries legitimate?</p>
<p>Maybe a better way to frame this question is to split it in two - am I being productive for myself, and am I being productive for the community - the two things that are currently important to me personally.</p>
<p>I think I am failing at being productive for myself, in some really important ways. I'm also succeeding in some - for example, I used to wish I had an engine to run my blog, and now I have <a href="https://github.com/straticjs">such an engine</a>. But in others I am failing.</p>
<p>What is the purpose of RC? Why am I here?</p>
<hr>
<p>recurse.com <a href="https://www.recurse.com/about#who-comes-to-the-recurse-center">says this</a> about people who come to RC:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The Recurse Center is for people who want to become better programmers. We are not startup school nor are we a bootcamp: Our focus is helping people become better programmers, not building prototypes, and we're not a training program for web developers.</p>
<p>Because there is no certification or grading, the only reason to come to the Recurse Center is to become a better programmer. As such, you will find kindred spirits and tremendous energy. We look for smart, friendly, self-directed, intellectually curious people who enjoy programming and want to get dramatically better.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>More directly, <a href="https://www.recurse.com/manual">the manual</a> has this to say:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You should be here primarily because you want to become a better programmer and spend the majority of your time here programming and doing things directly related to programming.</p>
<p>Well, we could ask you to be respectful of speakers and keep conversations on-topic in the Recurse Center space during the day (i.e. if you want to take a break and chat about your weekend, go grab a coffee).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>However, as <a href="https://haroldtreen.com">Harold</a> points out, that <a href="https://haroldtreen.com/tech/recurse/2017/01/27/recurse-center-return-statement/">isn't necessarily an accurate picture</a> of what RC is about. I think a lot of what it's really about is the people who are in the space with you. I've sure had a wonderful time with the people. Does that mean I'm "succeeding"?</p>
<p>Then there's the teaching.</p>
<hr>
<p><img src="/images/anja-teaching.jpg" alt="Screenshot of a Zulip message where Anja says &quot;thank you AJ for teaching us so many things. :)&quot;"></p>
<p>This is referring to the fact that I teach at Security Club every week, plus my volunteering to run a workshop or two for Beginner's Club and Web Dev 101.</p>
<p>Practically speaking, I get very, very little out of teaching at RC. Sometimes it helps solidify (or just plain remind me of) the concepts I teach, but this is the exception, not the norm. So in that sense by spending time teaching, I'm "failing" at being productive for myself. But it seems clear to me that people get a lot out of the time I spend, so I seem to be very productive for the community.</p>
<p>Equally importantly I <em>love</em> teaching. I qualified the previous paragraph with "practically speaking" because emotionally teaching is something that's very beneficial to me. Does that mean I'm "succeeding"? Does it mean I'm "failing" and "succeeding" at the same time?</p>
<p>I honestly don't know.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/driftless-at-1000-mph</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/driftless-at-1000-mph</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2017 16:27:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[RC week 8]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>This is week 8 of being at the <a href="https://recurse.com">Recurse Center</a>. </p>
<script async="" defer="" src="https://www.recurse-scout.com/loader.js?t=3d49e64361d4b897ffd2fd56dcd93ca4"></script>
<h2>Day 27</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:35, departed ~0:30, total time at RC 13h55m.</p>
<p>Had a nice discussion about Stratic in my checkin group this morning. After that I went to the Capture The Flag introduction workshop, then spent essentially the entire rest of the day finishing up <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/from-static-to-stratic-part-1">static to Stratic</a> (which included, in a truly horrifying fashion, me rewriting and force-pushing the demo repository's history a good four times or so) so I'd have a post up for the iron bloggers meeting. Also spent some time fixing some bugs in <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/generator-stratic">generator-stratic</a> and published the beta 2 release with those fixes. Closed out the evening by digging into a remark problem where <code>&lt;script&gt;</code> tags would be stripped from posts. Ended up just asking on Gitter.</p>
<h2>Day 28</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:30, departed ~20:40, total time at RC 10h10m.</p>
<p>Continued to investigate the remark problem based on replies received overnight - turns out it was a bug in remark fixed in a release that had gone out the door literally the same day I asked. After that I spent the day upgrading <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/generator-stratic">generator-stratic</a> (which, remember, was originally scaffolded <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2014/12/new-blog-new-site">years ago</a>) to newer and newer releases of <code>yeoman-generator</code> until it used <code>yeoman-generator@latest</code>. Then I spent time adding some basic tests - they're kind of just smoketests for now (are the correct files generated, does <code>gulp serve</code> work) but I <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/generator-stratic/issues/11">intend</a> to expand them. Also moved over some issues to the new <a href="https://github.com/straticjs/RFCs">straticjs/RFCs</a> repository and attended Casual Presentations.</p>
<h2>Day 29</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:50, departed ~20:35, total time at RC 9h45m.</p>
<p>Didn't do a whole lot codewise today. However, I did teach Unix fundamentals for Beginner Club, which went pretty well - I just spent the entire time in the commandline, demonstrating different commands. We spent a little time talking about shell scripting, but not much. I forgot to cover conditionals, which was dumb since they're pretty weird in shell scripting. Spent some time in the afternoon starting a draft of <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/how-i-passed-2k-github-contributions">How I passed 2k GitHub contributions</a></p>
<p>Watched Kiki's Delivery Service in the evening.</p>
<h2>Day 30</h2>
<p>Arrived ~10:35, departed ~00:05, total time at RC 13h30m.</p>
<p>Finished and published <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/02/how-i-passed-2k-github-contributions">How I passed 2k GitHub contributions</a>. Presented <a href="https://strugee.net/presentation-cryptography-basics">cryptography basics</a> at Security Club, then spent a lot of time fixing miscellaneous items on steevie. In particular ejabberd was apparently configured to use a standalone certificate bundle (instead of symlinking to something in <code>/etc/letsencrypt/live</code>) - this was because ejabberd requires the private key and the full chain to be in the same file. TLS certificate renewal didn't properly update this bundle, so XMPP client connections weren't working. ZNC was broken in the same way, so I fixed both of those. I also spent some time setting up a system to publish everything custom in <code>/usr/local</code> <a href="https://github.com/strugee/steevie-usr-local">on GitHub</a> so that it's public and version-controlled. So that's nice.</p>
<h2>Friday</h2>
<p>Arrived ~15:50, departed ~1:00, total time at RC 9h10m. As always, Friday doesn't count as a day because RC is technically not in session.</p>
<p>Came in super late (though I woke up earlier). Almost immediately after that I attended an initial meeting about starting an RFC reading group (an idea I floated on Zulip a couple days ago). Spent most of the day poking at IETF things as well as responding to <a href="https://github.com/hubot-scripts/hubot-seen">hubot-seen</a> PR comments. I just got write access! \o/</p>
<p>Closed out the evening by attending Bottle Share Friday, where I had a long discussion with <a href="http://www.aberke.com/">Alex</a> about running my own email server (which spun off into a discussion of how completely terrible and busted email is), followed by a long discussion about whether Apple's release schedule for Safari and attitude towards new web features and third-party iOS rendering engines is justifiable.</p>
<h2>Saturday</h2>
<p>Arrived ~11:15, departed ~23:30, total time at RC 12h15m. Saturday doesn't count as a day because RC is not in session.</p>
<p>Marathoned Lord of the Rings today. The showing was small and people drifted in and out but most of the time there were a couple people watching, which was fun. The original plan was to watch the director's cut versions, watching The Return of the King on Sunday, but we ended up watching the regular versions because you can't rent the director's cuts off Amazon, and I wasn't about to pay $30 for movies that I <em>already own</em> on DVD back home. We probably would've still watched on Sunday, except that I went out to get pizza for dinnr and found out that it was pouring rain (with thunder/lightning and everything). So I decided we'd watch The Return of the King and wait for the rain to let up, which worked beautifully.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/Husseinfarah93">Hussein</a> came in just as I was about to leave and stated that he almost had a heart attack because he sprinted literally from his apartment to Duane Reade, which truthfully was absolutely <em>hilarious</em>. We had some fun wandering around Duane Reade trying to find soap (which I needed to buy) before we both headed home.</p>
<p>(As a side note, my favorite brand of mac 'n' cheese by far is Annie's, which my local supermarket does not carry. But apparently Duane Reade does!? Wat???)</p>
<h2>Executive summary</h2>
<p>This week was weirdly divided - some parts were hyper-productive and some parts were pretty terrible. I certainly got a lot of work done on Stratic, and I taught a lot. But I didn't really do a good job of working on stuff that pushed my programming abilities forward.</p>
<p>Total time at RC 68 hours 45 minutes; cumulative time 363 hours 10 minutes.</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/rc-week-8</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2017/03/rc-week-8</guid><category><![CDATA[personal]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 14:11:19 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>