<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[strugee.net blog - December - 2019]]></title><description><![CDATA[strugee.net blog - December - 2019]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2019/12</link><generator>stratic-indexes-to-rss</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2023 18:55:45 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://strugee.net/blog/2019/12/index.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><copyright><![CDATA[© Copyright 2012-2018 AJ Jordan. Available under the GNU Affero GPL.]]></copyright><webMaster><![CDATA[AJ Jordan <alex@strugee.net>]]></webMaster><item><title><![CDATA[filter-other-days 1.1.0 and 2.0.0 are now available]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I'm pleased to announce that <code>filter-other-days</code> 1.1.0 and 2.0.0 are now available. In fact, they were both released simultaneously over three weeks ago while I was at <a href="https://seagl.org/">SeaGL</a>, but things at college have been so hectic I'm only just finding time to write about them! If you're not already familiar with <code>filter-other-days</code> - which provides reliable, Artificial Ignorance-compatible logfile date filtering even in the face of unknown formats - I would encourage you to read my blog post <a href="https://strugee.net/blog/2017/10/announcing-filter-other-days">introducing the tool for the first time</a>. Or, if you read this post late enough, you could even watch video of the <a href="https://osem.seagl.org/conferences/seagl2019/program/proposals/682">talk I gave at SeaGL</a>, which talks about <code>filter-other-days</code> before pivoting into a broader discussion of the kind of runaway complexity <code>filter-other-days</code> is designed to address.</p>
<p>1.1.0 and 2.0.0 are both feature releases. Due to <code>filter-other-days</code> 2.0.0 breaking compatibility with OpenBSD, I'm providing 1.1.0 which contains everything that <code>filter-other-days</code> 2.0.0 does <em>except</em> for the feature that breaks OpenBSD support - localization in the logfile filters. (Localization does not and to my knowledge cannot work on OpenBSD because OpenBSD does not support the POSIX features that <code>filter-other-days</code>' localization relies on.)</p>
<p>Here are the highlights of the engineering that both 1.1.0 and 2.0.0 share:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>filter-other-days -d</code> operates on any day instead of the current date on supported systems</li>
<li><code>filter-other-days</code> is portable to OpenBSD, NetBSD, OpenIndiana and OmniOS (i.e. illumos), and Cygwin</li>
<li>GNU <code>seq</code> is no longer required; the only requirement for core functionality is now POSIX</li>
<li>Several bugs have been fixed</li>
<li>Release artifacts are built <a href="https://reproducible-builds.org/">reproducibly</a></li>
<li>Automated testing has been improved</li>
</ul>
<p>Note that <code>filter-other-days -d</code> <em>does</em> require more than POSIX - it needs a system with either GNU <code>date -d</code> semantics or BSD <code>date -r</code> semantics. This is because POSIX does not provide enough support to implement this feature otherwise. If your system does not support either of these, <code>filter-other-days</code> will simply turn the feature off. You can check if <code>-d</code> is available by looking for it in the help output - it will show up only if the system supports it.</p>
<p>In addition to the above, <code>filter-other-days</code> 2.0.0 <em>also</em> includes support for filtering logfiles in different locales. This means that if your system logs things like month names in languages other than English, <code>filter-other-days</code> will now be able to process these logs! <code>filter-other-days</code> will automatically use the C locale (which is mandated to be available by POSIX) and will additionally use the locale defined by the <code>$LANG</code> environment variable, if set. You can also specify more locales to be loaded by specifiying the <code>-l</code> command line flag. <code>filter-other-days</code> extracts the information it needs using specific keywords in the system locales, which means that if you want <code>filter-other-days</code> to load a particular locale to filter with, you need to have that locale installed.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, there's one more complication: some systems are buggy and do not have keywords that properly conform to POSIX. <a href="https://bugs.freebsd.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=237752">FreeBSD 12.0 and below</a> as well as <a href="https://gnats.netbsd.org/cgi-bin/query-pr-single.pl?number=54693">NetBSD</a> are known to have these bugs. Since these systems are relatively popular, I am providing patched versions of <code>filter-other-days</code> that will work around these bugs. You can recognize these versions because they have <code>freebsd</code> in the tarball filename. They will also tell you they've been patched for FreeBSD (and NetBSD) in all relevant places, like the version output and the manpage.</p>
<p>So, to summarize what version to use:</p>
<ul>
<li>If you're on OpenBSD, use 1.1.0</li>
<li>If you're on FreeBSD 12.0 or below, or on NetBSD, use 2.0.0 with FreeBSD patches</li>
<li>Otherwise, use the unpatched 2.0.0 tarballs</li>
</ul>
<p>I hope these releases of <code>filter-other-days</code> are useful to people! I'm super proud of them and I couldn't be more excited for people to try them out. And as always, feel free to <a href="https://github.com/strugee/filter-other-days/issues">report any bugs</a> you find!</p>
]]></description><link>https://strugee.net/blog/2019/12/filter-other-days-1.1.0-and-2.0.0-are-now-available</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://strugee.net/blog/2019/12/filter-other-days-1.1.0-and-2.0.0-are-now-available</guid><category><![CDATA[development]]></category><category><![CDATA[releases]]></category><category><![CDATA[sysadmin]]></category><category><![CDATA[blaggregator]]></category><pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2019 17:45:24 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>